The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
I was curious.
How important do you think the understanding
of computational complexities and complexity theory
is to the understanding of intelligence
and the field of data?
That's a really, I can't remember
anybody asking that question.
What common sense questions are complex?
That would be a, yes?
One of the big insights you propose
is that the simplest problems that we solve
tend to be really complex.
I mean, there's different notions of complexity,
but in a certain way, let's say computation,
a lot of the simplest things like division and language
acquisition are probably much more complex
than a lot of the expertise and problems
that we usually talk about.
Yeah.
Have I shown this slide before?
It was published in the Toshiba Journal of Research
and Development, because I thought of it at some point
when I was in Japan.
Turn your microphone off.
I turned it off?
Yes.
I have some hot melt glue, which I could put my wallet
in the other pocket.
So this isn't complexity, but I think
I talked about this briefly.
The idea is this is one way of classifying problems,
and it's a very naive kind of complexity.
Namely, if you're trying to achieve some situation
or reach some goal, then what method should you use?
And so this is a cute little table
where you just count the number of inputs
and how much effect they have.
And I didn't bring a pointer either.
Oh, well.
Here's a pointer.
So if there are very few causes and each has a small effect,
then it's an easy problem.
I'm not sure of anything to say about it.
If you have a very large number of inputs to a situation
and each has a large effect, then it's probably hopeless,
because if there are n kinds of inputs
and they're all important, then you probably
have to exhaustively look at all 2 to the n cases
to be sure you haven't missed something.
And then here are eight areas of artificial intelligence
for intermediate situations.
So that's a kind of complexity.
But it doesn't say anything about how complex the problem
is, but just what kind of context
is in and how many inputs are involved.
So anyway, I'd like to see a better table
if anybody can think of what's another way of classifying
artificial intelligence problems.
And if you can think of one even dumber than this,
I'd be surprised.
However, if you look at recursive function theory,
then every now and then you run into some wonderful discovery,
like there's one that's attributed
to Friedberg and who was an undergraduate here, which
says that there are problems that there are some not
quite universal Turing machines which still have
unsolvable halting problems.
And these were constructed by sort
of mutilating two universal Turing machines that
are talking to each other and a lot of interesting partial
ordering mathematics, which I don't think I could reproduce.
So there is these wonderful theories
of algorithmic complexity.
How many of you have encountered that field?
There's a problem that quite a few.
My favorite problem is one that I worked on for months
and didn't solve.
And it was proposed by Emil Post in 1923,
I think.
He's a professor at NYU in New York University in New York.
And he had the idea of tag processes.
It's called tag because it's one process chasing another one
and trying to catch up.
And so the idea is you have some string of zeros and ones.
And the process that Emil Post studied,
and I wasted a lot of time on, was this.
You look at the first symbol in the string.
And if it's a 1, then you write 1101 at the end of the string.
But you cross off three of them.
And then if it's a 0, you write 00 and cross off three of them.
It's called the tag problem because you're
wondering if the front of it is going to catch up to the back.
And if there were equal numbers of zeros and ones,
then you'd see that sometimes you're adding three things,
four things, and sometimes you're adding two.
And you're always pulling off three.
So it's sort of crazy.
I don't know what got him interested
in that in the first place.
So this is bad.
It's going to be, oh, we're going to get a lot of 1101.
So it's getting longer if I cross out three at a time.
So if you start with various strings,
sometimes it gets pretty long.
And then it gets eaten away and disappears,
or almost disappears.
Or it keeps getting longer forever.
What's the third case?
The third case would be maybe it gets into a loop
where it stays the same.
If it ever gets back to repeating the same string,
then it'll do that forever.
So Post asked, is there any string
which will grow forever?
And a lot of people have simulated this as far as 10
to the 10th steps.
And they always grew, except for the ones
that stop pretty soon.
So no one knows the answer.
Is there an initial string that grows infinite?
If you want to waste a summer, try
to find either some good theory of that.
Anyway, it's not clear what is the significance of that one.
But it was discovered, partly by me,
that there were tag systems like this that were universal
and could be made to simulate any other machine.
The trouble is you have to use a sort of complicated coding
to encode the problem for a tag process and decode it again.
Anyway, that's an example of a nice computational complexity
problem that's still unsolved.
And one of you might get some sudden insight
and figure out how to.
Yes?
So you mentioned that you helped prove
that there were some universal tag systems.
This is the way that they showed that some 2D cellular
automata are universal by converting it to the tag.
It's pretty similar.
I'm trying to remember the one that I proved was universal.
It wasn't.
It's pretty simple.
But it involved just knocking off two each time.
But it had, I've forgotten how many symbols it needed.
Anyway, I don't think I know any interesting case
where computational complexity has actually
influenced any work on AI.
Have you ever seen any of this?
Recursive function theory is a very beautiful branch
of mathematics.
And it's great fun, sort of like geometry
in that it starts with almost nothing.
And there is quite a lot about it in my old book
on computation.
There's a bit in Kurtzweil's great big book.
But I'm not sure what.
Yeah?
So Watson seems to be a good system
to answer questions.
Why is there an AI division of what intelligent system is?
Because it seems that the computers that we have
and the intelligent systems that we have,
they are good to solve specific problems.
But did we divide the intelligence
into fields that we want to solve?
Because as you said, we have, I don't know,
intelligence maybe can be divided in several pieces.
And maybe we're not trying to solve these parts.
The Turing test says, oh, we need a machine that
wants to imitate the human intelligence or whatever.
But the human intelligence itself
is a bunch of things we can't, I don't know, solve
different problems.
And it seems that there is no division of the intelligence.
Always we are asking, do we have a system that
can achieve human intelligence?
But we don't divide this problem.
How can we solve this big problem
if we don't divide this problem into smaller problems which
people can tackle?
Well, there are lots of things that we
have programs for that people can't solve.
So I'm not sure that the word intelligence
makes much sense anymore.
It's like consciousness.
Maybe at any particular moment, you're
talking about five or 10 or 20 different things.
For example, Watson is very good at getting
the name of a movie actor from a few clues.
But can it do any common sense reasoning?
You've been studying it a bit, Henry.
I think it can a little bit, not to the extent that we like.
But Eric Euler, who was part of the Watson team,
and he's been working on common sense knowledge.
So I think he probably does have some capability,
but not a lot.
It'd be nice to know more about it.
I haven't read what they've published.
But the trouble is they're not in business for their health.
And why don't we divide intelligence,
the problem of intelligence, into some problems
and try to tackle them?
Well, there's Howard Gardner with his.
Like, they do, I don't know, vision, I don't know.
I mean, that's not like AI we should do, right?
No one's trying to solve everything at once.
People are working on specific subproblems.
Yeah, but are they integrated?
Are which integrated?
I mean, can we integrate these subsystems?
Eventually, hopefully, maybe.
Let's see here.
In what sense are people integrated?
No, no, no.
Can we integrate the subsystems?
Like, OK, somebody's solving, like, the problem of vision.
Well, they would have to know about each other,
what the other subsystems can do,
so that they would get an idea to make an estimation,
or for example, Watson would be able to decide,
oh, this is something that I cannot handle.
I have to give it to this other program.
So you need to have a good classification system
that the more sub-systems, they would be able to talk to each
other, so I don't know if that's helpful.
Yeah, that's what I try to approximate
with these critics, which you have a bunch of systems.
I guess we don't know much about how parallel things
are in the human brain.
But presumably, some particular small number of processes
are going on any time, maybe a large number
of very trivial processes like, well, I don't know what like.
But my picture of the integration in human psychology
is by having these critics, so that whatever processes are
going on, you have other processes that
don't understand the ones that are actually doing the work,
but have some superficial assessment,
like this one is using up half of my sugar,
or it's wasted a lot of time, and it
hasn't solved its quota of problems
in the last five minutes, or five seconds,
or who knows, 100 milliseconds.
In the early work of Newell and Simon,
they did lots of experiments with stopwatches and instruments
to see how long people took to react to things.
And they concluded that for a conscious operation,
by conscious, I mean something that a person might actually
have a word for and mention.
Because when they get them solving problems,
they train their subjects to keep talking all the time
about what they're doing.
And so Newell concluded that there
were some operations that took about a 30th of a second.
And those were things on the verge of what
we might call consciousness.
And that there must have been other operations that
were two or three milliseconds that the person couldn't
talk about.
But he was studying operations which we understand very well,
like how you add up columns of numbers
and just little arithmetic things,
and timing these people with stopwatches
for endless periods.
And so he found that if you ask somebody to how much is eight
and three, the person would say 11.
And another time later, you'd ask them
how much is three and eight.
And he discovered, Newell reports,
that it usually takes people noticeably longer
in milliseconds to say that three and eight is 11
than to say that eight and three and 11.
And he fitted this to data and concluded
that when you add three and eight, you go three,
and then you count up 24 milliseconds.
And he concluded that you're doing addition one at a time
in three millisecond chunks.
Well, that's sort of nutty.
If you do enough experiments, I guess you can prove anything.
But where is all this going?
I think the, well, what would Watson
need to understand why you can pull something with a string,
but you can't push it?
And it seems to me if you could find a story in which
a famous actor came to a terrible fate
because he was pushing a string instead of pulling it,
Watson would get that right away because it would be
at the top level of your description of the movie.
But the question is, how much progress
are they making toward ordinary common sense thinking
and reasoning?
And I presume, as Henry Lieberman said,
if Eric Mueller is actually in the middle of that,
then they have a first class AI researcher
because he did a lot of interesting things
before he disappeared from view.
Any other?
Where else is anything on that scale happening?
I bet that's the largest AI program in the world,
except maybe there are a couple of secret ones
in the classified.
It would be nice to believe that there were something
like the RAND Corporation actually
doing exciting, profound things for the benefit of all of us.
But I think I mentioned that I used
to hang around there in the middle of the 1950s,
and it was full of wonderful basic research.
But then things gradually got classified.
Anyway, I'd like to see a few more diagrams like this,
just trying to make commonsensical classifications
of AI problems and maybe figuring out where people are.
Are there some fairly important basic problems
that nobody's working on because they just
haven't formulated them in a way that they
can get people to work on them?
I look back at 1970, and here's a program
that has a bunch of assumptions about the physical world
and understands how to generate subgoals from goals
in various ways and keep track of things.
So everyone who's interested in AI
should read the PhD theses in the early 70s
by Jerry Sussman and Pat Winston and Terry Winograd.
And I'd say each of those theses has
maybe a dozen lines of research that nobody
has followed very far because, like any other field,
AI has run into large-scale global funding fads.
And there was a decade in which rule-based systems were
virtually the only thing people worked on,
and they discovered a certain amount.
So lots of rule-based systems are out there in the world
doing useful things.
They never got to make three or four levels of criticism
in those systems.
And so to me, that area sort of reached
a certain point of economic usefulness
but almost disappeared from the horizon of research.
What's that project called, ACT?
What's the big rule-based system project that I'm
asking Pat Winston there?
I'm not sure what you were talking about.
ACT-R, is that what you were talking about?
Yeah.
ACT-R, yeah.
That had a lot of people all over the country
sort of participating.
And I wonder if anything ever.
Well, it's a descendant of SOAR, which
is the other big production rule system.
That was in the Will Simons.
And they keep refining those and adding this and adding that.
But it doesn't seem to come up to the surface
and announce a breakthrough of any sort,
or at least I haven't heard of any.
Well, the problem is it's a little hard
to tell whether it's a cognitive architecture
or a bad programming language.
You mean in order to get it to do something,
they have to do something specifically for that?
So it didn't just fall out.
The programming language is pretty awkward.
And because it doesn't actually do anything by itself,
it is a programming language.
So is there anything comparable to that?
Are there any big rule-based systems which are not
a programming language?
After all, programming languages are just fancy things that say,
if this, do that.
So if you try to tell us something
deeper rather than a rule-based system in FORTRAN,
it's more of a mindset than a set of criteria.
Of course, this was written in Lisp, this Winograd thing.
I don't know if one of the things about Lisp, which
is potentially important, is that the underlying language
is so simple that it's fairly easy to write programs in Lisp
that make up, that write programs in Lisp.
I think it's probably almost impossible to do
that in a language like C++, because there's
a compiler in the way.
And of course, you can have an operation saying,
compile what I just said.
But I doubt if one of the features of Terry Winograd's
program is that you could tell it to build something.
And then the course of building things,
you'd give it a goal, and it would generate subgoals.
And it could answer questions about why it did something.
So for example, if you built some sort of tower
and you asked it, why did you move the green block?
Winograd's program could articulate that and say,
I had to move it to clean the surface of the large red block
so that I could put this other thing on it.
And so there you had a program that, at one level,
it's full of rule-based rules.
But it only fires up a rule when it
has a goal and some knowledge base says,
a way to achieve that goal is to apply this transformation.
Then what Winograd's program did was
it kept a record of each of the goals that it had generated
and each of the subgoals for that goal
that it had generated in order to achieve it.
And then the great achievement, which
was that he got enough English language idioms
into the operating system for that,
that if you asked it a question about why it did something,
it would actually give the same answer
that a person or a child would on the whole.
So the question to ask is, if they did so much in 1970,
what happened in the 40 years since then?
And it's quite a mystery.
He had six graduate students who tried to improve the thing,
and they all changed their thesis and advisor
at some point.
Do you remember?
What's the explanation why this never went further?
Pat's thesis was in the same year.
I guess I think the explanation is, in part,
that the Bloch's world presented no serious representation
problems.
So moving from the Bloch's world to some other world,
you suddenly have to deal with all kinds of things
that the Bloch's world doesn't have, like I, you, and goals.
It didn't.
Emotional goals, things like that.
OK, there wasn't anything in the Bloch's world
that had goals.
Right.
Well, there should be something in between,
because you're going all the way to people
like Romeo and Juliet.
Have you tackled them, or are you in Macbeth?
I'm still in Shakespeare.
Mostly Macbeth and Helen, which was so parallel.
Of course, you could switch to Leonard Bernstein.
And what was that play called?
West Side Story.
I was born on the west side, but it
didn't have any gangs then that are 86th Street.
Well.
So part of the topic, I guess you seem to think of tragedies.
I'm curious what makes the story easier or harder to analyze,
and why you picked the ones you didn't.
Well, why do they pick the ones I did?
I mean, Macbeth and Shakespeare, the stories.
Let's see.
There's an official answer and a real answer.
I'm not sure what the real answer is.
I've articulated the official answer so often,
I'm beginning to believe it.
But the official answer is that Shakespeare plots
have all the kinds of things you find in any human situation.
Or any situation that's even the situation
between organizations or countries.
You get everything.
You get the greed.
You get revenge.
You get all kinds of jealousies, threats, and all sorts
of things you would want to be able to deal with.
So that's the official answer.
The real answer is I kind of like those things.
And the plots are familiar to you,
so I didn't have to go out.
But it's really true.
If you take any of those Shakespearean plays,
they're all about the human condition in various ways.
And through three of them, you can cover a lot of ground.
And I'm presuming that if I can deal with the plot in Macbeth,
then I can deal with a lot of stuff.
You probably deal with a lot of other Shakespeare plays.
They run very similar.
If you look at the plot of Hamlet and Macbeth,
they're almost identical.
I sometimes forget who's who.
Did they all kill their mother?
They all had them.
The king was always killed by somebody
and killed by somebody else in revenge.
It was remarkably easy to see analogies.
Yes, it's been happening in the last months out in real life,
almost as though they read the stuff.
But now you're allowed to kill them with drones.
It's pretty serious.
Well, what would you like to see the AI people working on?
A robot baseball player?
We should finish up soccer first.
Is soccer hard?
It's harder than robots.
I was just talking to Hakey about this.
There was an AI researcher named Woodrow Bledsoe who
did some of the best early work in visual pattern recognition.
And he defeated all of us at ping pong.
And one day I asked him, how come you're so good at ping pong?
And he said, I don't think I'm any better than any of you,
except I look five steps ahead.
And we'll never know if he just made that up.
Yeah?
So you asked what AI people should work on every time.
So really classically, AI is studied
for linguistic capability.
And in recent times, we've been doing
that other senses should also be taking into account.
Vision for a long time has been included.
But I don't know, every time we talk about this,
I always think about, what about other senses?
Does anyone do anything with olfactory sense?
Because that can have a big effect on memory, right?
You can smell something and then have this memory that's
strongly associated with it.
So I think that probably a lot of senses
have something interesting about it.
Some interesting component of intelligence in them.
And I wonder if anyone just has done any of the,
if anyone has tried to touch at least on all the senses
and on what they could possibly achieve.
It's funny, because the olfactory thing,
I don't know what to say, because as far as I know,
it's just a bunch of chemical detectors.
But you could say that about almost anything, I suppose.
Well, the interesting thing to me is they're all coupled.
So a smell can remind you of something
that you experienced 30 years ago.
And sometimes a memory can make you,
if you remember something, you can kind of
experience the smell, even though it might not exist.
Have you ever had that phenomenon?
Some Microsoft researcher works on the sense of smell
in lobsters.
And he said that the organs are almost the same as in ours.
But of course, you can't say much about a system
from the primary detectors.
The question is what you do with the stuff.
Well, it seems to me that the important thing
about all the senses is that they give us some access.
They give us some mechanism that allows
us to build up a model of stuff that happens in the world.
So if you don't have vision, you substitute touch,
and you still get the idea that two solid objects can't
intersect each other, and things fall.
Yes, I know people who've lost their sense of smell.
There's some virus infections that do that.
And they miss it a bit, but they're not hugely handicapped.
What?
You can get a huge stomach ache.
If you eat the wrong thing?
Yeah, because then you'll start eating more than food.
So I guess you should be.
You make sure that the can isn't under pressure.
Yes, we make sure that you only buy things from supermarkets
that have sell-by gates in them.
Sell-by.
So maybe we won't have a sense of smell in 100 years.
I don't think anybody's built a good smell detector yet.
When people are trying to create soccer robots that play soccer,
I believe they have problems identifying the ball
if the lights are changing.
And I think that this is a big problem.
Do you believe that's a problem because the algorithms that we
have, they are bad?
Or it's just like the sensory that we have is bad?
For example, Kinect, they used a different type of sensory
to see people, like 25 people.
Maybe it's just a problem with the sensory that we have.
Because the algorithms, they seem pretty good.
Is the Kinect the one that outlines your posture?
It's a great gadget.
Well, don't get me started on sports.
If you look at the world budget for various activities,
it adds up to more than 100%.
But how much?
What fraction of the gross world product
goes into sports and activities like that?
That gets back to the, what are we
going to do with all the people now
that we have 7 billion of them?
And I'm pretty sure that the biologists will find ways
to treat or slow down most of the degenerative diseases
in the next 50 years, say.
People should be living for about 200 years.
And what will we get them to do?
I just gave a lecture to some other people.
Wow.
And there's a scene in 2001 where the pod comes back
to the spaceship.
And it turns the handle on the door and opens the door.
And I was very impressed.
And the next time I saw Kubrick, I said,
how did he get the thing to actually work?
And he looked at me as though I were an idiot.
And he said, we did that with stop action.
And then somebody on the other side of the door
turned the doorknob.
But I would like to see better robots.
And something like this could be,
we could make these and throw them up to the moon.
And the idea here is, let's make a robot out
of very simple modules.
So you see, there's only two kinds of things here.
There are these hinges and these rods.
And they have some kind of motor in them.
And if we could fabricate them to be pretty reliable
and ship up a truckload of them and drop it on the moon,
and they could each have a solar cell or two,
because you don't mind if it takes
10 minutes to move a few inches, then the idea
is, if you had enough of these, like four or five,
then if any one of them broke, two of the others
could take it apart and fix it and replace the parts.
And for the price of one shuttle flight or two,
we could have robots on the moon for the next 20 years.
What are they doing instead?
They're still planning more manned space expeditions
at enormous expense.
And we may not see them in our lifetimes.
NASA is going.
As you can see, I don't have a lecture.
OK, but.
I've got a question.
So I was reading Sussman's Hackberg.
And I noticed that initially, the question that
was asked, and this is from GPS, Hacker, and NOAA,
and Interplan, was they attempted a theory of bugs.
But very soon, I noticed that the question
changed the planning.
And then just planning, in general, search and planning.
And then there was no mention of bugs.
There were ideas of critics and stories,
but that died in like 10 years.
And it seemed like the focus switched to planning.
And the thought I had was maybe it's
what question you ask dictates the direction in the next few
decades you're probably going to take.
And the question I had was, both in Push's thesis and in Hacker,
there's an attempt to build a library of critics.
So there are bugs.
There are patches in the library, which probably look up.
Given A representation, we have this library.
Maybe when we hit some threshold for this,
especially when we're moving from something
like a Blocks world to the real world,
if that library keeps growing, maybe it's
an expensive process.
Maybe we want to use that library
to create a new representation on the fly.
Does that make sense to you?
Well, of course, most representations
are worse than the one you have.
It's a great question.
How often, where do we get our representations?
Do teachers have the idea in grade school or nursery school
of what the children are doing?
And I'm not sure that we.
What do you learn in education school?
Is it still conditioned reflexes,
or is there some cognitive psychology?
And do modern cognitive psychology people
have anything like the representation theories
that AI people have?
The whole thing seems so muddy to me.
I asked the other day how many of you
have taken a psychology course.
It wasn't many, a few.
Do they talk about representations,
or are they still in the world of optical illusions
and conditioned reflexes and things like that?
They weren't supposed to find words to mean other words,
but aren't actually saying anything.
Well, I hope that gets back to the.
Well, representations, the idea that we all
learn about vectors, that's elementary physics nowadays,
the idea that vector calculus is only
from the time of Willard Gibbs, 1880.
Can you look up Gibbs?
So how come humankind didn't invent a lot of mathematics
between the time of Archimedes and Gauss?
Gauss is about 1840, and there are
a bunch of mathematicians scattered in those periods.
But the modern representations in mathematics, most of them
are only about a century or a little more
than a century old.
So every child invents a lot of new representations,
but we don't know much about what they are.
I guess Piaget is the 1930s, the first psychologist
to try to make effective theories
and prove them by experiments on young children,
figure out how they represent things.
Yeah?
The private computer in it says,
Gibbs developed vector analysis from 1880, 1884.
Isn't that something?
Now, what did Descartes do?
He got the coordinates.
Apparently, quaternions existed before then,
and some other outgrowth calculus.
Yeah, the quaternions were a beautiful dead end.
And if Hamilton had invented vectors instead,
he might not have been able to handle rotation so well.
But all the rest of physics would have been better off.
How many of you have ever used a quaternion?
For graphics?
They have amazing property that they only
work in three dimensions, too.
So they're no good for relativistic space-time
and things like that.
It's very strange.
Help?
Yeah?
STUDENT 1.
There's a study for taking newborn infant
and place them on a table top for the first time,
and they crawl to the edge.
They won't fall off.
They'll see the edge and crawl back.
They'll never see the edge.
Do you think this is either some innate representation,
some ability to model, and a primitive physics simulation
already happening?
Or do you think this is sort of a hard-coded edge detector?
Or are they just lucky?
Well, if you look at a mountain goat,
it gets born and drops out, and it
starts to walk in about five minutes,
and then it can follow its mother
and knows where to get milk.
And when it comes to a crevasse, I
get this from Seymour Papert.
I haven't seen it myself.
But the very first time the baby goat comes to a crevasse,
it goes up and around and comes down again.
The mother steps across, and the fairly newborn baby
is following her around.
STUDENT 1.
I don't think they know exactly where to go to get milk.
Maybe they use smell.
STUDENT 1.
I once saw a newborn goat go back and forth
between the front lines and the back lines.
I once saw a newborn cocoa back and forth
between the front legs and the back legs.
I'm sure of exactly what you have to search for.
Somebody put this movie of a giraffe being born on the web.
And have you seen that recently?
It's just spectacular, because the things
are so incredibly awkward.
But after about 10 minutes, it keeps trying to get up.
And after about 10 minutes, it manages to get up and walk.
And sort of like juggling, it's really just about to fall over.
But anyway, so it looks clear that those things that
happened a few minutes after birth,
there hasn't been time for much trial and error.
But when you think about it, getting food
is the most important thing in the universe.
And so you could afford to.
The system has to put priority on staying
alive for the first hour, so that you
can start to learn after that.
So still, it would be nice to know how those circuits work
and what is it that's built in.
And are your later learning mechanisms
mutated copies of the built-in ones at first?
Yes.
Is that still there?
No.
How about a five-minute break?
I'm running out of voice.
There were a lot of discussions.
Anyone want to report on one?
We were talking to Sharad, and we were talking about bugs.
And when we talked about, I was describing a system
that one of my students, Alex Fay, worked on
that tried to understand bugs in web procedures,
like you were ordering on Amazon.
And it used common sense knowledge to say,
OK, the parts of the purchase are selection of the book,
maybe you want to buy, payment, delivery.
And then it said, OK, how do we tell if something went wrong?
And so then you could grade it down and say
that if the order got in correctly,
you would have got a receipt.
If the delivery happened, then you
would have got a FedEx tracking number,
and then the system could check these things automatically.
So in some sense, that's a little bit like Hacker,
having to catalyze with different bugs
and using common sense knowledge to break it down
and understanding if something went wrong.
So I think those are systems that
are kind of like end-user debugging,
so they're debugging without actually having
the program to be bugged.
So then we were talking more generally
about just the idea of building people's knowledge.
There was a lot of this AI stuff generated in the early days,
but nobody could have time to explore
all the consequences of it.
So a lot of things got lost, and certain things got trendy
and maybe not always the right things.
But still, there's a lot of stuff out there
that could be built on.
And part of doing interesting research
is understanding what's the really important stuff
to build on, even if other people don't
think it's fashionable.
And then you can be innovative by building on that stuff.
MARVIN MINSKY It's interesting if can you
think of problem solving as debugging,
because sometimes people think of knowing
what to do and planning.
But if you think of that Newell and Simon general problem
solver, every step is, what's the difference between what
I want and what I got?
And so you could think of the GPS as doing nothing
but debugging.
It's actually good at debugging, because if you get it off
track, then it tells you how to repair it.
But a higher level one is, you might
have spent too much time debugging something
that was just a minor part.
Maybe if you fixed something else,
this bug wouldn't have happened anyway.
Is that a theory of problem solving?
Well, I think one important thing about problem solving
is keeping track of what depends on what.
So things like truth maintenance systems,
that's what they're all about, is trying to keep.
So if you know what depends on what,
then you can trace back for debugging.
Are there any systems?
Yes, what do companies do when they get complaints?
Do they have systems?
They have a phone call to India, and they tell you,
you can't help, they can't help you.
They give you another number to call.
Funny story is that I had for one of the call to help
customers, went to India, and this person picked it up
and said, do you have this manual?
I said, yes, I do.
He said, could you look at this chapter and this section?
Okay.
And then they said, can you look for your problem
in that section?
And I said, great.
So after like 15 minutes, I ended up fixing it myself.
Just didn't know where the manual was.
I could have done it myself.
So sometimes that happens.
On that topic, does it make sense to ask how genes represent
mistakes?
Genes?
Genes.
Is there an idea of, is there an error in mutation or something?
Well, of course, every gene that's selected
is selected because the parent managed
to solve some problem that the others didn't solve, I suppose.
That's a great question because I've been complaining
that evolution has this big bug.
Namely, it doesn't remember why the losers died.
So there are lots of minor bugs in the genetic system.
And I think that's a great question.
You could call them bugs.
But when you have a population of animals
and it gets too cold, then some of them
die out because they didn't eat enough before it got cold
or whatever.
And evolution doesn't keep any record of that.
But on the other hand, you could say
that all the genes you do have are
ones that corrected some bug.
So in that sense, it remembers how to solve the bugs,
but it doesn't remember what the bugs were.
So could you make an evo- But to make an evolutionary system
that kept records of why the losers died,
wouldn't that take a higher level language or something?
Maybe there's no way to evolve such a system.
I mean, could have a system that reversed engineers
based on what did survive, what the mistakes were?
You could have to think, keep two copies of the genomes.
And when you have children, you have one of each.
And well, it's too complicated.
So when we make artificial evolution,
we can probably make the thing millions of times
more efficient by keeping a moderate size
record of what caused fatalities.
Of course, that's what medical records are for,
but they don't get back into the genetic system yet.
Doesn't that depend a lot on text?
For instance, something may be beneficial during an ice age.
But if you institutionalize that,
then when you're living in a tropical jungle,
it could be to your detriment.
I was just thinking of ice age because of what's-his-name's
book.
So you'd have to keep copies for millions of years
and store all the descriptions of environments.
Or else you have that same genetic mutation
occurring over periods of time.
And when it's beneficial, you keep it.
And when the circumstances aren't right for it,
then it goes away with the idea that it might
be able to come back later.
So that's, in fact, what we do when
we have historians and society.
And it might not make any sense to try
to build it into a low-level genetic system.
Just carry books around.
Well, how long will we be able to read those books?
Because a language from 1,000 years ago
is still, I think, only specialized people can read
very, very old Germanic languages, for example.
Modern English speakers cannot, for certain.
So all of our interpretation of those old texts
that were how to avoid people who come at you with bears
or swans or whatever have evolved as well.
How does the technology work?
The culture or is it an important place?
Well, I think things like the iPad are going to.
I was just thinking, my wife was involved
with some children who were carrying
30% of their weight in books in elementary school.
It's incredible how heavy.
They don't even have wheels on their book bag.
But we could re-engineer the nervous system
to have gigabytes of storage.
And then evolution could keep lots of records.
I want to know what was being said up there.
Is anyone?
Were you talking to Pat?
A little bit about complexity and also
about storytelling, just some current topics
and what his lab is working on.
For example, how can you teach if you're going to?
People have different models.
So any understating assumptions, something
that you might be taking as propaganda
or maybe taking something for a less malicious way.
What time is his class?
I think I should be sitting in on it.
I'm not sure.
Except before I'm not sure.
Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 10 AM.
It's not so bad.
Yeah.
What?
Lectures are only Monday and Wednesday.
And then Friday, there's a problem solving session.
It started out, so Fridays were lectures.
And then we used to do less lectures at the end.
But there's not much left, so.
That's the way it always seems.
Yeah?
So I missed a lecture last week.
Did we talk about maybe interesting past projects
for the class?
We didn't.
Maybe can you think of some good ones?
I guess Justin isn't here tonight.
I hate to say it, but the best projects
were in the days when you could have
an incomplete for a whole year.
I think now it's, what is it, the third week of the next term?
Yeah.
Yeah, I had some great papers that came a year later.
But somebody in the administration
decided that incompletes had to be completed.
Have you seen any good projects?
Because nobody's written them yet.
The term project.
I'll try to find some from previous years.
Maybe we can get permission to make a book of them.
The other thing to be focused on,
there seems to be a preference for some engineering
deliverables as well, like some code or program.
Not necessarily.
Hi.
Well, there was a year or two when
Bo Morgan was one of the TAs, and he
was developing a programming language
and wanted to get people to do projects in that language.
But it wasn't such a good idea, because he
kept changing the language.
Yeah.
What's the best language?
Well, if you're going to, yeah, if you're going to have, which?
Vigour.
If you're going to have reflective thinking,
then can you do it with the same language at each level?
Because if you don't, how many words were there in Latin?
Is it a big language?
Depends on how you count.
If you count all the conjugations,
that would be two or nine to two, right there.
When I graduated from Harvard, you had a choice of a BA or a BS,
and you could get a BA if you had credit in Latin, which
I had from grade school.
But I never understood a word of it, hardly.
People said, if you learn Latin, then it
will be easier for you to learn French and Spanish and Italian
and all of those.
And after a while, I suddenly realized
that if I had learned French or Spanish or Italian,
then it would be easier to learn Latin.
I confronted the teachers with that,
and they had no good answer.
And besides, it should have been Greek,
because Latin is full of pretty good stuff,
but it's not the only thing that's good.
Greek has Aristotle.
Yeah?
I know Latin pretty well.
The thing I find it most practically useful for
is I'm taking intro to neuroscience,
and there's a lot of different neuroscience
where you have to memorize all of them.
And almost all are from Latin.
And so I can memorize them based on associations
like dorsal.
Oh, I know that means back, so I know that's the back direction.
And like every word, I only remember
because I know what it means.
Otherwise, just having to memorize the words
would be way more hard.
That reminds me of, I guess it's my wife Gloria
is a physician, and she once had a Greek patient, I think.
And the patient said, what's wrong with me?
And she said, you have gastroenteritis.
And he said, I know that, but what's wrong with me?
And she realized that that was a non-diagnosis
that doctors use to make themselves feel
that they know what's happening.
So have you used it ever?
The Latin.
I mean, I use it for my just description.
I also, I mean, I don't think things
need to have practical value to have utility.
I enjoy reading Latin.
Well, what are the best stories?
Are there any good plays in ancient Latin?
There are some, yeah.
Mostly reading poetry.
Poetry.
But they don't rhyme, do they?
Because the endings are all the same.
Yeah, they generally don't rhyme.
But it's called poetry.
They're very strict meterless.
OK.
A fair amount of the society of mind is in iambic tetrameter.
I just found it was easier to think rhythmically sometimes.
It's very strange.
I'm not sure it does any.
If you don't know that there's a meter,
it certainly doesn't help understanding anything.
But I guess in poetry, if you're skillful,
then you're seeing analogies because the emphasis,
emphases are in similar places in different sentences.
So you're constructing a network of similarities
beyond the meanings of the words,
just from the places where the meter hits.
Like this rap is very popular.
And that's Alexander Pope.
Have any of you looked at any of him?
It's all couplets, rhyming couplets.
And it's exactly like rap, except without the bad music.
Oh, well.
A little earlier, we speculated that pre-engineering
can bring in gigabytes of memory.
And to some extent, we already have that
with very slow lookup times.
So I was wondering if you had any commentary
on how we could improve artwork tools, computers or otherwise,
to help people solve problems and be more intelligent.
Do you think these are proceeding
in the right direction?
Do you think there's other areas of innovation
that are lacking?
Well, I think the web is evolving.
Things like Google are getting to be quite remarkable.
And lately, I've been using the Dragon query language.
And the things are remarkable.
If you ask Dragon a question, it goes to Google
and makes up a pretty good query.
And just about every time I've tried it in recent weeks,
the answer to, where is the biggest island
with a volcano or blah, blah, whatever it is,
it comes right up on the first page.
So I suppose that there will be some very crude thing sometime
in the next decades where you put a bunch of sensors
over one of the speech are
that you can't do with a hand.
Of course, two hands is better than.
But I think getting outputs from the brain
to go into memory devices and feeding them back
into the brain, that's going to become
commonplace at some point.
But we first have to find out how to do it at all,
and then how to implant these things without a big operation
and infection risk and all that.
Yeah?
People currently are burdened with these implants
where they get magnets installed near their ankles.
People get magnets installed near their ankles.
So they can start feeling.
They feel slightly when there's a magnetic attraction
between the magnets in their legs and something.
And so they start developing a sort of magnetic sense.
And then apparently, people report
that even if they get these magnets removed,
they still sort of retain the magnetic sense,
which is pretty weird.
Sounds weird.
Can they tell which way is north?
I don't think so.
I think they can tell when they're around objects
that the magnets will be attracted to.
You certainly could make a magnetic sensor
and put it anywhere in the body connected
to a couple of nerves.
And then you'd know which way is north all the time.
Do you remember?
People who made a belt with a compass
and it had a bunch of solenoids in it,
and it sort of poked you at whatever part of your waist
was pointed north.
After a while, people would sort of no longer
notice the poking and just know which way is north.
Oh.
And sort of get incorporated, in a sense.
My friend Oliver Selfridge, who died recently,
was a pioneer in cybernetics and AI.
And he always knew where north was.
And it turned out, I traveled around with him some.
And whenever he went in a building after a while,
and he always knew where north was,
but I noticed that he would always go into some office
with a window and straighten out the secretary's flowers.
He knew the names of all flowers, also in Latin.
So apparently, he felt uneasy when
he was losing track of direction.
And he'd go to a window.
And before he went in a building,
he'd memorize the big features.
So.
Did it work in this building, because I always get lost?
I had the idea of chiseling little arrows pointing north.
Are there any vandals among us?
It would really be useful.
The Muslims never get lost, because they always
know which direction they're going.
The bud?
The Muslims never get lost, because they
know always which direction the neck is.
Oh, right.
Yes, I think there should be little arrows pointing north
in every room.
The first time I visited a Muslim country,
I noticed that every time I stayed in a hotel room,
there was an arrow on the ceiling of the hotel room.
Oh, on the ceiling?
On the ceiling, yes.
Where you can't raise it.
Yeah.
And if that's the way it told you, we'd echo it.
We could do that.
In fact, if we had a point to Mecca instead of north,
then nobody could criticize us.
Right.
So what's exactly the opposite of Mecca?
What's on the other side of Mecca?
The ocean?
Other side of what?
On the other side of Mecca, the ocean.
Yeah, yeah, so I was just thinking
that there is a point where Mecca is in all directions.
And how can you then go, OK, maybe I should go there?
That's not true, because within the face of YQ,
there is an integrity inside.
I think wherever you are, the probability is about 80%
that the opposite is ocean.
Unless you're in the ocean.
Well, it's still 80%.
This is a water planet.
We could make a little gun that just pops them up there,
and it would take them weeks to get maintenance done.
It would take them weeks to get maintenance to remove it.
Do you think nobody wants to watch something in Aspen?
I haven't heard any reports.
Hey, could we get Eric Muller to give us a talk?
Well, we could invite him to give a different talk,
and then ask questions.
It's been 8.59 for a whole minute.
There's still time for a question.
No, nope.
Thank you.