The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
So everyone's working on papers, I suppose.
When are they due in?
They're due on Sunday.
Horrors.
Well, when I went to graduate school,
it was at Princeton in the math department.
And there were all sorts of courses
given by very good professors, because I
think I've mentioned this.
This is sort of 1950, and the universities in the United
States were, at least the science departments,
were filled with great mathematicians and physicists
and people like that who had been extracted from Europe
because of World War II.
And the math department at Princeton
was very, very, very exciting because of the,
if you had a question, you had a very good chance
that the world's leading authority on that subject
would be in the next room or two.
I was interested in the theory of knots,
and there was a Professor Ralph Fox, who
was one of the world's experts on knot theory.
And in fact, he was so good at it that I gave up.
This is a nice, important thing to keep in mind.
Always be ready to give up if there's someone
doing something better than you and find the right niche.
But anyway, they had courses, and you
would register for courses, and everyone
got an A in all courses.
I'm sorry.
There were no grades when I got there
because Professor Lefcets didn't like the idea of grading
people, and he was head of the department.
And his feeling was that if somebody wasn't doing good work,
then it wasn't that person's fault.
It was the fault of the admissions committee.
And if anybody got through the hurdles to get there,
then they were assumed to be mathematicians,
and that was that.
But after a couple of years, the provost of the university
got annoyed with the math department,
and he sent down a message that there would have
to be grades in every course.
And Lefcets said, OK.
He didn't believe in fighting when
there was a good alternative.
The alternative was everybody got A's in every course,
whether they took the course or not.
And I think the end of the story is
that when he retired, the new chairman
wasn't as good at evading the authorities.
So I have a little discomfort at grades myself.
And when I gave this course in the 60s and in the 70s,
everybody got an A. And it took several years
for the departments to notice.
Anyway, so we have to give grades at MIT.
But all that's great fun.
Anybody?
What didn't we cover in this course that you wish we had?
And I'd like to know what some of you
are doing also.
What's your plan to make machines smarter
in the future?
And how hard is it to find a job where you can do research?
I haven't tried getting a new job for a long time.
I just tried to hire a former student,
but he's starting a huge startup.
And if you can't find a job, I guess you can make one
if you can fool enough investors into supporting a new operation.
The most of the work you're going to do
is designed around a very specific problem.
Design what?
Around a very specific problem that you're
addressing, getting a machine to solve some particular problem.
There's always a fast path to that
by finding the right set of data and really
finding the right model that will work reasonably well.
It's not really like a business case
that you're made for making a general intelligence in it
when there's motivation for some specific application.
That's right.
Goes back to World War II again.
The reason we could do so much in those early years
about general theories was that the Defense Department had
created this new wing called ARPA, Advanced Research
Projects Agency.
And I actually don't know what caused it to begin,
but a lot of it was involved with trying
to make new kinds of instruments to detect
intercontinental missiles and heaven knows what else.
But they decided to have a basic research branch
to because if you're in the military, one of your concerns
is defense.
And for some reason that I don't know how to explain,
but a group of people in the Office of Naval Research
concluded that the best defense is
to be way ahead in technology of everyone else.
And since there were no particular constraints on them,
they didn't have to say you have to write a progress
report every three months and stuff like that.
Anyway, another unique thing about the situation
when I started was that the students knew more
than the professors about computer science.
Now, there were people around MIT who knew about computers,
but we had the bad luck of having the best analog
computers in the world, Vannevar Bush and people like that.
So when things change suddenly enough,
your best people might turn out to be the worst for a few years.
And the leaders in innovation came from the Tech Model
Railroad Club and a few institutions like that.
I certainly knew something about computers, at least
the theory of them, but I didn't know anything
about modern programming.
And either did anyone else, except Newell and Simon
and Carnegie Mellon and John McCarthy, who
they invented Lisp processing languages,
and John McCarthy refined them and basically combined
a very clumsy logo-like Lisp processing language
with algebraic language.
And so Lisp came after.
There had been primitive Lisp processors.
And all of Newell and Simon's work, including a chess program,
had been done with just a programming language that
had something like car, clutter, and cons.
So that was about 10 years after the beginning.
The first computers at MIT came mainly
from Lincoln Lab, who had the job of building supercomputers
to analyze radar data and stuff like that, which were indeed
connected with national defense and trying
to combine radar reports from all sorts of places
to get early warnings of activities in space
and so forth.
When the first Sputnik was launched by the Russians,
there was just a little thing going beep, beep,
beep in low Earth orbit.
And within a couple of hours after the Russians announced
that Sputnik was there and they announced its orbit,
a couple of hackers at Lincoln Lab, surely,
managed to track the thing by hooking a couple of radio.
It was going beep, beep, beep.
And a guy named Brad Howland, who was a teenager,
I think, then hooked a couple of radio receivers
up with some flip flops and things
and was able to get its exact trajectory from the Doppler
shifts.
Anyway, then I think I've talked about that history.
At some point about early 1970 or so,
it's 10 or 15 years after ARPA started.
Well, the big ARPA project was called Project MAC in 1963.
And MIT got $3 million a year for designing and building
a time sharing system.
The idea for a time sharing system
had bubbled up in a few places.
But it was mainly a couple of other youngsters, John
McCarthy and Edward Fredkin, who recognized
that if a computer could compute thousands of operations
per second, then it should be able to compute
hundreds of operations per second for tens of people.
And when it gets to a billion operations per second,
then it should be able to compute
a million operations per second for 1,000 people
and so forth.
And MIT was the first place to develop time sharing system.
And as I said, they sent this $3 million a year
to get that project to work.
And because the guy in charge of that
was a former professor of psychology named Joe Licklider,
had been a friend of mine when I was an undergraduate,
he added another million dollars a year
and gave it to us to start the AI lab.
And if that ever happens to you, I hope it will.
Anyway, as I complained a lot during the course,
we were able to sort of do anything
we thought was possible.
And we didn't worry about whether it could be done
in a year or two or 20.
We just had enough money and enough adventurous people
to just start doing those things.
So in the very first year, we had
Jim Slagle making the program that
could do integrals at the level that students in 1801
were learning to do.
I think I mentioned I made the first program that
computed derivatives.
And it was just five or 10 lines of code
because it worked lexically.
It said, if you see xy, replace it by the symbols x dy plus y
dx, and so forth.
That's how you do derivatives, where d means derivative.
And since it's operating on the names of functions,
then you just recurse until all the function names
have disappeared.
And so that was just a page of code.
And then Slagle, who was blind, wrote 20 pages of code.
And Joel Moses, who was what's he now?
Provost or?
He used to be.
Did he retire or go back to work?
Probably both.
Yep.
And he mentioned that it took him a very long time
to decode Slagle's 20 pages.
Because since Slagle is writing in Braille,
poor Slagle has to understand his code, too.
And you can't just glance at a page.
So he wrote this incredibly intricate compressed stuff.
And it had the weird property that it solved integrals.
It did integrals at just about the same speed
as good math students.
So if you gave it an expression with a couple of sines
and cosines and things, it might take 10 or 15 minutes.
And everybody was very impressed that this computer could keep
up with a human.
But of course, that fact had no meaning whatever.
That happened to be how slow computers were at that time.
The IBM 704, which was I guess we had a 701 and then a 704.
And I think that machine was doing about 20,000 operations
per second, which is probably more than a person can do.
But no one knows.
Well, so who has an idea on what should be done next?
Yeah, what would you like to do?
A robot that would integrate, like, I don't know,
maybe an AI system that would interact more with the world
if I do.
Well, we're going to need robots pretty soon.
Just for example, this aging problem.
We're getting more and more people
who are crippled in one way or another,
handicapped, a huge population of people
with mild brain disorders, of course, serious ones also.
And there are not enough nurses to take care
of the disabled, aged people.
And I think that's probably going
to be a major need for robotics.
As I see it, the problem with robotics
is that people build robots.
And you look at any laboratory that
has built a physical robot, and Media Lab
is a perfect example of it.
Or Rod Brooks had a wonderful robot called
Cog with a head and two hands.
Took a lot of engineering.
And there was only one of it.
And it only worked for a few hours a week
because it's very complicated and it breaks.
And so the joke is that if I were starting a robotics lab,
I would not permit robots.
Once you simulate the robots and get them to do what you want,
then you take it out of the university
and hire some good mechanical engineers
to make the robot you want.
But you don't want to.
Robotics research should not involve robots.
And I think I have sort of mixed feelings about the, what's
the great basketball robot event called?
Well, whatever you call it, they kick a ball and try to get.
It's actually, they try to get it through to a goal.
So it is soccer.
Yeah, whatever.
That's probably a plus for the high school students
who are involved in it.
But yes?
Why do you have robots that all universities use as a base?
Why do we keep building hardware?
Is it necessary to keep building hardware back again?
I'm not sure what's your question.
When we use computers, we don't build the computers back again.
We use the, like we just create software.
Yes.
Aren't we doing the same for robots?
And if not, why aren't we just programming the robot
to do stuff that we want?
What I'm saying is if people program the robot,
then it takes them two weeks to do the simplest thing.
If you're programming a simulated robot,
then it takes two minutes.
Why does it take more to program the robot?
Because the robot's broken, and there's only one in the lab.
And there are eight people who want to use it.
And 3 quarters of the time, it's down because some motor,
because it's not in mass production.
If you have a machine that somebody made,
it's probably the first machine that person ever made.
So it's no good.
Look at the Honda robot called ASIMO.
You've all seen it.
But you all saw it 10 years ago.
It has not changed.
But they say it doesn't fall over so often anymore.
There is a company, a French company,
that does a robot called Now Robot that works pretty good.
I don't know.
Why don't we buy some robots from some company?
Because they're no good.
They don't do any.
They've only got one elbow.
They can't reach around.
They don't have, they don't.
You can buy a hand for $30,000 or $40,000
that has three or four fingers.
But
There's probably a trade-off, though,
between making a more complex robot that has more interaction
you can make.
That gets more difficult when you're building an actual robot.
But for a simulator, simulating the real environment and gravity
in those sort of systems can also be difficult to create.
So that you're sure that whatever their reaction
So your program, if they robot, you
need to make sure the environment that it's in
is somewhat real, right?
Well, it depends what you mean by real.
It seems to me if the robot is smart and can learn
and is adaptable and when a piece of its software
doesn't work, then it modifies it.
In other words, if you had a higher level learning machine
in the processor of the robot, then
it could work in a real environment
by learning that if you do this on a slippery floor,
you might, maybe you should lean the other way before you.
Patty Mays did a little bit of that 20 years ago.
With what?
Rule system that defines that moving
and attacks on threshold energy.
Yeah, but you see, if you have a real robot,
you've only got an hour a week to debug this thing.
And the program is working in real time
if you look at real robots.
Whereas if you're simulating a stick figure robot,
then you can simulate friction and slipping.
But you can move it at 100,000 operations per second, maybe.
Another thing is there's something
weird about the robot people.
They tell me there's so much feedback needed
that they need a separate computer for each joint.
I hear this everywhere.
They say, it's distributed.
It's really good.
Of course, it's still falling over.
I agree that there are a lot of things about robots
that can be simulated on a computer.
And I agree that a lot of the things
that people are currently working on with real robots
would better be first done simulated.
But I think that when you have a robot, especially when
you have situations where it interacts with a human being,
the reaction of the human being is sort of really different,
depending on whether it's a simulation or a physical being.
Because I guess human beings inherently
have different reactions to objects
with physical embodiments.
So I feel like at a certain point,
especially when it interfaces with humans, such as caretaker
robots, you do have to switch to the real robots.
Well, the caretaker robot has to be a smart program that's
running a physical robot eventually.
It's just that we don't have the smart programs.
And we could have had them 25 years ago
if the people wanting to make a helper robot
didn't have a physical robot in their lab.
Look at COG, which COG is proudly
displayed in the MIT Museum.
I don't know of a single fact or technique or idea
that came out of that project in the decade
when graduate students wrote bad theses about it.
So I guess then ultimately, it's sort
of like a division of labor problem, where it's like,
because it seems like when people are testing
their code on actual robots, it's
like they have too many problems at the same time.
Whereas you're saying they should focus on the software.
And after the software is all good,
then they can move on to integrating the software
with the hardware.
Yeah, well, the robots in Second Life.
We're pretty good.
I don't know of any people who complained
that they wanted real ones.
I'm not familiar with the robots in Second Life.
What did they do?
Well, you could make one, because there was a language
for it.
I don't think they did anything much.
But they don't fall over.
But I guess a good example might be, well,
Dean Kamen's robot soccer project.
And Carnegie Mellon had a robot soccer project for many years.
And I don't know that any.
I've never heard of any interesting discovery
that came from that.
The Media Lab also, they're the nice looking robots that smile.
And people are impressed by the way
that humans are attracted to interact with these robots.
But I think once we know that, it's
something to avoid rather than to exploit.
Until when the robot says, pleased to meet you,
wouldn't it be nice if it were actually pleased to meet you?
The Intelligent Welcome match would be our target.
Even if it doesn't move, if it just sat there and felt
good about seeing you, that would be a great achievement.
I don't know how you would test for it.
Have you ever played with a Leo dinosaur?
Yes.
And there was a cat that Itachi made.
In fact, we ordered a PLEO, but we never got it.
Are they still in production?
I believe so.
I don't know.
I don't think so.
They seem like they appear to be, yes.
What?
They appear to be.
Yeah, it's a beautiful job.
Somebody made a cat.
I'm trying to remember.
Another Japanese company.
It was an awfully good cat.
It wouldn't do much, but every now and then it would mew
and sort of look at you and beg for something.
But you couldn't resist it.
Yeah?
So from your experience, do you know how long it would take
to simulate a real world, to create a simulation,
a simple simulation of the real world?
Well, what?
And how many people?
Because you're saying that we should simulate robots.
You need a computer to create software for that,
to set up real robots.
And so we need to create the software
that simulates the real world.
But that's complicated for me.
You know, like, you have some ideas,
like how long would it take, how many people,
and why aren't we doing that?
Or why isn't there somebody doing that?
I wish somebody would explain to me why the majority of,
you know, there are epidemics of ideologies.
So that around 1980, the dominant idea
of making machines better was to build rule-based systems.
And that's probably still the most popular way
to program a computer for a complicated commercial
application, like making airplane reservations
and keeping stock of parts in the factory and on and on.
Now, when the first rule-based systems appeared,
they were called production-based languages.
Production is just, I think, the word
comes from Emil Post in the 1920s.
And the idea is you have a set of symbols, x, a, y, b, z,
where x, y, and z are variables, and a and b are constants.
In other words, an algebraic expression, basically.
And if the state of the world or the state of some process
is described by this expression, then you change it
into something else like ax.
So one operation might be, if there's an ace anywhere,
let's move it to the left.
That's just a simple production.
Anyway, if you read my old book on computation,
there's a couple of chapters about production systems.
And those were the first universal logical systems
that could be applied to computers.
So although there were no computers in the 1920s
when Emil Post started working on that,
there had been some discussion back in 1900 or so
when mathematicians like Hilbert, who
were interested both in applied mathematics
and basic logic theories, were trying
to say what kinds of processes can be represented
by what kinds of algebraic or production-like systems.
So there was a lot of research before.
Well, not a lot, but quite a bit of research
before computers even appeared.
And in the 1950s, making rule-based systems
just out of transforming sequences of symbols
became popular.
And that was fine, because those systems are sort of universal.
However, to make a production system
to play a good game of chess, there
might be some point at which just making rules,
saying if there's a pawn here and a queen here
and a bishop here, do this.
Maybe you can't express things that way.
And you might have to have a higher level expression,
such as if two pieces are under attack
at distant parts of the board, then
you should decide to make a move that improves your situation
in one of these situations and blocks
a way of the opponent improving his situation
on the other one.
So you can't express that in terms
of the positions of the pieces.
You have to have a higher level abstraction.
And what happened in the development
of rule-based systems is that you could make rules
about rules, but nobody ever got very good at it.
And you still don't find six-level systems
like the kind proposed in the Society of Mind Book, which
says whatever you do, you want to have multiple levels.
And at the third or fourth level,
the system should have some reflective ability
so that it's keeping track of how successful it's
been at something.
That's a simple kind of learning.
Or it's noticing that abstractions of a certain sort
have been very productive in a certain kind of situation
described by some other abstraction.
Nobody's ever built any programs that go up four or five
levels of that sort.
And I suppose the reason is that nobody, virtually no one,
has a job where they could definitely
plan to spend four or five years.
I think David here said, did you say three or four years
to map out this animal?
That's my hope.
Right, and then you should have a meta-hope
that you'll have such a good student or two
that you'll only have to spend a year of it
in this young Richard Greenblatt or Bill Gosper
or Peter Sampson will come up.
And you'll notice that he's better than you at this.
And that's the best thing.
And then you can quit and go to a higher level.
But there aren't any jobs like that.
We had a lab, sub lab, that split off from the media lab
that I won't mention its name.
But its director got into the habit
of warning a progress report each month.
Well, when we were funded by ARPA,
there was something about a proposal each year.
And guess what our proposal was?
Anybody want to guess?
Intelligent machines?
It was what we had done.
We proposed to do what we had done last year.
Of course, it's nice when the head of the agency
is an old buddy of yours from undergraduate years.
That was Licklider.
But that worked out fine.
And so our proposals were, in fact, progress reports.
And that way, you could do anything you want.
Now, if you had to do that every month,
then those proposals would look so flimsy and sick
that any good executive would say,
you should squash that project.
It's not getting anything done.
Well, I don't know how to fix that.
If we try to deal with the economic collapse
of the civilization that we're in,
it may be politically hard to have five- or 10-year research
projects.
So I have no idea what's going to happen in the next decade.
Yes?
Two questions.
What do you think is the most effective format for people
to make progress in the AI research?
In universities, would it be within corporations,
like what IBM is doing, or what?
And also, who you think should be working on these problems?
Well, the problem, it looks like this,
what do you call the IBM thing?
Watson.
That might be a good thing.
It's the first substantial AI project
that is trying to combine more than one method.
But I don't know.
I actually haven't read even what's available about it.
But IBM did have AI researchers for the last.
There was a group in the middle 1950s.
You've all read about this Dartmouth AI conference
in 1954.
And that had McCarthy and me from around here,
and Newell and Simon, who were at Carnegie Mellon.
I think it was called Carnegie Institute of Technology then,
but whatever.
And it had a couple of people from IBM,
and it had about six or seven assorted individuals
from here and there.
So IBM had a guy named Nat Rochester,
who had been involved in designing computers.
And he had a lot of good ideas.
And I had written on paper a geometry theorem proving
program.
And he started a project to actually put that
on a computer.
So for a few years, IBM had a few people working
on different small AI projects.
Then that disappeared after about 10 or 15 years.
And there was essentially no artificial and very little
programming research at IBM.
And they were mostly into hardware and commercial
software and so forth.
This Watson thing is apparently three or four years old,
and it looks like a substantial project.
And I'm a little worried that since they're not
very academic, they might not have the idea that if you've
discovered something, the first thing you should do
is publish all its details so that you get credit for it.
Well, it's hard.
Not very many companies encourage
the individuals getting credit.
And it looks like the guys in that project
are able to publish a substantial amount.
But I think the first good sign will be if they just dump
their code out, too, and let people go over it and copy it
and see if there's anything there they can use.
It's very rare for any AI researcher
to use anyone else's code, as far as I know.
It's almost never happened.
I don't know.
The best example, almost, was Winograd's Shrutlu program,
which was exported to Carnegie Mellon and to Stanford.
And both of them ran that program quite a bit.
But it wasn't.
I don't know why it died.
But apparently, Winograd himself hadn't commented enough
to remember how it worked.
And the beginners never got very far in improving
either its robotic ability, which was non-trivial,
or its linguistic ability, which was unique.
It had better parsers and better semantic operations,
if only for a limited blocks world,
put the big red block on top of the little green block.
And it would do things like that.
And you could say, put the block which
is on top of the big red block and do such and such with it.
So it had fairly complicated ways
to refer to and describe things.
But it became a showpiece where you could demonstrate it.
And after a few years, you couldn't even.
Has anyone tried it?
I haven't.
I've looked into it, but it's immaculate.
So it's not even, there isn't even a path to run it.
So there's no interpreter to run it.
It should have had the whole package, of course.
Because that program was big, and MACLIS
would have only been 2% of the whole thing.
Winograd had quite a number of graduate students
who finally left and did something else,
because the project was, they just
found it too hard to understand the code.
But who has an idea of what to do next?
I bet you all have some fantasy of how to make machines smarter.
You could wait for the human brain people to, yes?
I was thinking you could get more funding for science fiction
writers, and then hopefully one of them
will come up with a brilliant idea.
Yes?
Greg Egan had a computer.
How many of you know the name of Greg Egan?
Look at his web page.
It has more exciting mathematical demonstrations
than his.
As far as I know, I don't know anything like it.
Well, yes, Ken Perlin.
Type Ken Perlin into your Google and get his web page.
And he has, I think he must invent two or three
incredibly brilliant small programs every week,
because there are quite a few hundred
of these gorgeous demonstrations of one principle after another.
Oh, dear.
I didn't look ahead.
Another feature of Greg Egan is that he read The Society of Mind
and worked a lot of ideas that I hadn't thought
of into some of his stories.
So but another feature of him is that no one has ever met him.
That is, if you knock on his door, which is in Perth,
it won't answer.
And I was discussing this with Greg Benford
and apparently there are a couple of people who have seen him,
but nobody knows anyone who knows him.
You could do that.
Maybe that's the way to get a lot done.
Make a list of all your friends and abandon them.
Just think of all the free time you'll have.
Is there any other Gregs?
Oh, well, Greg Benford.
But this isn't fair.
I've lost the big chalk.
Among the science fiction writers,
there are only a few who actually know a lot of science.
Benford is quite a good physicist and knows a lot
and publishes serious physics papers.
Larry Niven knew quite a bit of science
but was never a practicing one.
So in his science fiction, there are
occasional technical errors, like in Ringworld.
Ringworld was a big ring-shaped planet around the sun.
And so here's the sun and here's this ring.
And the ring is about 8,000 miles wide
and goes all the way around its sun in something
like Earth's orbit, which means that it
has an area of the order of 100,000 Earths.
Well, Larry didn't realize that there was a bug.
And if you make a ring that's rotating around the sun,
well, first of all, there's no particular reason
why it should rotate.
But if it didn't, it would squash.
But it's not gravitationally stable.
So as soon as it gets slightly off-center,
then this part, if this is closer, it gets pulled in.
And so finally, one part of it falls into the sun
and the rest follows it.
So in the sequel to Ringworld, some physicists
pointed this out to Larry Niven.
And so now Larry Niven had little wires.
I forget what they're connected to.
They're made of something called scryth,
which is 10 to the 50th time stronger than anything real
because it's pretty hard to hold a thing that massive.
Oh, then they're little jets, which
have been built by the original inhabitants.
I forgot all the geometry.
So now there's an active system for maintaining the Ringworld
to not fall into the sun.
And the sequel, this was built by some disappeared aliens
millions of years ago.
And the hardware is beginning to break down.
So they need to find an alien race with enough engineering
to fix it and blah, blah.
Anyway, Larry Niven is awfully good at making up things
with a pretty good scientific background.
And then when he makes a mistake,
he writes a sequel to correct it.
So maybe that's actually better than getting it
right the first time.
He has a machine, the transporters in Star Trek.
Niven's transporters are nice because they take out
all the chemicals in your cells that shouldn't be there.
So once they have transporters, automatically the people
now become nearly immortal.
Because if you're being scanned and reconstructed
by a transporter, it might as well fix all your bugs
while it's at it.
Anyway, there's a good idea on every page of this guy,
even if it's wrong.
So when I read a regular novel, which is very rare,
there's usually a good idea every chapter maybe.
But I didn't write Larry Niven's name.
Probably he had more ideas than any other writer,
but they're not all correct.
So how many of you are going to pursue AI,
or are you going to work on trying to make machines smarter?
Here's one.
We sure could use them.
I'm sort of amused at the there are
a couple of transhumanist communities,
whatever that means.
And they're worried that the AI will,
as many science fiction writers have, be hostile and take over
and want everything for itself.
And so there are serious discussions
on how to make friendly AIs.
And of course, the master of that
was Isaac Asimov, who said that a robot should always
put its interests beneath those of its owner or whatever.
How many of you know Asimov's laws?
And then there was the fourth law
that he had to make, which is that it's
all right to harm a human if it's
to save a large number of others from being harmed.
But it's like saying we shouldn't eat meat.
It's very hard to make up ethical principles that
are foolproof.
I'm not sure what the safe AI people
have as their Asimov laws.
But if you walk around the AI world today,
it's hard to take seriously the idea
that they might form some sort of threat.
Of course, it could happen overnight, but, well,
we discussed the big threat the other day,
somebody making a virus that kills everything.
That's the road toward nanotechnology.
I can't get them to propose anything.
What happens in your class, Pat?
I haven't been there for a long time.
Oh, I don't know.
Yes.
Do you think efforts to augment human intelligence
are going to stand?
Rather than finding a machine that can tell us what's out,
given all the ways that we can make people more intelligent
and more healthy?
That's a great question, because we're probably
fairly close to the technology to do something
exciting in that direction, except that we're afraid to.
Because it seems to me that suppose you just wanted
to do something modest, like improve some person's memory,
I'll bet that with a few million dollars and I don't know
how many years, you could do something
without understanding how the brain works
to attach accessories to it.
I think I mentioned Brindley's first experiment
on trying to restore vision to a blind person.
I think I mentioned that last time.
L-E-Y, I think.
So what he did was here's his secretary, who's blind.
And here's her occipital lobe of the brain.
And here's this area, which is the primary visual.
I think it's called area 17 for no good reason.
That's the place where the signals get
into the brain from the eye.
Stupid, isn't it?
Here's the eye, and here's the optic nerve.
And then here's some other stuff.
And it's all the way back here.
I presume this is because we used
to be an octopus or something, and the eye was here.
But anyway, what's more, the wires cross
and all sorts of things.
But anyway, so here's this piece of brain.
And what Brindley does is he makes a little gadget
with 64 electrodes.
And I've forgotten the details, but I
think that these actually has little coils.
I believe that the thing was there's
no wire coming out of her head.
But these little wires, little coils, and electrodes
are in the 1950s.
And silicone had just appeared, and it looked pretty harmless.
So this is a little pad of silicone.
He has to take the bone off the back of her skull,
which is risky.
So there's the gadget.
And as I said, when you stimulate these,
I believe 48 of them worked, and about eight of them hurt.
And about eight of them didn't do anything.
But if you fired up this one, then she
described it as being like half a matchstick at arm's length.
And they were little bars, which is interesting.
They were not little round dots.
But there were enough of them that she could read letters
one at a time.
And so that's the 1950s.
And as far as I know, it's never been done again.
Maybe there's some way to look that up.
Yes?
So they can improve the memory of rats recently.
Of rats?
Yeah, and they can turn off and turn on.
OK.
Yeah.
But anyway, I suspect that if you got permission to try,
I'll bet you could put 1,000 electrodes maybe
in a couple of places on the cortex and just poke around.
And I'll bet that you could do it without much danger
and eventually get enough inputs and outputs
to hook it up to something stupid
like the Oxford Dictionary, which
would be about that big, or make it a memory retrieval system
where you think, I don't know what you'd think,
but people having this gadget in their head
for a long time with a screen producing outputs
would learn how to control some of those little spots.
And then another part of their brain
would learn to control groups of them and so forth.
And maybe after a few days or weeks or months,
you'd be able to operate this as like a touch
screen on your iPhone.
And it would provide you with a huge, inexhaustible amount
of memory.
And for one in a dozen people, it
might produce outputs that get right
into your mind in some graphic or auditory or unspeakably
alien sense.
And you'd know something that you didn't know before.
So that would be a very thrilling area.
And there are lots of epileptics who
are having pieces of their brain removed
because it's saving their life.
And it would be almost risk-free to slide this little gadget
in while you're at it because now it's 60 years later.
And we know which kinds of silicone implants
are tolerated.
And I'm sure there are other things.
What substances can you put in the body that don't irritate it?
Must be quite a few.
I mean, I think we're sort of already doing this like
with our computers or with our smartphones,
except for the interface between us
and the devices is a lot funkier.
This is just more direct.
Whereas right now, it's like we have to, I guess,
use our bodies to actuate the machine
and then use our senses to get the information back
into our mind.
And we're being very sluggish about it.
I don't see why you couldn't put little pads
in the toes of your shoes so you wouldn't need a mouse.
Or they have like tongue interfaces where like
Well, yes.
The tongue displays where it sort of sends
like electric signals on your tongue in a 2D grid
so that you can like, I guess, feel like some shape.
And there's also, I saw this talk last week
of Microsoft Research working on this tongue controlling
interface where you can use, no, seriously,
they gave this to disabled people
and put it in this wheelchair and they can use their tongue
to control the wheelchair.
And it's almost like they're mind controlling it.
Yes, right.
I think there's actually something that does it
with scanning the activity in the brain.
So I saw this head talk a lot back.
On the emotive device?
I actually tried it in the stuff I created.
Oh.
They think of that right and they can control
the way, I don't know what it's like.
Yeah, so I think it works.
I did an internship at a video game company
and used that exact device to make video games.
And you have to stream it, except for it's sort of
an engine because basically the way it works is like
you have this streaming interface where they tell you
to like push or pull and like it associates
like your certain like thought patterns
with like the push or with the pull.
But I don't know, it's like,
maybe I just didn't practice it enough.
It's not that reliable.
So it's like for a video game or for like toy applications,
it's okay if you actually use that to like control,
I don't know, like an Evangelion style giant robot.
This is an old thing.
I don't know if there are any better ones.
Yes, the people with the tongue gadget
claim very good results.
I don't know what it's like to go around
with that thing in your mouth, but.
They made a wireless one.
It's like in the shape of a retainer.
Oh, okay, is it anchored to the teeth or something?
It's basically like a retainer with, you know,
wires to hold it on your teeth.
It sticks all the way through your mouth.
Oh, so you just, that doesn't sound so bad.
Is it wireless?
That would be.
Yeah, yeah.
There was a talk by Desme Tan from Microsoft Research
and he showed stuff about that.
This guy, I think it's spelled right, but I'm not sure,
is a professor at Stanford.
And he made an array of vibrators
that go on your back.
And I put it on once.
It's 20 by 20, I think.
And they all work, so it's better than the 8 by 8 thing.
And I was able to recognize a telephone.
It's connected to a video camera and it's just
a pad on your back.
And if you have a TV camera with the right kind of contrast
and you can find the door and stuff like that, it's easy.
And I recognized a couple of objects.
I was only in it for about five minutes,
but the interesting thing is that it didn't take any time
to feel this input as a shape.
I was pretty surprised.
That was many years ago.
I don't know what's happened since.
There are reading devices for the blind
that go on your finger.
So instead of Braille, you go like this
and it can make a sound or it can make
a vibration in your fingertip.
So the trouble with Braille is you have to have Braille.
But this device, I can't remember who makes it.
You just put this little thimble on
and it has tiny vibrators so that it's like Braille.
And you can feel the letters go by as you move your finger.
And I've forgotten the professor's name for this.
Does that ring a bell?
Anyway, only about 10% of blind people
find it easy to learn to read this way.
So it's not widely in production.
But that's all beside the point.
I think at some point in some country
we'll want to try this direct brain connection thing.
Might be great.
Might be really good for an older person who's
become blind and a senior person whose lost vision
might not be able to soup up their hearing
and other senses well enough or learn fast enough
to get around, so being.
If you become blind deaf like Helen Keller
when you're a few months old.
Or was she three years old?
Anybody remember?
So she just adapted and became quite a good writer.
When thinking about augmenting human intelligence,
there are really two big rounds to think about.
One round is developing the external device
that does the thinking for you that retrieves information.
And then the other round is the interface
between the external being and the human being.
Yes, what's the representations?
And it'd be wonderful to have a gadget with a bunch of brain
electrodes so you could discover what kinds of symbols
can people learn to distinguish.
And we'd probably learn more about the brain
a couple of years than in the previous century
because we could get some idea of representations.
Do people represent things as list structures
or as productions or computer science
has come up with lots of ways to represent knowledge?
I've never met a neuroscientist who even knows
what your smirk.
Maybe there are some I haven't met.
I'm sure.
Well, there's me.
That's why I smirk.
But I've complained about this about four times already.
But the best example is to look at the review of the emotion
machine on the Amazon book page for it
because there's this neurologist who says,
he writes all about these K lines and panologies
and isonomes.
And he has no evidence they exist.
And it's just so funny because I'm writing this book
to help those.
Here they're drowning in ignorance.
And I've just taught them this life raft.
And they say, well, he hasn't tested this life raft
to see if it exists.
They don't like the idea of a suggestion
if you haven't proved it.
That is not the way to do science.
You have to make hypotheses.
And if you're a neuroscientist, you
can't do that because it's not in your nature.
So you have to get them from someone else.
Very simple.
How come there are no programming languages
that have decent representations of anything?
People tell me they use C++, whatever that is.
I think Winston wrote a book on how to program in that.
And I asked him, do you actually know
how to program in that language?
He said, of course not.
But I know how to write books on how to program.
Do you remember that?
It's a great learning experience.
You actually said something like that because you write the book
and then you can get other people to put in the examples.
You should all read some of my.
I couldn't force myself to learn C without writing a book
about it.
It was too boring.
That's the way.
Right.
If you read my book on computation, which is still
actually current because it's about things
that they don't teach much.
And the best thing about the book
is that it's full of problems that you can actually solve.
But I wasn't good at making up problems.
So most of the problems there were made up
by a young graduate student named Manuel Bloom.
And I don't think I gave him enough credit in the book.
I just took it for granted that people
are good at making up problems.
And I didn't realize how rare this was.
He now has the property that Manuel and his wife, Lenore,
and his son, whose name I forgot, are all professors at CMU.
Computer science.
Yes.
Are there any other such families?
And as far as I can tell, Winston's book
has been substantially replaced by this Norwegian.
What's his name?
But there's almost no ideas about AI in that book.
So we have a textbook that is not helping the field progress
very much because it's giving a lot of details about methods
that I do.
Well, like lots of stuff about probabilistic learning,
which is very nice, but I don't think it has much future.
So if you meet anybody who's interested in AI,
get them to read Paks' book.
Yes.
So what happened?
Why did MIT change so much?
Why did so many machine learning people?
Well, there was a very strange phenomenon
called Rodney Brooks, who somehow
got a worldwide reputation for inventing
what was it called?
Subsumption.
Subsumption was a formulation related
to what the first computer people called
priority interrupt.
So instead of having high level programming languages,
Brooke pointed out that if you just
have a bunch of statements and give them priorities
and then take the one that you take all the statements that
apply to a situation and take the one with the highest
priority and do that, then you can write a PhD thesis
and make a movie of an experiment in which a robot
actually found a Coke bottle.
Now, the fact that the first 40 times
it didn't find the Coke bottle because when
it got near the table, it couldn't see it anymore,
and it had no memory was ignored by the worldwide community.
And so some of Rodney Brooks' ideas swept the entire world,
stopped research in Japan, because they all
turned towards saying, if you just observe the environment
properly, you can solve a lot of problems without making plans.
And he won the top prize that the AI Society gave out.
It's a complete mystery to me.
Here is four or five really bad ideas
that swept the world and replaced
almost all other AI research for a decade or two.
Wonderful.
That's why there are no robots that
can go into the reactors in Japan and fix things,
because all the robots we have only react to never mind.
Yeah.
So how do you see we're changing that from now on?
Because now we have a problem that most of the,
maybe most of the stuff in computer science
are both in AI, probabilistic inference
or some kind of supervised learning or supervised learning.
And that makes a lot of money.
But I mean, if you were to.
Well, that's the problem.
The best way to make money is to steal it.
So why doesn't everybody just turn and go down the corner
and mug someone?
I mean, there's a real problem here.
Because you can mug a lot of people
in the parallel using awkwardness.
Right.
That's really.
You got it.
And isn't there any other smart professors that, like,
why can they see that?
Why do they see that?
It beats me.
I'd like to hear some theories of why
the textbook by Russell and Norwood
doesn't mention the society of mind theories, for example.
I mean, they've been out there for 30 years.
So there's something.
I don't know what the problem is.
But 250,000 people are taking that course.
Well, so things are going to get worse or better.
Whoops.
Has anybody watched some of this course?
Has it started yet?
Oh, it's almost over.
OK.
Have any of you looked?
No one here?
I think we have more people who aren't taking classes here.
I couldn't hear.
I think we have more people who aren't already
taking classes here.
Most people I know are taking that
out of the working industry or their high school or whatever.
It seems to me that, for example, machine learning,
when people take machine learning,
they think they are very smart because they
can do calculations with a lot of symbols.
And they think, oh, I'm such a genius.
I'm not saying that I'm smart, but it seems to me
that dealing with symbols make people think
that they are very smart.
That makes the situation even worse
because you have maybe people that
could solve this problem.
And they are, oh, I can do a lot of calculations.
And there are these really hard formulas that only I know.
It seems that theory of symbols is more complex and harder.
And people tend to stick to theories
that have symbols and formulas.
I guess so, but somehow it doesn't.
To me, mathematics is really hard, and symbols are easy.
It's sort of funny.
Yeah, but there are still symbols.
Yeah.
Well, does the machine course ever
mention like Pat Winston's?
It sounds like technique.
Machine learning.
Yes, because what Winston does is
he looks at the differences between things
and gets rid of them.
And you can think of it as a sort of symbolic servo.
But there are a lot of very simple, common sense,
sensical operations in the methods that he describes.
But none of them are easy to express as equations.
And maybe programming isn't technical enough.
And you need to dress things up in algebra to make them.
Yeah, should we do that as an energy minimization
principle or something?
Yes.
That's cute.
Getting closer to the goal, that's all it is.
I think I mentioned the Newell and Simon had this great idea
of getting closer to the goal.
And they gave up when they couldn't solve the missionary
and cannibals problem, because there's
a step where you have to take three people back in the boat.
And their program refused to do that,
because it wasn't getting them closer to the goal.
And the funny part is that if you used pairs of operations
as the unit, then their method would work.
Nice question is, how do people make a very beautiful theory
and then not take the next step, and someone else
does it n years later?
I guess it always happens.
Yes.
I was just going to say, I think machine learning
is an incredibly useful mission to describe it,
because it really isn't AI.
And I think a lot of the problems
between machine learning people and AI people
is that they're trying to do different things,
and they just have shared history
and see different important problems.
Well, they're not doing different things.
One is doing a subset of the other.
Yes.
I mean, machine learning is the subset of the world.
But they are making a lot of good progress
in solving certain types of really hard problems.
And it can be really useful, because a lot of these
are problems that people aren't able to solve themselves
and aren't good at.
The short answer is definitely genius.
And AI is the science.
One at a time.
Yeah.
You could say that about anything, though.
Surely, what's really important is not
solving all sorts of useful things,
but getting to a higher level where you can solve things
that no one else can solve.
That's probably what you mean important for what?
Important for the advancement of science?
Yes.
Important for miscellaneous applications
that are useful to people?
Well, in the long run, you're dead.
So things like science.
To say that everything that doesn't just
advance science is completely useless is crazy.
No, I'm saying science.
Science has disappeared, because the dark ages.
It's interesting.
But if you say it's just advancing science, yes.
I take the position that we should
spend a fraction of our world's resources on long-term things.
And it's no excuse.
And no one should say, let's spend all our resources
on immediate, useful money making labor-saving processes.
I'm not saying that.
I think we should spend a lot of good money on science.
But I'm saying that doesn't mean that anything that's not
science is useful.
Yeah, but if you look at AI, no money.
I only know about 10 people in the entire country
who are thinking about hard problems in AI.
So it's not just a mild complaint.
There's some kind of pathology.
There's no support.
I don't think anybody's denying that machine learning is
useful, which just the problem is
that it seems like the obsession with machine learning
is sort of overtaking anyone trying to make progress in AI.
So it's like, OK, in the ideal world,
it's like there are the people who work on machine learning.
But then there are also the people who are solving
the big AI problems.
But it seems like in the current world,
so many people are doing machine learning.
And there are so many resources for it,
such that there is not enough for people who are doing AI.
Yeah, my complaint is that there's almost no one doing AI.
It's very peculiar.
So what is it about the current culture of science
and technology that causes this to happen?
A great example would be, what's the gross product of,
what's the income of IBM?
It's a big company.
How come they're doing that funny thing?
I keep forgetting.
How come they're doing Watson?
Isn't that?
Because it's cheaper than Super Bowl ads.
OK, they got a lot more publicity out of it
than they would have gotten if it's got all that money
on Super Bowl ads.
I guess so.
But it's a serious company.
It fired its real AI group.
And what?
Maybe properly.
The question is, perhaps the supplementary observation
is that when we were doing stuff a long time ago,
it was regarded as a great success
if you could get a program to do something for the first time.
And I feel it was taken over by people
who want to measure how much better your thing is
than the next thing.
And there are only a few kinds of problems
that are susceptible to that kind of comparison.
As a consequence, people working on those kinds of problems
are not doing things that ought to be done,
like doing something for the first time.
So it's a lot easier to write an article
about how your parser is 1% better than somebody else's
parser than it is to get a program
to have common sense for instance.
Yeah.
Well, now there are four or five common sense research groups,
I think.
How many?
I don't know if any of them make a living yet.
Well, they're collecting common sense.
I'm not sure they have common sense.
And you can measure how many things you know,
but it's not clear that they're measuring
how effective they are with the stuff that they know.
Yeah.
I wonder how hard it would be to make
a program that knows mathematics,
and a lot of mathematics, and does the kinds of things
that mathematicians do.
But somebody would have to pay them to do it.
And where do you get support for common sense
in mathematical reasoning?
It's a beautiful subject.
Well, there was Len, and there was Maxima,
and there was Slabel, and there was Moses.
So there were lots of work to do.
Right.
And Wolfram.
It might be for all his faults, Wolfram's
going to get people to work on real AI,
because he's hired some people to try to make,
what's it called?
Wolfram Alpha, that's cool.
To make it have more and more common sense.
Yeah.
I was going to make one at the beginning.
One of the challenges to trying to make systems
that want to do math, or things that mathematicians do,
is deciding what problems are interesting
that one wants to work on.
There is automatic verification in proving,
although those are also rather difficult problems.
When you get complicated things, it's important as well.
What should be proven is something
that I've never seen tackled, and doesn't seem all that
feasible at the moment.
Well, the first piece of work was on a thesis
that did a kind of mathematical exploration on the basis
of some theory of why an expression or a transformation
might be interesting.
So even that had some precedent.
Oh, really?
It was a system that started from scratch,
and proved a few theorems, and looked around
for things that were interesting and embedded
the opposite of least common divisor, or something like that.
Yeah, that was AM.
And it was pretty exciting.
And that's something that anybody
could take up again any time, and be a great thesis topic.
Lenat, the phenomenon in AM was that it
discovered division, and prime numbers, and a number.
I think I talked about it.
And as Pat says, it had a bunch of criterion
for interestingness.
And it would find sets that were unusually
larger, unusually small, and try to make more things like them,
and that sort of thing.
But it's never been followed up.
What's the main problem with all the high school
Olympia math problems?
Yeah, high school algebra is a wonderful area.
And there was Bobrow's thesis, which did a little bit of it.
And now there's so much more known about natural language.
You'd think somebody would do a super Bobrow
program that might actually be good enough to connect
into Google so that it would solve problems
that real people faced every now and then.
So yeah, the appearance of the new Siri and Dragon things,
which actually answer useful questions,
and roll from alpha, might change.
There might be an industry in commonsense AI
that's actually useful because a few million people might start
using it as soon as it gets just a little bit better.
And I find that Dragon and Siri, I haven't used Siri,
but Dragon now has a thing called Dragon Search.
You talk to it.
And ask a question in ordinary English.
And it goes to the web and makes a Google Search sentence out
of what you said.
And a good fraction of the time, it
saves you a half hour of search.
None of those really have any idea of context, though.
Like, is there any context to it?
Like, a very simple improvement would be,
and Wolfram Althoff already does this a little bit,
is to say, assuming that you meant x, did you mean y or z?
And you can click those instead.
And that's as far as the conversation
with Wolfram Althoff goes.
Right, but you're a person.
And if it had a lot of information about you,
you could collect.
First of all, it would say, what kind of person are you?
And you'd give your biography.
And maybe we'll get common-sense databases that say,
well, here are the kinds of things
that somebody who likes pole vaulting is likely to know.
We already have the what kind of person
are you databases in social networks.
That's what it is, right?
Google's personalized search, yeah.
Well, I just joined Facebook by mistake.
And all sorts of people want to link.
And all you have to do is look at their biography
and see what music they like.
And you can see you don't want to have that person as a friend.
But I wish, has anybody written a program to automate this?
I could tell them, I don't like music
written in the last 20 years.
And that would get rid of about half of them right off.
Of course, it might be Freeman Dyson or somebody
happens to like one of these tunes.
I don't know.
So then you have to make a hierarchy.
If the person happens to be a really good physicist,
then we'll flush that particular filter.
Yeah, also Google's personalized search profile
thinks that I'm a man, because apparently I've
searched too many computer science things in the past.
That's pretty good.
OK.
Maybe thinks most people are a man.
Oh, I don't know.
With other women, they get it right.
But if you happen to be a woman who does computer tech-age
stuff, and if you happen to do a lot of search on programming,
for instance, like looking up APIs of things,
then it tends to try to make that you're a man.
Does it store the gender as a Boolean, or is it?
I saw this a while ago, and it was just like, according to this,
here's what they think that you are.
And at the top, it was like, we think you're a man.
I'm interested to know, though, how manly exactly you
become for certain stuff.
So I don't think they actually tell you
their internal representation of who you are.
But you just get to see a couple of categories,
like male, 25 to 35, interested in computers,
interested in, et cetera.
I'm sure they keep it at a level somewhere.
You could cross-correlate that with geography
and be like, this is the manliest level in a circle.
Is there anything in Facebook that
would help us get a commonsense database, or is it?
There's no cause for that.
Or is there no useful knowledge?
Must be something that could.
Well, apparently, a few years back
for how we was in this class, somebody
made a program that could find out who was gay or not,
even if they don't put gay or not gay on their profile,
based on who their friends are.
Yeah, my friend was gay when he found out.
Well, see, this is not a statistical correlation.
It's actually useful, because you
can specify that you're looking for someone
who is 0.75 female.
How many women's names begin with the letter X?
Begin with?
The letter X. That may be your problem.
No.
Yes, it could be.
I heard that China is allowing more names.
Is it allowing?
Well, I read an article which said there are only
about 100 names in most of China.
And in fact, there was a law that both your names
have to be from this small set.
And so there are only 10,000 different pairs of names.
Do I mean that?
Yeah.
Family names?
Are there a lot of family names?
Well, I feel like there aren't really restrictions for names,
as long as they're Chinese characters.
I heard about a lawsuit in China where somebody wanted
to name their kid something-something.com
in the government.
But as long as you pick real Chinese characters,
you can name your kid Big Poopyhead, and it's OK.
In fact, naming your kid Big Poopyhead
is actually rather common in the countryside,
because there's some superstition that
believes that if your kid has a really terrible name,
then he won't die during childhood,
because even the devil won't want him.
And for all that we know, it's true.
I was like, I'm just thinking about killing him.
Cobble says knowledge.
Are you only allowed one first and last name now?
Because it seems like you should only need two names,
and then just give everyone at most 64 names,
and that should cover all of China.
Well, I think in Chinese, it's like,
there's a set of last names that's pretty much standard.
And I'm not sure how many, but maybe a few hundred.
And then given names.
So family names are usually one character,
but occasionally they're two characters.
And given names are either one or two characters.
And you just get those two?
And you can pick any character.
Oh, well, there are a lot of characters.
Yeah.
Like several thousand?
So it's something like 1,000 by 1,000 or?
Or 3,000.
3,000 by 3,000 by maybe another 3,000.
The British solution is to just keep adding simple names.
Like my brother's name is Dylan Neville Thomas Bedford.
And you can just keep changing that name.
And then if you get stuck with too many John Smiths,
you just do thirds, fourths, fifths.
Well, the article I read must have been wrong then.
I misunderstood it.
Because it said somewhere, areas of China,
there are only 100 names.
So if you have more than 10,000 people,
you get people with the same name.
Anyway, that's their problem.
Maybe the person who wrote the article
couldn't tell the difference between their friend Xu
and their friend Xu.
Well, one thing that they also did historically in China
is that sometimes people have middle names.
And the middle name is based on this thing that
was written centuries ago that for each generation,
it has a set character that must be your middle name.
So your name will be like family name, this middle name,
and then your actual given name.
So I don't know.
But that's sort of like becoming more obsolete nowadays.
Well, in English, we have lots of names
like farmer and painter and so forth.
But people don't live up to them much.
Because it's difficult to tell what a given baby is
going to do.
But you can order it around.
But actually, the historic Chinese system
is kind of an interesting way of addressing people,
like indexing people.
Because you have the first character, which is the family.
And then the second character is the generation.
And then the third character is you.
So it's like if your family is X and you're from generation A,
then your siblings will be like XAB, XAC, whatever.
And then the next generation will be like XB, whatever.
OK, maybe I should have picked a different outfit instead.
But you know what I mean.
Oh, a generation number?
Kind of, except for it's a character.
There should be enough IPV6 as an example.
I do agree that you're just going to end up
with us all being numbers in X.
But that being said, I've always wanted
to name my kids something that rhymes with the letter like 1,
2, 3, 4, so that I can just call them by their number
without them realizing that I'm calling them by their number.
That's a great idea.
I picked 1 instead of X.
1, serving me a name.
It could be the number of letters in the name, like 4.
I just want to start with, please.
You name your fourth kid Forrest.
Fork, I'm here.
Or name your third kid Tray.
Eventually, the name could be longer,
and it could be a whole little semantic net
with a little list structure in it.
There was a nice science fiction story about some culture
where you had to know your genealogy back
hundreds of generations.
I forgot the author.
But it was made into a movie.
Well, who wants the last word?
That's good.
Someone else can have it.
Yeah, do we have any announcement to make?
No, just final projects we do on Sunday.
That's it.
Do you know what you're teaching next semester?
We're trying to make a plan for some kind of weekly seminar
that's not for credit, although I
might have to make it for credit for financial reasons,
or nobody will pay me.
But we could go back to giving everyone A's again.
So you won't be teaching this subject until next fall, then?
I guess not.
I haven't absolutely decided, but I'm pretty sure.
Can they take your class?
How many students do you have each year?
Well, we've got room for about 40,
and usually about 120 sign up.
Mm-hmm.
And then you weed them out?
Yes.
I'd like to borrow your weeding program.
OK, well, thank you all for coming, and it's been fun.
Thank you.