The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
So I think I've talked about this before a little bit,
but as you know, the longevity in the developed countries
was increasing about one year every four
since the introduction of antibiotics.
So I suppose a moderate fraction of that
is due to the advances in killing germs
and developing new vaccines and so forth.
The lifespan in underdeveloped countries
is much more affected than the developed ones
by things like tuberculosis and malaria and AIDS
and a few things like that.
But what I expect is that there'll
be a bunch of breakthroughs in the next few years.
By few, I mean 20 or 30.
There's been an almost alarming lack of development
of new antibiotics in the last 20 years
so that the conquest of infectious diseases
actually slowed down in recent years.
And now we're getting into some strange problems
about some of the drugs suddenly hugely increasing in prices
because of no one knows exactly what.
But I'm beginning to wonder whether the patent system should
be removed for developments in public health
just because the pharmacy companies claim
that evaluating a new drug is very expensive,
with the order of a billion dollars.
And so that's 1,000 million.
And so they have to price the new drugs at very high rates.
But I suspect that if you took the valuation out
of the hands of commerce and set up some other kind of system,
then we could collect public health records
on everybody in the world or all the people
on Facebook, which is almost the same thing,
and find some way to collect medical records efficiently
at much lower costs.
And then when there's a new drug,
you evaluate it as best you can on guinea pigs and drosophila
and rats and people like that.
And then let people volunteer, maybe pay them,
and collect a lot more data much more quickly.
So anyway, if it doesn't happen in the United States,
maybe some other countries like China
will face the problem of rising health costs
and do something about it.
Who has something to discuss?
So I have a quick question, or it may not be quick.
If in the future we decide to let robots
take care of the elderly, are we also
going to trust them to take care of our children,
and if so, to educate them?
And with that, in the future, are artificial intelligences
going to become teachers?
Well, the arithmetic is sort of funny
because there'll be a huge number of elderly
because we have no idea how productive the people between
age 100 and 200 will be.
And presumably, if we're talking about the next 100 years,
there'll be the consequences of global warming and things
like that.
So I don't know how many children there'll be.
But once the machines are smart enough,
then the idea of smart educational programs will.
I mean, just imagine if a teacher knew most of what
you know.
Then, of course, somebody would have to design or make
some plans for how to adapt to each child
and ask, what should the child learn next?
But it's not clear that what teachers
do with classes of 20 to 40 people,
it's not clear that the decisions they make
are particularly good either.
So yeah.
At that point, what's left for humans to do?
Well, you mean as soon as the machines
are smarter than the people?
Sure.
Well, you could ask what's left for Tyrannosaurus Rex to do.
What do you think people should do?
I guess the usual answer is, we'll
let robots take care of the intellectual things,
or I guess the more work-based things.
We'll do the leisurely, having fun, and artistic activities.
But robots might take part in those, too.
Well, yeah.
I think you're asking a very hard question, namely,
what should we be thinking about our future?
Because along with the next 100 years
of making brains healthier, no one
knows how to fix Alzheimer's, for example.
And that's becoming maybe the most expensive single disease
now that all of the usual diseases have disappeared.
So one solution, which has been discussed for years
by people like Hans Moravec and a few others,
is can you scan the human brain and copy it into a ROM
and then become immune to biological diseases?
Because once you've got the data,
then you can write all sorts of software
to prevent software viruses.
So I think in the next 100 years,
we might learn enough about how things are stored in the brain
to start copying the brain.
And that's another way out or in or whatever you want to call it.
Who wants to be copied into a Macintosh?
And then how many copies should you have?
And what to do with the backups?
Didn't I mention Arthur Clarke's The City and the Stars?
And the novel he wrote twice.
One was against the fall of night,
and the other was The City and the Stars.
And I can't remember which was later.
But he rewrote the first novel because he
realized computers were going to be important.
But in any case, that was the story
in which the planet Earth has maybe a billion people.
But all but a few million are stored in ROMs here and there.
And you come out every 1,000 years and live 100 years.
I forget the arithmetic.
In fact, when you ask a question like,
what should we do with people, I forget.
But my usual instinct is to say, as far as I know,
the only people who have thought a lot about that
are in that little known world called science fiction.
And people like Larry Niven, and David Brin, and Greg Egan,
and Greg Benford.
There's maybe two dozen people who, in my view,
have better ideas about things that
might happen in the future and what
we might do about it than any of the reputable philosophers
or sociologists or futurists who all seem like they're
very good at looking seven years ahead.
And no respectable futurist looks 100 years ahead.
And there are too many possibilities.
In fact, I once gave a talk on this telepresence stuff.
And it was at a meeting.
And the writer Larry Niven was there.
And somebody ordered him to write up,
write an article on what I said about future robots.
And when it came out, it was a pleasure
to see how articulate I had been with it.
It's nothing like having a really first-rate writer
paraphrase what you said.
Are there any great writers at MIT?
You?
No, no.
Who's the best writer here?
That's silly, right?
There's no best.
What's the name of the science fiction writer who used to?
Joe Holderman, he's a good futurist.
Is he still active?
What?
Yeah, well, go to it.
OK.
So anyway, that Chinese situation is interesting.
I don't know what they mean by a million robots.
But I sort of assembled a slide about the current situation.
I can't find it.
But I haven't seen any really exciting advances
in robotics for quite a while.
And it would be nice to know if this Foxconn company has
anything really interesting.
But how many human hours does it take to make an iPhone?
Any of you have how much labor is involved in?
Including the design or just manufacturing?
Manufacturing.
Anybody know what is the manufacturing
cost of the thing?
Is it $5 or $100?
I think it's $200 of change, if I remember correctly.
Most of that's from the flash storage.
Well, flash is?
It seems to be around $180.
$180?
Mm-hmm.
I guess probably the Apple ones are very up to date.
So they haven't had the cost reduction of mass production.
But I wonder how many hours of work
it takes to make the thing.
Can you ask Google that?
Do they estimate that it costs $8 to manufacture,
with the majority of the rest of the cost being parts?
So if you want to estimate based on the going away
for Chinese laborers these days, and then figure out
eight hours, I mean $8, it probably
can't be significantly more than eight hours or something.
Well, just popping all the things into the box
can't be terribly hard, but making the chips.
At the computer store, I was there the other day,
and it said only two hard disks to a customer.
And this is because there's a flood in Korea.
And something like half the hard disks in the world
are made in one small area there.
It says only two to a customer.
Hm.
But that's how much is the, what's
the ratio of flash memory cost to hard disk cost?
Hard disks are about $1 a gigabyte, half that.
They're almost comparable.
Is that possible?
Hard disks probably cost less than $1 a gigabyte.
You can get a 1 terabyte, right?
$8.
How much is a terabyte?
Like $80.
OK, great.
That sounds familiar.
How much memory do you think you need?
I made some estimates in an old article,
but I don't have much confidence in them.
Alan Newell did a survey among psychologists and literature
about memory.
And he concluded that if you take all the published
psychological experiments that he could find,
then over a long period, no human
could memorize more than one bit every two seconds.
And there's 30 million seconds in a year.
So that's 4 megabytes.
But you're not doing, you're not memorizing all the time,
or maybe you are.
So if it's just a megabyte or two per year,
then in 100 years, it's just a couple of hundred megabytes.
So copying a human should be really easy
if you only knew what the bytes were
and what they represent, et cetera.
And it seems low, but I agree with the pretty low estimate,
because I think our compression algorithms are really,
really good in terms of connecting things
to other things as opposed to memorizing a few things.
So we probably have really good compression.
Yeah, now, probably those experiments
don't say much about, for each of these items,
how many others it gets connected to.
So.
And also, how many bits is each connection?
Because those sort of take up.
Yeah, because if something can be connected to 30 million
others, then that's 25 bits for each.
It's not so much.
So if you believe that stuff, that
means that making a machine that knows as much as a person,
it shouldn't be very hard in terms of manufacturing.
It's just that we don't really have the slightest idea of how
to represent that knowledge.
And I mean, I've got a slide here somewhere about what
do you do with a fragment of knowledge?
Well, how do you retrieve it?
You ought to know something about it
has to be linked to something about what kind of problems
it might be relevant to solving and what kind of purposes
it might serve to activate that statement or fact.
In fact, generally, I sort of agree
with the old theories of Roger Schenck
that it doesn't make much sense to store things like facts,
although maybe a few million of them,
like books are made of paper, usually make sense.
But Schenck's idea was that it would
be very hard to use random fragments of knowledge
unless they were connected into stories.
And what's a story?
A story is not just a string of sentences.
For a story to be called a story,
it must engage the listener in a certain way,
or else they'd say, why are you telling me
these strings of assertions?
So what's in a standard story?
Most stories are about people.
And there's usually a main character, maybe two,
but there's a point of view usually.
And that's because it's not just a character,
but it's a character with a problem.
So a story starts out with a situation or develops one.
And typically, then something goes wrong.
If nothing goes wrong, then you're back to the,
why are you wasting my time with this?
So if some problem comes up, and the hero tries to solve it,
and he tries something, and that just
makes it worse, so that didn't work.
And then he tries something else,
or somebody comes to help, or whatever you want.
And eventually, the problem gets broken into subproblems,
and solutions appear, and everything's wrapped up,
even if it's like a Greek tragedy,
which everything is wrapped up by everyone
being dead at the end.
What was that Oedipus story?
The first one is Oedipus Rax.
They are also known as the three Thebian Plates.
What's that?
The first one is Oedipus Rax, but the three of them
are also often known as the three Thebian Plates.
I'm trying to remember the one where, what's your name?
It's both his daughter and his wife.
That's Rax.
There's also Enthusi and Oedipus.
So those are wonderful stories.
And they haven't changed much in 2,000 years.
It's somebody with a problem, and there's a solution.
And in the most popular ones, the solution
is to kill the person who is causing the trouble.
Anyway, so Roger Schenck has several books
about theories of classifying stories
and how to get a machine.
He doesn't talk about AI very much,
but it's in the background.
And he's saying that the way a machine would be smart
is to have a huge number of stories
so that whatever problem comes up,
maybe you'll have half a dozen stories that give you
a hint about how to deal with that problem.
And if you have enough of those, then you'll get through life,
and people will think you're smart and so forth.
But when Newell did that review of publications about memory,
he didn't ask, how many stories does a person know?
And I don't think I've ever seen any discussion of trying
to estimate this higher level.
Have you ever run?
Dustin, because you're thinking about understanding stories.
Can you understand a story unless you
know a story like it?
I think it's always going to connect to some similar event.
So what's the shortest stories?
If you just have a problem and a solution,
that's a very short story.
What do psychologists do?
That's actually a good question, because until there
was a field called cognitive psychology, which
from our point of view is, how do you do AI
without any technical machinery?
Psychologists didn't have theories
that you could use for much.
The behaviorists had non-stories so
that everything was made of very small fragments of behavior,
like if you smell something bad, run away.
So here's this very short list, and I'd like a bigger one.
I wish Henry were here, because any of you in Lieberman's
project, they're starting to add all sorts of new kinds of links
to the common sense knowledge base.
And I don't know if any of them are going to be able to do that.
So consider that.
What kinds of problems are there?
Anybody have a?
How would you classify?
Can you think of a theory?
Yeah?
You could classify them based on the tools you need to use.
Based on?
The tools you might need to use to solve them.
If there were super classes of tools,
if there were certain types of tools, you could, like,
for example, there are certain problems
that you can solve with an ax, and there are other ones
that you can solve with a piece of string or something.
Yeah.
If you do that, then you're in very good shape.
I guess when I talked about the mind being made
of critics and selectors, and I might have gotten that idea
from somewhere in Freud, that's almost the same thing,
because critics are things that recognize not just
that there's a problem, but they recognize a type of problem.
And a critic is sort of useless unless it
points to some tool or way of thinking
that you might use to solve it.
So where would we look for?
What literature would contain a classification of what
are the problems people face?
You mean medical?
Sure.
Health, survival.
A Darwinian might say all problems are of the same kind,
namely, making sure that you have enough children
that your genes survive.
But of course, the funny part of evolution
is that there isn't any representation anywhere
in the whole thing of that description of what
the whole thing is for.
Yeah.
Maybe all sorts of problems you solve
could be related to your general evolutionary needs
in some way or another.
For example, you can think of a path-finding problem
as you needing to move around in the world
and get places so that you can achieve your goals.
You have problems of social life,
where you try to understand people and figure them out
and manipulate that information to get whatever it is
that you want.
OK, well, I don't think the evolutionary system doesn't
know these, but that's a great idea.
Maybe we just look up the names of all professions,
because a profession, if it has a name,
then somebody has recognized a particular class of problems
as a thing in itself.
That would be a great start.
So there are storytellers, plumbers, and OK,
so that's almost the same as what old, bigger.
So for each thing, for each fragment of knowledge,
there are kinds of purposes it might serve,
but that also applies for each fact and each object.
What purpose does this serve?
If it were 20 years ago, nobody could imagine any purpose.
I was visiting Toshiba one day many years ago
when the first Bluetooth worked.
And I thought they were saying Brutus,
and there was this great demonstration
where the thing was two feet from the computer,
and somebody did something, and the computer did something.
Everybody clapped, and I thought, boy, is that useless.
So for each fragment of knowledge,
well, I don't know what this one is for.
Other things it is similar to.
Well, if a piece of knowledge didn't quite work,
then you would want links to, then that's a subproblem.
I tried to cut this rope, but my scissors were too small.
So if you say, oh, maybe a bigger scissors would do it,
just ordinary kinds of thinking like that
allow you to use knowledge that doesn't quite fit,
if you can characterize.
Oh, well, so maybe the most important thing
is what's the bug here?
So the reason we're so smart is you
see a problem, and something pops into your mind.
I'll try this, and it doesn't quite work.
And then you automatically turn on this whole bunch
of other things, which is other things that this is similar to,
and do they have the same bug?
And can you find something almost situation or a memory
which is very similar, but it doesn't have that bug?
And then you say, well, what's the difference?
It's a sharper knife or a bigger hammer or whatever.
And we're back to the idea that solving problems
is by removing the differences between what you have
and what you want.
And stories are usually about something like that.
The hero has a problem.
There's something that the hero wants, doesn't have.
And you look at a knowledge base and say,
what produces this kind of property or value or change
or difference?
So how many stories could you know if it takes two seconds
to?
And that was the highest rate.
I think they couldn't find any instances
where you could learn a bit every two seconds
for several hours.
But it was easy to find instances
where you could do that for several minutes.
How could you estimate how many stories you know?
There's a minimal boundary on event perception.
If you flash two different colors into somebody's retina,
there's a certain speed at which they
won't be able to detect that there was a change.
Is that like 30 milliseconds or three?
On the order of milliseconds.
But I'm not sure exactly how much.
Wouldn't that vary by sense?
Each sense would have its own.
Yeah, you'd have to, I guess, do it for each modality.
And if they were at a phase, and it's possible
that maybe between multiple ones,
you can do something faster.
I feel like if you're estimating how many stories you know,
shouldn't be like, shouldn't be like,
when you said that you can memorize two bits per second,
I mean, that's like if you took in all your experience
through verbal stories or something,
or information stories.
But I think you learn a lot more just through,
I think you learn maybe more bits than that
through repeated actions that your body knows.
Learn to ice skate or something.
I feel like there's more bits encoded
in that kind of approach.
Well, but it takes you many hours to learn to ice skate well.
Look at sports people.
They practice.
I feel like those kind of things make up a lot of your knowledge
too, not just.
Right, but if you're using a lot of seconds,
then it's making up that fraction.
Well, I just feel like that part of your,
I feel like you make when you learn all those things
through your senses, when you're teaching someone else,
then you make up a story from that.
But it wasn't encoded in you as a story.
Or it was a completely different story
that wouldn't apply to them.
Well, it's just a format.
You could theoretically store a book
as images of the page, or as ASCII encoded characters,
or something like that.
So there's lots of formats.
But I like what you were saying earlier,
where it was like different things.
We have different compression schemes.
So we are really good at compressing and seeing
relationships between multiple tasks.
So we don't need to store different copies
of the same words, or letters, or whatever.
Just have references to them.
Well, you hear stories about people
who can read a whole book and remember the whole thing.
And the question is, are any of them real?
Or are they all amateur magicians
who are fooling you?
Yeah.
About how many stories you might know,
writers tend to think that there aren't that many stories.
Like, people write books and books on how,
no matter how complicated a story looks,
there's the underlying, no hero going through a journey,
that kind of thing.
We might know another few stories,
but just story components that we don't like.
Well, it's true that the most popular stories probably are,
there's 50 or 100 plots that make up 90% of, you know,
it's easy to make up numbers like that.
There certainly is a distribution
for all sorts of psychological things,
where a large amount of your performance
comes from a small number of very useful things.
And then smaller numbers of things,
or on less frequent intervals, you're
using more obscure fragments of knowledge.
Yeah.
I also think that not everything in our heads
is represented as stories.
I mean, I feel like sometimes you do learn a story,
and it's a complete story.
Every time you go through it, it's the same story.
But I think oftentimes, when we learn
individual bits of information or chunks of information,
and then we either create the connections when we learn them
or we develop new connections.
And oftentimes, when we're telling a story,
what we're actually doing is sort
of traversing different paths throughout the bits.
So that one time that we tell the story,
it might be slightly different from the other time.
Or it might take a different path entirely
and branch out.
So these stories have various possibilities and variations.
And it's only a story in the sense
that it has a progression as we construct the path.
Yeah.
I wonder if anybody's tried to take a collection
and represent the whole knowledge in it.
Like if Shakespeare plays, there are lots of people
and their mother.
And the mother is likely to be a queen.
I can't remember the difference between Hamlet and Macbeth
because there are so many features in common.
But of course, once you have a lot of knowledge,
then you may have an experience.
And that might seem very complicated,
but you're actually making two or three links between two
already large structures.
And then each time you think about that, you elaborate it.
So we have this network in our heads.
And when we communicate with other people,
we generally communicate in these so-called stories.
So we could either improvise the entire thing on the spot,
much like what I'm doing right now.
Or we can kind of practice these stories
and then keep the path stored somewhere else
so that the next time you just look at the instructions
that we wrote down and say, OK, so now it's
time to talk about this thing, this thing, that.
You mean plot units, like?
And then these stored paths could also be smaller units
so that you might improvise part of the story
but use the pre-planned out version
for a different segment.
Yeah.
Wendy Leonard was a PhD student, I think,
at UMass Amherst in the 70s.
And she wrote a brilliant thesis
about the structures of stories.
They're things called plot units.
So it's very much of what you were
suggesting, that a new story might
be made by extracting some of the structure of an old story
and putting the new characters and events in.
But it still might have some analogous links
to the old one so that then when you're reading Hamlet,
you say, oh, that's like Macbeth in this respect.
Does Winston have Hamlet?
Or is it all?
Does he have both?
Yeah.
We have both.
What?
Hamlet and Macbeth.
Which place do you have?
Well, actually, we work mostly with Hamlet, Macbeth,
Julian Caesar, Romeo and Juliet.
They're all about the same.
Yeah.
Especially Hamlet and Macbeth.
That's why you can't keep them straight.
Yeah, I was looking at the Oedipus one,
where his daughter is also his sister.
Very complicated.
You didn't get that one in there.
Incest makes the family relations look pretty funny.
So what happened to Wendy Leonard?
Did she ever publish anything after that?
She separated herself from natural language research
because she didn't like the way the center of gravity
was moving towards statistical methods
and went into oriental medicine or something.
Oh, yeah.
I keep them feeling things.
Great loss to Schenck's best student, without a doubt.
I bet if we had a job, we could get her back,
because I talked to her at that reunion the other day.
Well, it's terrible to lose a good student.
In the meantime, Roger Schenck wrote about 15 books,
but I don't know how different they all are.
But everyone should read his first book, which
has a lot of ideas about how things depend on each other
and one another in different ways.
It was called Conceptual Dependency,
and it led to a lot of interesting research
for quite a few years.
Well, what's bothering you?
That's almost the same list.
Oh, sure.
I hadn't thought of looking up.
But the projector went off, too.
Are they correlated?
Or were we wiped out by daylight saving, John?
I don't think so.
It needs to be selected.
It is following up.
That's the good side.
And it's showing it here that it was following up.
Each fragment of knowledge, types of problems
it might help to solve, what kind of goals it could serve.
It's starting up.
What bugs come from using this fragment of knowledge?
What are typical cases?
And maybe most important, if you have a fragment of knowledge,
what kind of contextual cues is going to get it to be retrieved?
So having things in memory is no use
unless you have links to them, and how do you learn those?
Is that slide actually the same as the one I had before?
That's, yep, bugs that might come from using it.
So that certainly is, I'm trying to guess how many of you
were around when something called new math started
to be taught.
Does that ring a bell?
Do you remember it?
It wasn't there that early.
It was a period when some group of mathematicians
said, this is terrible.
Children aren't learning about the empty set.
And then they realized that there
they realized that there was a committee of really very good
mathematicians who thought things
should be more clear and precise.
And you should distinguish between ratios and fractions
and quotients and percentages.
And oh, god, there were nine of them.
And explaining the difference between ratios and fractions,
bleh.
And distinguish between nothing and the empty set.
And so a short generation, I think it was five or six years
till finally the teachers admitted
they couldn't understand what they were talking about.
But it was very exciting, and I remember mathematicians
feeling that this was great because the public was going
to learn more about what they were doing.
Quotients.
But it did go back to Russell and Whitehead,
and they explained to children that you could start
with the set that only contains one subset, namely
the empty set.
And that one of them is 0.
I think the empty set is not 0 because that
wouldn't be quite right.
But the set that contains only the empty set could be 0.
And then the set that contains that could be 1.
And that was one proposal of Russell and Whitehead.
But I think they found that wasn't quite good enough.
And so they got the idea that 2 should be maybe
should be 1 and the set that only I've forgotten.
The numbers were becoming ordered pairs.
I'm sorry I've forgotten what Russell and Whitehead did.
But of course, what Russell and Whitehead did
was explain numbers and then explain fractions
and then explain limits and then dedicant sets,
which are sets of rationals that have an upper bound
but don't contain the upper, may or may not be closed.
And they got all the way up to number theory
and calculus and continuity, stuff like that.
And making all of that out of the empty set
was quite a tour de force.
But the idea of teaching that to children
actually swept the country for maybe five or six years.
I wonder what they learned in computer science.
Great.
Don't you think there's a problem with just
trying to teach computers common sense with stories,
with textual stories?
Do you think there's a natural limit
to how useful a system like that could be?
I'm not sure what you mean by useful.
Aren't there pieces of knowledge or wisdom
that you could never really get from just
like a collection of stories?
Well, it depends on who you think the story is.
If the story includes recipes, then it
includes learning how to do calculus problems.
I think someone might argue that it would be very hard
to teach a computer what smells mean if it didn't have a nose.
But on the other hand, you could make
a simulation of a sense organ, which just has
10,000 different bit strings.
And you could decide that this represented a rotten egg
and this represented such and such.
And then if you had enough stories,
the computer would act as though it
had a humanoid collection of records of experiences.
So it's hard to you can sort of make some arbitrary statement
I think a computer could not understand x or y.
But if you think about it, you might say, well,
I don't understand how people do it.
So maybe if I got more scientists to study it,
we could, in fact, understand how people represent
smells in their brains and the problem would go away.
So generally, if you have a feeling
that there's something that a machine cannot do,
it would be very hard to defend that indefinitely
because every year, we discover new representations
and new languages and new kinds of processes.
Yeah?
Sure.
I just wanted to throw an idea out there
to respond to whether there is a limit.
It seems like as long as the machine
is equipped with the ability to understand stories
and generate stories, there should be no limit.
Because I remember, OK, I think it's because in 6.034,
one time Professor Wilson asked us
what happens if you run down the street with a bucket full
and we all knew what would happen if the water would just
spill and it was not because we didn't necessarily
run with a bucket of water, but we
were able to simulate that kind of story in our heads.
And so as long as you have a machine that
is able to generate stories, it doesn't even
have to know all the stories ever
because it can make its own stories to answer questions.
Thank you.
Well, I guess we have a very stratified society.
And there are lots of people who feel
that because a computer is mechanical or something
or because it's understandable, which is worse,
then there must be things it couldn't do
because I'm trying to characterize
this collection of ordinary people and philosophers.
And my favorite example is the idea of a qualia, a quail.
People talked about qualia because there's
a word in English called qualities.
But if you're going to be respectable,
you have to find the Latin word for something.
And so there is a very popular branch
of philosophy in which people argue that, well, machines
can do this and that.
But there are some things that are innately
by their nature irreducible.
And for example, the experience of redness
is a sort of absolute and not reducible
to combinations of other concepts or activities
or processes or synonym, synonym, synonym.
And what could lead someone to argue
that something is, in that sense, irreducible,
cannot be described in terms of other things?
Well, one thing that could lead you to that idea
is that ordinarily, you like to think
that a good description of something
is an expression that entirely consists of simpler things
than the thing you're describing.
That's reducing something to other things that are simpler.
If you say something is irreducible,
are there some synonyms for that?
And they say, well, you can't reduce red.
What?
Atomic?
Yeah, sort of like atomic.
I remember you being told that green was
a mixture of yellow and blue.
So that gets rid of green, doesn't it?
But anyway, that's a very strange idea,
because maybe the right explanation,
I'm sure there's no baby about it,
is that redness is a complicated combination of things
that are more complicated than it.
So the word reduce isn't the right thing.
For some mental things, one part of the brain
gets a bunch of inputs, and it says red,
and that's the output.
But the inputs might be a whole collection
of very complicated things.
I think I sort of tried to list, like when you were a little kid
and you got cut and you were bleeding,
or you ate a red pepper and your mouth felt terrible,
or there's a sunset, and there are
lots and lots of different things
that give rise to this sensation of redness.
And to say that it's irreducible is to say,
oh, the part of my brain that said that word
didn't have a good theory of what combination of origins
the inputs to it came from.
So I'm afraid that if you look up
criticisms of artificial intelligence on the web,
you'll find, what's his name?
Steven, who's the Qualia guy?
[? Grossberg? ?] No.
Louder.
I forget.
But if you look for the combination
of artificial intelligence and philosophy,
you'll find droves of people who are sort of arguing that,
well, machines can do this and that,
but they'll never really be people
or they'll never really think, because there
are these problems like the problem of irreducible Qualia.
And there's no way a machine could have anything like that.
And then if you ask, well, how could a person have that?
And they say, well, I won't tell you,
but I think I understand it.
Yeah?
Would you respond to the argument,
the more reasonable version of that argument, which is that,
sure, we may one day be able to build
a machine that emulates human intelligence and consciousness,
whatever those things mean.
But it won't actually be intelligent or conscious,
because it'll be simulating intelligence.
By analogy, if you built a simulation
of the digestive system, it would be simulating digestion.
It wouldn't actually be digesting anything.
So if you built a machine.
Yeah, I've seen the one.
Steven Pinker, I think, does that.
He says, or Searle, you simulate a thunderstorm,
but the things aren't really wet.
Well, foo, wetness is what?
If you look into wetness carefully, it goes away,
and it's molecules of hydrogen oxide,
which are sticking to oily things with the hydrogen side,
and they're sticking to ionic sides,
things with the oxygen size.
And the reason the water sticks to some things and wets them
is because it's a polar molecule,
and it has a charge here and no charge there.
And the hydrogen likes to bond to the other hydrogens.
The oxygen likes to, if the hydrogen
is pulling the electrons here, the oxygen
likes to stick to these things there.
And the idea of wetness is where it turns out
to be not an irreducible, unachievable thing,
but a rather complicated thing that only a advanced quantum
mechanics theory can even approximate.
But how does that respond to the argument?
Because we're not trying to simulate the brain atom
by atom.
We're trying to simulate something
I'm saying to say there's no wetness in the brain.
It's saying there's no process that
corresponds to this oxidation reduction electron sharing
thing.
And the answer is, yes, there are.
Every neuron that doesn't have a myelin sheath
is probably wet here and there.
And who cares?
It's full.
I actually disagree with your analogy on digestion.
What you're saying is, OK, well, whatever
metaphor that you have on digestion.
So what you're saying is, basically, we're
trying to simulate the digestive system
by building it on a computer.
But I think that what we're actually
trying to do, like the equivalent for the brain,
is if we actually build a digestive system using
different physical materials, but it still chemically
digests the things.
No, but I'm saying this.
That would be an obvious feeling,
trying to build the brain by looking up
a bunch of wires to be off your arms.
No, what I'm saying is that there's
no such thing as wetness.
Wetness is a very, very complicated collection
of processes.
And you can have, in the brain, very complicated collections
of processes, which are similar but not exactly the same.
And who cares?
Why do you think it's important?
So basically, you're saying if you build the brain,
or if you build whatever thing out of a different material
then it can't possibly do the same things, which
is like a flawed argument.
No, I'm not saying that.
Oh, not you.
I said that John's rule.
I'm saying it's not important what the lower
levels of the brain do, because at least in my case,
I think that there's an insulation layer in the brain,
which is something like the cortical columns, which
protect the higher levels of thinking
from the weird and unreliable processes
that individual synapses and nerve cells have.
So the great thing is that our brain is
simulating a computer, and our higher level thinking
is of the more or less digital nature,
no matter what the neuroscientists will tell you.
That is, why do we have these columns?
And my answer is, it's the same reason
why computer have flip flops instead of transistors.
The computer is really analog, but it's
designed so that the awful properties of analog things
don't interfere with what it's doing.
Another way to respond to that would be, I think, OK,
two systems are equivalent if given the same input,
they have the same output, right?
Maybe in simulating the digestive tract,
then maybe you're not entirely successful.
Well, OK, well, you're not giving the exact same input
you're not giving some sort of system that's simulated there.
But if you have a machine which, given the same input
as humans are given, such as knowledge, sensory input,
and stuff, they are able to produce the same kinds
of outputs that humans produce, such as, I don't know,
making inferences or reacting to these inputs,
then essentially you have in your hands
a successful simulation, a system that you cannot
distinguish from the original.
Right, but couldn't you have the same,
you could have the same inputs and outputs
for simulating some organ system that's not simulated?
Sure, then maybe the digestive system
is not simulated well, because you're not, OK, but, sorry,
I interrupted you as you were saying something.
But, OK, maybe the digestive system, for example,
doesn't really work because what's happening
is you're doing this in a digital medium where, really,
your inputs and outputs to the system
that you're trying to simulate is not the inputs
that you're using in your simulation.
However, in your simulation of a brain on a machine,
your inputs could very much be the same things.
Yeah, well, you're simulating that the digestive system,
your inputs are virtual.
Exactly, so, yeah, so maybe it has to do with your inputs
having the correct representation and the exact same thing,
the same nature that your inputs in the real world have.
Now, like, who cares if your AI is philosophically equivalent
to a brain, like, as long as it does these little things?
Well, that's an interesting question.
Yeah, from an engineering point of view,
you don't care from a philosophical point of view,
you care.
Especially if you want to live forever,
then you don't want to have the biological bugs.
Whatever.
It seems to me like it's a little bit...
Without change, it depends, yeah.
It seems to me like it's a little bit like
railing against differential equations.
Of course, the model is always a surrogate for the real thing,
but it still tells us about the constraints
that the real thing has to obey,
and so that's why it's a model.
Right, but then, like, an artificial intelligence,
whatever intelligence system is a model of the brain.
Which is fine, but, which is fine,
I mean, just, like, the claim of this argument
is that it's not that cautious.
It's not quite...
It's not in a trivial sense, it certainly isn't.
The question is, does it shed light on the thing,
if that's the thing you're trying to understand.
I think the problem comes when you...
Wetness is one thing,
but when you come to consciousness,
the same people,
in my caricature of them, Pinker and others,
is that there's a fluid called consciousness,
and it's a kind of wetness, and it's irreducible.
There's just this raw understanding, knowing things.
It's like being wet, as opposed to dry,
and to me, that's nutty,
because I didn't have any trouble
listing 40 other English words
that look like they're in the same suitcase,
like having a limited but measurable
amount of short-term memory
about what you were recently thinking.
Now, it's hard to think of a drop of water
as having that, but of course, it does to some degree.
It's left some...
When it rolled down the side of your cheek,
it left a little stream of evaporating water,
and so what?
Your model may or may not bother to say
wherever the water drops been,
it will leave some of itself,
but it just depends what you're trying to compute,
and in the case of consciousness,
if that is a suitcase word of 40 rather different processes,
maybe we could very well do without 10 of them,
and there's probably 15 more that if we had,
we would hold regular people in utter contempt,
because I can hear too many words
in two tunes at once, and maybe half of you can,
and when I think of a third tune,
this is because as a baby,
I spent a lot of time developing the skill,
so I look at people listening to music,
and I know that some of them, like Todd Macover,
are hearing more than I am,
and most of them are just hearing,
bub, bub, bub, bub, bub, bub,
and getting a great deal of stupid pleasure out of it,
so thinking of psychological words as like things
is usually a big mistake,
because they're abbreviations for,
they're not combinations of elementary things,
they're combinations of more complicated things.
It doesn't stop anywhere, yeah.
Okay, to play the devil's advocate again,
how would you respond to the Chinese room?
The Chinese room, it understands English Chinese perfectly.
I don't see any problem if it can answer questions in Chinese.
Why does Searle think that just because it is a machine,
it doesn't really understand them?
Because if it gives the right answers,
yes, it really understands them in the sense
that the word understand means 40 different things,
most of which Searle hasn't allowed himself to even imagine,
and any Chinese room that has 11 or 12 of them
would probably understand Chinese better than Searle,
only talks of, does he know Chinese?
Where's the understanding?
You know how Herbert Simon got the Nobel Prize?
He learned Swedish.
Sorry.
Where in the system is the understanding?
Are you just saying that the system overall
has understanding?
The idea that there's a thing called-
Of course there's no understanding,
and like a set of rules.
There isn't anything, given any word,
there's no such thing.
That word is an abbreviation for 15 or 20
various different things.
Understanding isn't anywhere.
Understanding is knowing grammar,
having short-term memory,
being able to criticize a story by recognizing the bugs.
If you give yourself five minutes,
you'll write 40 different requirements for understanding.
And then the idea that there's some thing,
that's too complicated, bottle cap.
There's some thing, which is the raw understanding,
just like a bottle cap,
except that nobody knows what it is.
What silly people.
Why did they think there is,
just because they have a word,
why did they think there's something to go with that word?
Well, because other people understand it.
Well, when all the gerbils are,
what's the animal that allegedly runs over the cliff
into the ocean?
Lemmings.
Do they understand how important it is
to run over the cliff?
I don't know what I'm illustrating.
Can I ask what you think that Chinese-Rome argument
would help, what kind of bearing would it have on AI as a whole?
That one?
No?
Sorry.
Oh, I was asking you what bearing do you think
this argument has on AI in general?
Because I would assume that there's plenty of serious people
who work on AI that would not say,
just because you can respond to certain questions,
that you are intelligent, right?
Humans do a lot more things.
Right, so it's intended not,
the argument is intended to be an argument against strong AI
because the argument is intended to say,
look, this system appears to understand Chinese,
but there doesn't seem to actually be anything
that's understanding Chinese.
Therefore, a properly programmed computer
doesn't literally understand what it's doing.
Well, the problem is the argument applies to you, too.
So you have a memory and you have processes
that operate on that memory.
So it's just like Cyril's room.
So, Cyril's room isn't intelligent either.
Let me try this.
Please explain Cyril's Chinese room argument.
I'm sure if you didn't say clearly what it said.
It said, the experiment is the centerpiece
of Cyril's Chinese room argument,
which holds that a program can be used to explain the mind.
I'm skipping the dots.
The study of the brain is irrelevant
to the study of the mind.
It goes on.
If you want to know anything, download Dragon's search.
I could ask you.
It got antiquated the other night
when I asked it who married their mother or father
or whatever it was.
Just thinking about something else.
The idea of you understand things through stories.
I feel like it's been like bugging writers,
pay rise, and people who do TVs a lot.
It feels like a common understanding
among these group of people.
We're not psychologists, not computer scientists,
but they share a somewhat common belief.
What they have trouble with is sometimes
when things happen, say a documentary or a TV show,
their facts or just happenings that do not fit
into a story model, those are not understood.
Whatever, and they've been having trouble with that.
They've been exploiting that fact.
It's just interesting.
Well, sometimes somebody will talk,
and if you don't see a story, you get confused,
or you say, what's the point?
Does that mean you're not understanding
or you're criticizing, I guess?
It's almost like in order to relay information,
you have to put them into a form that's understandable,
that those people think are stories.
Sometimes a child has a favorite story,
and she wants you to tell it over and over.
What's going on then?
Do you have a favorite story?
When I was like four years old, about four years old,
I basically watched The Lion King just all day,
and I was like, oh my God, I'm going to die.
I was like, oh my God, I'm going to die.
Just all day.
The whole day?
I did the same thing over and over and over.
I don't know that anymore.
Sexist, racist, and fascist.
The devil, the rise, the fall of the light.
Uh-huh.
It's okay.
That was my Shakespearean 16th century movie.
What's the most popular story in the world?
For four-year-olds.
Some fairy tale probably.
Oh, for four-year-olds.
I thought you said for four euros.
Sorry, I just got back from school.
How did you do that?
You played it back and forth over several times?
Like realizing what it actually was.
You replayed the tape.
I don't know.
What?
I'm saying you replayed the tape that says four-year-olds.
Oh, yeah.
I heard four euros, and then that's how I made my comment.
And then Tang Tang was like, wait, for four-year-olds?
And I was like, oh, wait.
I guess I could have misheard.
When I was little, my favorite story was The Three Little Pigs.
And my mom would tell it to me when I was going to bed.
But it was a time when she was also very tired.
So she would kind of change the story each time.
And I think that's why I like to hear it.
I knew the actual story.
And my mom would be really tired after a day of work.
And she would be falling asleep in the middle of the story
and saying wrong things about the story.
And I would just point it out to her.
I would tell her, no, that's not how it goes.
Tell it right.
So I don't know if the reason you want to hear the same story
over and over again is somehow to,
if you have a very concrete template of it,
to figure out what can go differently
and then consolidate that somehow.
I don't know why you would want to do it.
I feel like it's a lot like finding a favorite song
that you keep listening to over and over again.
It has to be between the trivial level of you pretty much
have been quoted the whole song in your head
and some rock man enough character that you really don't understand.
It has to be between, it has to be lyrical enough
so that there's parts that you understand.
But it's enough information that you haven't distilled it all
into your memory.
So you don't always know what's coming next
as you're listening to it again.
Could it just be for entertainment?
You just really like the story?
You'd like to be able to predict what's
going to happen next maybe.
Just you're rewarding your memory for being right.
So if you change a story a little bit,
they get really angry.
I have a story.
I had a little daughter who's now in her 40s.
But anyway, we would be driving,
as it happens, down Beacon Street in Brookline.
And every now and then she would shout, care.
And this was a baby who didn't like to go to sleep.
So she would fuss, and the only way to get her to be sleepy
was to take her for a ride.
Anyway, we'd be driving along, and she would yell, care.
And she's only two, so I couldn't figure out
what was this going on.
And then one day we were home, and there was a television set
on, and she yelled, care.
And it was an advert.
Do you know the Charitable Organization, CARE?
They collect food for, maybe it's disappeared.
Anybody heard of CARE lately?
It's gone.
Anyway, the feature of CARE is that it's showing a big box
full of packages, and on the side of the box
it's stenciled, C-A-R-E, in the stencil font.
Stencil font is such that the middle of the O
is attached by two little tabs so it won't fall out.
So it turned out that what she was doing was font recognition.
And next time we were driving, I was
able to correlate it with the numbers
stenciled on the telephone poles.
So you could watch this child for a long time
and never guess what on earth it's doing.
And it's recognizing a font.
How weird.
I don't know what the point of this story is,
but it's really hard to tell what people are thinking
before they can try.
Before they can talk.
Actually, she designs fonts now sometimes.
Maybe I could get two of you to argue.
Yes?
I have a question.
We kind of talked about how we would store stories
and why we would do that.
But do we have any idea of how we make the decision
whether to remember a story or not?
On the number?
No, just say you hear, OK, it seems
like it would be unmanageable if you
tried to commit to memory everything you ever heard.
Oh, right.
So somehow you need to determine whether something
is worth learning or not.
And in the case of stories, how do you decide
whether you should learn it or not?
That's a great question.
What's the answer?
Do psychologists?
Surprise it if you can remember it.
There has to be something unusual about it?
Surprise, slogan, symbol, thing like that.
Something maybe you can learn from it.
There must be theories of what things people remember.
I mean, I think when there is a very,
when the story or the event is attached
to a very intense emotion, you'll tend to remember it.
Well, as Pat says, there has to be some new information.
You don't remember anything either.
If it's, I mean, when you go to class,
you don't understand anything, you don't remember it.
If it's stuff you already know, you don't remember it.
So it's got to be on that wave front of understanding
if we can remember anything.
But then it has to be connected to something.
So it has to have some, you have to have some reason
why to connect it to something.
You may not know that.
You just don't want to be surprised, maybe.
So you have to store all surprises away
so they won't annoy you later.
Well, if we're sufficiently shocked or surprised,
whether we want to or not, we won't forget it.
The 9-11 disaster, the Kennedy assassination,
things like that can't be forgotten.
Apollo 11.
They have a problem on the freshman physics quiz.
I will never forget it.
Well, doesn't that explain maybe why you go through the day
and then when people ask you, what have you done,
the things you remember?
Or you don't remember the leaves falling on the sky?
Or you don't think that's relevant?
I don't know.
It seems like, the more I think about it,
it seems like it should also have something at least
to do with what stories you already know.
Because this comes from kind of a shallow place,
but when you go shopping for clothes,
you tend to pick out, you know what your wardrobe looks like
and you kind of pick out things that will make some sort of sense
within that wardrobe.
And you already know all the stories that you know,
so maybe in the background you have some sort of process
that's going on, trying to figure out whether this new story
is something that you can connect meaningfully
to your already existing model.
So that's not quite surprise.
But it's filling a goal, maybe.
It brings me back to wondering what psychologists do.
Yeah?
So I have a different question.
There seems to be sort of a problem,
but it's something I'm confused about.
So we postulate that artificial intelligence is
trying to create an intelligent machine,
but it doesn't really define what intelligent means.
So we say, okay, intelligent is equivalent to human intelligence.
So then we say, okay, how are we going to figure out
if we've built something that's equivalent to human intelligence?
We don't know, because a computer is much better
than a human in some things, and currently a human
is much better than a computer in other things.
So, I mean, there's a way to say this by, okay,
our equivalence metric is the Turing test,
but that doesn't seem to be a good metric,
because, I mean, there's already some random, you know,
like scripts and things that pass the Turing test
just by doing a few clever things,
because fooling people isn't that hard,
because people are pretty stupid.
So how do we define intelligence and figure out
if we've built in, like, what it means
to build an artificial intelligence?
Well, some things are so obvious that you don't define them.
I mean, how do you define good?
So, I mean, I don't know anybody working
on artificial intelligence who feels any need to define it,
because, you know, each project is trying to do something
that they couldn't do last year, in most cases.
And how do you get the right,
how do you answer questions about a story?
How do you get a machine to read a book?
Right, because there's currently a lot of things
that we know that a human can do,
but we haven't yet built machines that can do that,
so we can solve those specific subproblems
Well, but maybe we can.
But some of them we've been trying to solve
for 40 or 50 years and haven't.
And I don't see any...
I don't think any of us think in those terms.
It's saying we're trying to make the machine smarter.
We're not trying to make it intelligent or smart.
We're trying to make it intelligenter or smarter.
And if you can't tell, then you didn't do it.
I've had that argument along with Seymour Papert,
people who were trying to evaluate
whether children who learned logo in second grade
were at some sort of advantage
than children who didn't know anything
about computational concepts and so forth.
I hate to mention it, but at a certain point
in the National Science Foundation budget
for educational projects,
70% of the money goes to evaluating.
Can you imagine?
That's a very large number.
And the reason was that they had a review
of what they had done for the last 10 years,
and nobody could point to anything
where they could really show
that the money hadn't been wasted.
Well, of course,
you probably have to wait 10 years
and see which of those children get into college
or better college or blah, blah, blah.
It's very hard to evaluate things.
But I don't think anybody that I know
thinks it's worth a minute to define intelligence
since there's 40 different things,
and everybody knows what they are.
And if you try to get it into one thing,
then you lose big,
because you end up saying it's smarter.
Right, but I mean, there's 10 different things
where you know a subset of them
but you don't know what the other ones are.
I'm not sure what you're saying.
It's not clear to me that that word is very useful.
It means roughly one thing is more intelligent
or better at a certain class of problems than another,
if it solves more of them or some of them more quickly
or some of them at less cost than you're used to.
And if you sit there for 10 minut
are bad at solving.
Problem solving is informing artificial intelligence.
Maybe you're using problem in a funny way.
What most of us are doing is trying
to make machines that fiddle with their own program
and get better at things.
So they're not solving problems.
They're getting better at solving problems.
That's the problem they're solving.
I mean, if you asked Picasso to solve a differential equation,
he would come out with IQ 20, I suppose,
and yet he would do something incredibly.
Now, if Picasso did that, you would all be swooning.
But I don't know how to do it.
And then there's Michelangelo just drawing a perfect circle.
Yeah?
What do you think about Ray Kurzweil?
Do you think about the similarity?
Say it again.
Ray Kurzweil.
Kurzweil.
What?
Ray Kurzweil.
Yeah.
And about disasters that may happen in the future,
are you worried that, for example, we
can't defend against biological weapons or something like that?
Yeah.
First of all, the Ray Kurzweil.
I don't know.
I'm not sure what.
Ask it again.
Sorry.
What do you think about hysteria about technology
being produced financially?
And in, I don't know, 40 years, are you
going to have machines that are 10,000 times smarter than us?
Well, first, I have a serious conflict of interest,
because Ray was a student here.
And we did some things together.
And he was awesome at various things.
And one day, after he was a student,
and he sends me a synthesizer every couple of years.
So the house is littered with them.
And they're the best thing.
Anyway, one day, he was being interviewed,
because he had the Kurzweil reading machine.
He was reading printed characters
and pronouncing them pretty well.
And he was on the interview.
And the interviewer said, well, Mr. Kurzweil,
could you demonstrate your reading machine?
And Ray turns the thing on, puts this press release on it,
and it says, this is a demonstration of the Kurzweil
reading machine, and blah, blah, blah.
And it went on and did that several times.
And then for the rest of the half hour,
the interviewer said, Mr. Kurzweil.
And Ray tried to correct him a couple of times.
But it was useless, because the machine had said it.
That's a funny story.
So he predicts that things will increase rapidly
until there will be inventions every minute.
And the way he proves that is by showing all sorts of graphs
of things that have increased exponentially.
I plotted how far a tire will roll,
because Google is so good.
And I had found in the attic of my house,
which was built in 1895, in the attic
there was a motor vehicle bulletin from 1915, I think,
maybe 17.
And it said, one thing you must know,
besides not alarming the horses, is
you have to know how to change a tire or a tube,
because if you take a long trip, like all the way to Lexington
and back, it said that.
You'll probably have to patch a tube.
I'm sorry.
I can't remember what got me started on that.
Oh, so I plotted the length tires
would roll before they go bad from the 15 miles in 1915
up to about 80,000 miles now.
How long do your tires last?
Is that the right number?
I think it's more like 40 or something.
40 or 50.
I calculated it once you wear off less than an atom
each time around.
It's remarkable.
Anyway, so he has this big, wonderful book showing
all these exponential curves.
And if you try, you can find lots
of curves which go up and then flatten out.
But there aren't so many of those in his book.
But basically, of course, he's right
that there are things like Moore's law where computers
get faster and cheaper and all that sort of thing.
But a lot of those laws come to an end
when you get down to an atom-sized bit.
And if those happen too soon, then the singularity
won't come.
But I think the proper way to look at it
is to say, yes, things are happening faster and faster.
And many of them are very important.
And if you live lower than 20 feet above sea level,
you should plan to move soon.
Well, what should we think about?
Oh, I know.
Well, next Thursday is Thanksgiving.
How many of you would still be here next Wednesday?
That's 40%.
What?
I'd be glad to come in and talk to people
about projects and things.
But a lot of you probably have to go somewhere
for Thanksgiving.
So if you don't come, I won't be surprised.