The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
So really, what my main concern has been for quite a few years
is to make some theory of what makes people
able to solve so many kinds of problems.
I guess if you ran through the spectrum of all the animals,
you'd find lots of problems that some animals can solve
and people can't, like how many of you
could build a beaver dam or a termite nest.
So there are all sorts of things that evolution
manages to produce.
But maybe the most impressive one
is what the human infant can do just
by hanging around for 10 or 20 or 30 years
and watching what other humans can do.
So we can solve all sorts of problems.
And my quarrel with most of the artificial intelligence
community has been that the great success of science
in the last 500 years really has been in physics.
And it's been rewarded by finding little sets of rules,
like Newton's three laws and Maxwell's four laws
and Einstein's one law or two, that
explained a huge range of everyday phenomena.
Of course, in the 1920s and 30s, that apple
cart got upset because, actually, Einstein
himself, who had discovered the first quantum phenomenon,
namely the quantization of photons,
had produced various scientific laboratory observations
that were inexplicable in terms of either Maxwell or Newton
or Einstein's earlier formulations.
So my picture of the history is that in the 19th century
and a little bit earlier, going back
to Locke and Spinoza and Hume and a few of those philosophers,
even Immanuel Kant, they had some pretty good
psychological ideas.
And as I mentioned the other day,
I suspect that Aristotle was more
like a modern cognitive psychologist
and had even better ideas.
But we've probably lost a lot of them
because there are no tape recorders.
Who knows what Aristotle and Plato
said that their students didn't write down
because it sounded silly.
So the idea that we developed around here, mostly
Seymour Papert and a lot of students,
Pat Winston was one of the great stars of that period,
was the idea that to get anything
like human intellectual abilities,
you're going to have to have all sorts of high level
representations.
So one has to say the old conditioned reflex of stimulus
producing a response isn't good enough.
The stimulus has to be represented
by some kind of semantic structure
somewhere in the brain or mind.
And so far as I know, it's only in the theories of not even
modern artificial intelligence, but the AI of the 60s and 70s
and 80s that people thought about what
could be the internal representation of the kinds
of things that we think about.
And even more important, if one of those representations,
you see something or you remember some incident
and your brain represents it in some way,
and if that way doesn't work, you take a breath
and you sort of stumble around and find another way
to represent it.
Maybe when the original event first happened,
you represented it in three or four ways.
And so we're beginning to see.
Did anybody hear Ferrucci's talk?
The Watson guy was up here a couple of days ago.
I missed it.
But they haven't made a technical publication,
as far as I know, of how this Watson program works.
But it sounds like it's something
of an interesting society of mind-like structure.
And it would be nice if they would.
Has anybody read any long paper on it?
There have been a lot of press reports.
Have you seen anything, Pat?
So anyway, they seem to have done some sorts of common sense
reasoning.
As I said the other day, I doubt that Watson
could understand why you can pull something with a string,
but you can't push.
And actually, I don't know if any existing program
can understand that yet.
I saw some amazing demonstrations yesterday
by, or Monday, by Steve Wolfram of his Wolfram
Alpha, which doesn't do much common sense reasoning.
But what it does do is, if you put it in a sentence,
it finds five or 10 different representations, anything
you can find that's sort of mathematical.
And so when you ask it a question,
it gives you 10 answers.
And it's much better than previous systems,
because it doesn't.
Well, Google gives you a quarter million answers,
but that's too many.
Anyway, I'm just going to talk a little bit more.
And just everybody should be trying
to think of a question that the rest of the class might answer.
So there are lots of different kinds of problems
that people can solve, going back to the first one,
like which moving object out there is my mother,
and which might be a potential threat.
So there are a lot of kinds of problems that we solve.
And I've never seen any discussion in psychology books
of what are the principal activities of common sense
thinking.
Somehow, they don't have, or people don't.
Before computers, there really wasn't any way
to think about high-level thinking,
because there weren't any technically usable ways
to describe complicated processes.
The idea of a conditional expression
was barely on the threshold of psychology.
So what kinds of problems do we have?
And if you take some particular problem,
like I find these days I can't get the top off bottles.
So how do I solve that?
And there are lots of answers.
One is you look for somebody who looks really strong,
or you reach into your pocket and you probably
have one of these, and so on.
There must be some way to put it on the floor
and step on it and kick it with the other foot.
So there are lots of problems that we're facing every day.
And if you look in traditional cognitive psychology,
well, what's the worst theory?
The worst and the best theory got popular in the 1980s.
It was called rule-based systems.
And you just have a big library which says,
if you have a soda bottle and you can't get the cap off,
then do this or that or the other.
And so some people decided, well,
that's really all you need.
Rod Brooks in the 1980s sort of said,
we don't need those fancy theories
that people like Minsky and Papert and Winston
are working on.
Why not just say, for each situation in the outer world,
have a rule that says how to deal with that situation?
Let's make a hierarchy of them.
And he described a system that sort of looked
like the priority interrupt system in a computer.
And he won all sorts of prizes for this really bad idea that
spread around the world.
But it solved a lot of problems.
There are things about priority interrupt that aren't obvious.
Like suppose you have, in the first computers,
there was some problem because what should you
do if there are several signals coming into the computer
and you want to respond to them and some of the signals
are very fast and very short?
Then you might think, well, I should
give the highest priority to the signal that's
going to be there the shortest time, something like that.
The funny part is that when you made such a system,
the result was that if you had a computer that
was responding to some signal that's coming in at a,
I'm talking about the days when computers were only
working at a few kilohertz, a few thousand operations
a second, god, that's slow, a million times shorter
than what you have in your pocket.
And if you give priority to the signals that
have to be reacted to very fast, then what
happens if you type to those computers,
it would never see them because it's always,
I saw this happening once.
And finally, somebody realized that you
should give the highest priority to the inputs that
come in most, least frequently because there's always,
otherwise, if there's something coming in very frequently,
you'll just always be responding to it.
Any of you run into this?
Took me a while to figure out why.
Anyway, there are lots of kinds of problems.
And the other day, I was complaining
that we didn't have enough ways to just,
we had hundreds of words for emotions.
And here's a couple of dozen.
They're in chapters 7 and 8, actually, most of these.
So here's a bunch of words for describing ways to think.
But they're not very technical.
So you can talk about remorse and sorrow and blah, blah,
blah, hundreds and hundreds of words for feelings.
And it's a lot of effort to find a dozen words
for intellectual, for what should I call them,
problem-solving processes.
So it's curious to me that the great field called
cognitive psychology has not focused in that direction.
Anyway, here's about 20 or 30 of them.
And you'll find them scattered through chapters 7 and 8.
Here's my favorite one.
And I don't know of any proper name for it.
But if you're trying to solve a problem and you're stuck,
and the example that comes to my mind
is if I'm trying to remember someone's name,
I can tell when it's hopeless.
And the reason is that for somehow or other,
I know that there's a huge tree of choices.
That's one way to represent what's going on.
And I might know that I'm sure that that name has a Z in it.
So you search around and try everything you can.
But of course, it doesn't have a Z.
It's so you're so the way to solve that problem
is to give up.
And then a couple of minutes later, the name occurs to you.
And you have no idea how it happened and so forth.
So anyway, the long story is that Papert and I
and lots of really great students in the 60s and 70s
spent a lot of time making little models of problem
solvers that didn't work.
And we discovered that you needed something else.
And we put that in.
Other people would come and say, that's hopeless.
You're putting in more things than you need.
And my conclusion is that, wow, it's the opposite of physics.
In physics, you're always trying to find you don't want to,
what is it called, Occam's razor?
Never have more structure than you need because what?
Well, it'll waste your time.
But my feeling was, I never have less than you'll need.
But you don't know how many you'll need.
So what I did, I had four of these.
And then I forced myself to put in two more.
And people ask, what's the difference
between self-models and self-conscious processes?
And I don't care.
Or what's the difference between self-conscious and reflective?
I don't care.
And the reason is that, wow, it's
nice to have a box that isn't full yet.
So if you find something that your previous theory,
going back to Brooks, he was so successful getting
simple robots to work that he concluded that the things
didn't need any internal representations at all.
And for some mysterious reason, the Artificial Intelligence
Society gave him their annual big prize
for this very wrong idea.
And it caused AI research to sort of half collapse
in places like Japan and said, oh, rule-based systems
is all we need.
Anybody want to defend him?
The odd thing is, if you talk to Brooks,
he's one of the best philosophers you'll ever meet.
And he says, oh, yes, of course that's wrong.
But it helps people do research and get things done.
As I think I mentioned the other day, when the Three Mile Island
thing happened, there was no way to get into the reactor.
That was 1980.
And 30 years later, when the, how do you pronounce it,
Fukushima accident happened.
There was no robot that could go in and open a door.
I don't know who to blame for that, maybe us.
But my picture of the history is that the places that
did research on robotics, there were quite a few places.
And for example, Carnegie Mellon was
very impressive in getting the Sony dogs to play soccer.
And they're still at it.
And I think I mentioned that Sony still has a stock of,
what's it called?
Fibos.
Say it again.
Fibo?
Fibo, A-I-B-O.
Right, Fibos.
Right.
But the trouble is they're always broken.
And there was a robot here called Cog that Brooks made.
And it sometimes worked.
But usually, it wasn't working.
And so only one student at a time
could experiment with the robot.
What was that wonderful project of trying
to make a walking machine?
For four years, there was a project to make a robot walk.
And there was only one of it.
So first, only one student at a time can do research on it.
And most of the time, something's broken
and you're fixing it.
And so you end up that you sort of get five or 10 hours a week
on your laboratory physical robot.
At the same time, Ed Fredkin had a student
who tried to make a walking robot.
And it was a stick figure on the screen.
And I forgot the student's name.
But anyway, he simulated gravity and a few other things.
And in a couple of weeks, he had a pretty good robot
that could walk and go around turns and bank.
And if you simulated an oily floor,
it could slip and fall, which we considered the high point
of the demo, actually.
So there we find.
So anyway, I've sort of asked you to read my two books
for this course.
But those are not the only good texts
about artificial intelligence.
And if you want to dig deeper, it
might be a good idea to go to the web
and type in Aaron Sloman, S-L-O-M-A-N.
And you'll get to his website, which is something like that.
And Sloman is a sort of philosopher who can program.
There are a handful of them in the world.
And he has lots of interesting ideas
that nobody's gotten to carry out.
And so I recommend.
Who else is?
Pat, do you ever recommend anyone else?
No.
What?
I'm trying to think.
I mean, if you're looking for philosophers,
Dan Dennett has a lot of ideas.
But Sloman is the only person I'd
say is a sort of real professional philosopher who
tries to program at least some of his ideas.
And he has successful students who
have made larger systems work.
So if you get tired of me, and you are too,
then go look at this guy and see who he recommends.
So OK, who has a good question to ask?
We were talking about how we have a lot of words
for emotions.
Why do we only have one word for cause?
It's a mystery, but I spent most of the couple of days
making this list bigger.
But these aren't, you know, these
are things that you do when you're thinking.
You make analogies.
If you have multiple goals, you try
to pick the most important one.
Or in some cases, if you have several goals,
maybe you should try to achieve the easiest one.
And there's a chance that it'll lead you
into what to do about the harder ones.
But a lot of people think that, mostly in England,
that logic is a good way to do reasoning.
And that's completely wrong.
Because in logic, first of all, you
can't do analogies at all, except at a very high level.
It takes four or five nested quantifiers
to say A is to B, and C is to which of the following five.
So I've never seen anyone do analogical thinking
using formal logic, first order or higher order
predicate calculus.
What's logic good for?
It's great after you've solved a problem,
because then you can formalize what you did
and see if some of the things you did weren't necessary.
In other words, after you've got the solution to a problem,
which you got by going through a big search,
you finally found a path from A to Z.
And now you can see if the assumptions
that you had to make to bridge all these various little gaps
were all essential or not.
So yes?
What example would you say that logic can do analogies?
Water is for bottle as containment.
Why would you just do a high level?
I don't see it.
Well, because you have to make a list of hypotheses.
And then let me see if I can find Evans.
The trouble is, darn, Evans' name is in a picture.
And Word can't look inside its pictures.
Can PowerPoint find words in its illustrations?
Why don't I use PowerPoint?
Because I've discovered that PowerPoint
can't read pictures made by other programs in the Microsoft
Word suite.
The drawing program in Word is pretty good.
And then there's an operation in Word
which will make a PowerPoint out of what you drew.
And it's 25 years since Microsoft
hasn't fixed the fatal errors that it
makes when you do that.
In other words, I don't think that the PowerPoint and Word
people communicate.
And they both make a lot of money.
So that might be the reason.
Where was I?
Why logic can't do analogies?
Well, you can do anything in logic if you try hard enough.
But A is to B, and C is to X is a four-part relation.
And you'd need a whole pile of quantifiers.
And how would you know what to do next?
Yes?
I want to talk a bit about the situation in which we
are able to perform some sort of action really fluently
and really well, but we cannot describe what we're doing.
And the example I give is, say, I'm
like an expert African drummer from Africa.
And I can make these really complicated rhythms.
But if you ask me, what did you just do?
I have no idea how to describe it.
And in that case, do you think the person is capable of,
or I guess do you think the person,
we can say that the person understands this even though
they cannot explain it?
Well, if you take an extreme form of that,
you can't explain why you used any particular word
for anything.
There's no reason to.
It's remarkable how well people can do in everyday life
to tell people how they got an idea.
But when you look at it, it doesn't
say how you would program a machine to do it.
So there's something very peculiar about the idea that
goes back to this idea that people have free will
and so forth.
Suppose I say, look at this and say,
this has a constriction at this point.
Why did I say constriction?
How do you decide what word to use for something?
You have no idea.
So it's a very general question.
It's not clear that the frontal lobes, which
might have something to do with making plans
and analyzing certain kinds of situations,
have any access to what happens in the Broca
or what's the speech production area.
It is Broca.
Broca.
And I'm trying to find the name of the other one.
It's connected by a cable that's about a quarter inch thick.
There's also Wernicke.
Wernicke, yeah.
We have no idea how those work.
As far as I've never seen any publication in neuroscience
that says, here's a theory of what
happens in Wernicke's area.
Have any of you ever seen one?
What do those people think about?
But they'll tell you about, I was reading something
which said, it's going to be very hard to understand
these areas because each neuron is connected
to 100,000 little fibers.
Well, some of them are.
And I bet they don't do much, except sort of set the bias
for some large collection of other neurons.
But if you ask somebody, how did you think of such a word,
they will tell you some story or anecdote.
But they won't be able to describe
some sort of procedure, which is, say,
in terms of a language like Lisp.
And say, I can't this and that.
And I took the clutter of this and the car of that.
And I put them in this register.
And then I swapped that with, you
don't see theories of how the mind works in psychology today.
The only parts are they know a little bit
about some aspects of vision, because you
can track the paths of images from the retina
to the what's called to the primary visual cortex.
And people have been able to figure out
what some of those cortical columns do.
And if you go back to an animal like the frog,
then researchers like Bitsy and others
have figured out how the equivalent of the cerebellum
in the frog, they've got almost the whole circuit of how
when the frog sees a fly, it manages to turn its head
that way and stick its tongue out and catch it.
But in the case of a human, I've never
seen any theory of how any person thinks of anything.
So there's artificial intelligence,
which has high-level theories of semantic representations.
And there's neuroscience, which has good theories of some parts
of locomotion and some parts of sensory systems.
And to this day, there's nothing much in between.
So David here has decided to go from one to the other.
And former student of mine, Bob Hearn,
has done a little bit on both.
And I bet there are 20 or 30 people around the country who
are trying to bridge the gap between symbolic artificial
intelligence and mappings of the nervous system.
But it's very rare.
And I don't know who you could ask
to get support to work on a problem like that for five
years.
Yeah?
So presumably, to build a human-like artificial
intelligence, we need to perfectly model
our own intelligence, which means that we're the system.
We ourselves are the system that we're trying to understand.
Well, it doesn't have to be exact.
I mean, people are different.
And a typical person looks like they
have 400 different brain centers doing
slightly different things or very different things.
And we have these examples.
In many cases, if you lose a lot of your brain,
you're very badly damaged.
And in other cases, you recover and become just about as smart
as you were, probably a few cases
where you got rid of something that was holding you back.
But it's hard to prove that.
So we don't need a theory of how people work yet.
And the nice thing about AI is that we could eventually
get models which are pretty good at solving what people call
everyday common sense problems.
And probably, in many respects, they're not
the way the human mind works.
It doesn't matter.
But once you've got, if I had a program which
was pretty good at understanding why you can pull with a string
but not push, then there's a fair chance
you could say, well, that seems to resemble what people do.
I'll do this a few psychological experiments
and see what's wrong with that theory and how to change it.
So at some point, there'll be people making AI systems,
comparing them to particular people,
and trying to make them fit.
The trouble is, nowadays, it takes a few months
if you get a really good new idea to program it.
I think there's something wrong with programming languages.
And what we need is a programming language
where the instructions describe goals and then subgoals.
And then finally, you might say, well,
let's represent this concept by a number or a semantic network
of some sort.
But yes?
On that idea of having a programming language
where you can find goals.
Is there a goal-oriented language?
So there's kind of one.
If you think about it, if you swim hard enough,
something like SQL, where you tell the computer,
I want to find the top 10 people in my database
with this high value, and then you
don't worry about how the system goes about doing that.
In a sense, that's redefining the goal when it goes in.
But you got to swim a little bit.
Uh-huh.
What's it called?
SQL.
So any of the books at a database and queries it
and asks it to pass it.
Oh, right.
Yes, I guess database query languages are on the track.
But Wolfram Alpha seems to be better than I thought.
Well, he was running it.
And Steve Wolfram was giving this demo
at a meeting we were at on Monday.
And he'd say, well, maybe I'll just say this.
And it always worked.
So maybe either the language is better than I thought,
or Wolfram is better than I thought.
That's something.
Remarkable guy.
Yes.
So I like this example of you only remember a name after your
or you can remember a name after you've given up consciously
trying to think about it.
Do you think this is a matter of us being able to set up
background processes?
And then either there's some delay,
like we give up, there's some delay in the process,
or we don't have the ability to correctly terminate processes.
Do you think this only works for memory,
or could it work for other things?
Could I start an adversity operation
and then give up and then go to the meeting later?
Well, there's a lot of nice questions
about things like that.
How many processes can you run at once in your brain?
And I was having a sort of argument
the other day about music.
And I was wondering if I see a big difference between Bach
and the composers who do counterpoint.
Counterpoint, you usually have several versions
of a very similar idea.
Maybe there's one theme, and you have it playing,
and then another voice comes in, and it
has that theme upside down or a variation of it,
or in some cases, exactly the same.
And then it's called a canon.
So the tour de force in classical music
is when you have two or three or four versions
of the same thought going on at once in different times.
And my feeling was that in popular music,
or if you take a typical band, then there
might be four people, and they're doing different things
at the same time, usually not the same musical tunes.
But there's a rhythm, and there's a timpani,
and there's various instruments doing different things.
But you don't have several doing the same thing.
I might be wrong.
And somebody said, well, some popular music
has a lot of counterpoint.
I'm just not familiar with it.
But I think that if you're trying to solve a hard problem,
it's fairly easy to look at the problem
in several different ways.
But what's hard is to look at it in several almost the same ways
that are slightly different.
Because probably, if you believe that the brain is
made of agents or resources or whatever,
you probably don't have duplicate copies of ones
that do important things, because that would take up
too much real estate.
But anyway, I might be completely wrong about jazz,
somebody.
Maybe they have just as complicated overlapping things
as Bach and the contrapuntal composers did.
Yeah?
What is the ultimate goal of artificial intelligence?
Is it some sort of application, or is it more philosophical?
Oh, everyone has different goals or ones.
In your opinion?
I think we're going to need it, because the disaster
that we're working our way toward
is that people are going to live longer,
and they'll become slightly less able.
And so you'll have billions of 200-year-old people
who can barely get around.
And there won't be enough people to import
from underdeveloped countries, or they
won't be able to afford them.
So we're going to have to have machines that take care of us.
Of course, that's just a transient, because at some point,
then you'll download your brain into a machine
and fix everything that's wrong.
So we'll need robots for a few hundred years,
or a few decades, and then we'll be them,
and we won't need them anymore.
But it's an important problem.
What's going to happen in the next 100 years?
You're going to have 20 billion 200-year-olds and nobody
to take care of them unless we get AI.
And nobody seems particularly sad about that.
Oh, another anecdote.
I was once giving a lecture and talking about people
living a long time, and nobody in the audience
seemed interested.
And I'd say, well, suppose you could live 400 years.
And most of the people, then I asked, what was the trouble?
And they said, wouldn't it be boring?
So then I tried it again in a couple of other lectures.
And if you ask a bunch of scientists,
how would you like to live 400 years, everyone says, yay.
And you ask them why, and they say, well,
I'm working on a problem that I might not have time to solve.
But if I had 400 years, I bet I could get somewhere on it.
And the other people don't have any goal.
That's my cold-blooded view of the typical non-scientist.
There's nothing for them to do in the long run.
Who can think of what should people do?
What's your goal?
How many of you want to live 400 years?
Wow.
Must be scientists here.
Try it on some crowd and let me know what happens.
Are people really afraid?
Yeah.
I think the differentiating factor is whether or not
your 400 years is just going to be the repetition of 100 years
experience, or if it will start to take off,
then you'll start to learn that it will progress.
Right.
I've seen 30 issues of the Big Bang,
and I don't look forward to the next one anymore,
because they're getting to be all the same,
although it's the only thing on TV that has scientists.
Seriously, I hardly read anything
except journals and science fiction, because.
Yeah.
What's the motivation to have robots take care of us
as opposed to enhancing our own cognitive abilities
or our own prosthetic body or something more cyborg?
Or the joy of living, and you can't do anything
if somebody takes care of you.
I can't think of any advantages, except that medicine
isn't getting the age of unhandicapped people
went up one year every four since the late 1940s.
So lifespan is, so that's 60 years.
So people are living 15 years longer on the average
than they did when I was born, or even more than that.
But it's leveled off lately.
Now, I suspect that you only have to fix a dozen genes,
or who knows?
Nobody really has a good estimate.
But you can probably double the lifespan
if you could fix.
Nobody knows.
But maybe there's just a dozen processes
that would fix a lot of things.
And then you could live longer without deteriorating.
And lots of people might get bored.
But they'll self-select.
I don't know.
What's your answer?
I feel that creating, I feel that AI is more, I mean,
the goal is not to help take care of people,
but to complement what we already have to entertain us.
You could also look at them as our descendants.
And we will have them replace us.
And just as a lot of people consider their children
to be the next generation of them,
and I know a lot of people who don't, so it's not a universal.
But what's the point of anything?
I don't want to get in.
We might be the only intelligent life in the universe.
And in that case, it's very important
that we solve all our problems and make sure
that something intelligent persists.
I think Carl Sagan had some argument of that sort.
If you were sure that there were lots of others,
then it wouldn't seem so important.
Who's the new Carl Sagan?
Is there a public scientist?
Who?
He's the guy who is like Nova all the time.
I've heard about this.
And there's no other scientist.
Oh, Tyson?
Bryan Green.
He's very good.
Tyson is the astrophysicist.
Bryan Green is a great actor.
He's quite impressive.
Yeah?
When would you say a machine has a sense of self?
We think there's something that's like a self inside us
because partly because there's some processes we don't just
show that from us.
We just mysteriously assign it to the self.
But when would you say a machine has a sense of self?
Well, I think that's a funny question.
Because if we're programming it, we
can make sure that the machine has a very good abstract
but correct model of how it works, which people don't.
So people have a sense of self.
But it's only a sense of self.
And it's just plain wrong in almost every respect.
So it's a really funny question because when
you make a machine that really has a good, useful
representation of what it is and how it works,
it might be quite different, have different attitudes
than a person does.
Like it might not consider itself very valuable and say,
oh, I could make something that's even better than me
and jump into that.
It might not have any self-protective reaction
because if you could improve yourself,
then you don't want not to.
Whereas we're in a state where there's
nothing much we can do except try to keep living.
And we don't have any alternative.
Stupid thing to say.
I can't imagine getting tired of living, but lots of people do.
Yeah.
So what do you think about creative thinking
and the way of thinking and where does this thinking
come from or anything that comes out of it?
I had a little section about that somewhere
that I wrote, which was the difference between artists
and scientists or engineers.
And engineers have a very nice situation
because they know what they want because somebody's ordered
them to make a.
In the last month, three times I've
walked away from my computer.
And how many of you have a Mac with the magnetic thing?
And three times I pulled it by tripping on this
and it fell to the floor and didn't break.
And I've had Macs for 20 odd years or since 1980.
When did they start?
Ooh, 30 years.
And they have the regular Jack power supply in the old days.
And I don't remember.
And usually when you pull the cord, it comes out.
Here's this cord that Steve Jobs and everybody designed
very carefully so that when you pull it,
nothing bad would happen.
But it does.
How do you account for that?
It used to be better when the old plugs were
perpendicular to the old plug.
And now it's kind of.
Well, it's quite a wide angle.
So it works at a certain angle.
And the cable now, instead of naturally
lying in that area, actually naturally
lies in the area where it doesn't work.
Well, what it needs is a little ramp
so that it would slide out.
I mean, it would only take a minute to file it down
But they didn't.
I forget why I mentioned that.
But.
You're on the front of engineers and creativity.
Right.
So what's the difference between an artist and engineer?
Well, when you do a painting, it seems to me
if you're already good at painting,
the 9 tenths of the problem is, what should I paint?
So you can think of an artist as 10% skill and 90%
trying to figure out what the problem is to solve.
Whereas for the engineer, somebody's
told him what to do, make a better cable connector.
And so he's going to spend 90% of his time
actually solving the problem, and only 10% of the time
trying to decide what problem to solve.
So I don't see any difference between artists and engineers,
except that the artist has more problems to solve
than it could possibly solve.
And usually ends up by picking a really dumb one, like,
let's have a saint and three angels.
Where will I put the third angel?
That's the engineering part.
Just improvising.
So to me, the media lab makes sense.
The artists or semi-artists and the scientists
are doing almost the same thing.
And if you look at the more arty people,
they're a little more concerned with human social relations
and this and that.
And others are more concerned with very technical,
specific aspects of signal processing
or semantic representations and so on.
So I don't see much difference between the arts
and the sciences.
And then, of course, the great moments
are when you run into people like Leonardo and Michelangelo,
who get some idea that requires a great new technical
innovation that nobody has ever done.
And it's hard to separate them.
I think there's some place where Leonardo realizes
that the lens in the eye would mean that the image is upside
down on the retina, and he couldn't stand that.
So there's a diagram he has where
the cornea is curved enough to invert the image,
and then the lens inverts it back again,
which is contrary to fact.
But he has a sketch showing that he
was worried about if the image were upside down on the retina,
wouldn't things look upside down?
Yeah?
I have a really exciting question.
Did you ever learn about hierarchical temporal memory
and temporal memory?
Temporal?
Temporal memory.
There is a system that I tried to create
based on how our brain requires them.
And they have a company called Lurema,
and they're going to release a song at the end of this year
on it.
And there's some research.
They have paper on it.
Well, I'm not sure what.
This is Jeff Hawkins' project?
I don't know his name.
Yeah, it's Jeff Hawkins.
I haven't heard about 10 years ago he said, Hawkins?
Yeah, well, he was talking about 10 years ago how great it was,
and I haven't heard a word of any progress.
Is there some?
Anybody heard of it?
There's a couple of books about it,
but I've never seen any claim that it works.
They wrote a ferocious review of The Society of Mind,
which came out in 1986.
And the Hawkins group existed then
and had this talk about a hierarchical memory system.
But as far as I can tell, it's all bluff.
Nothing happened.
I've never seen a report that they
have a machine which solved the problem.
Let me know if you find one, because oh, well,
Hawkins got really mad at me for pointing this out.
But I was really mad at him for having four of his assistants
write a bad book review of my book, so I hope we were even.
No.
If anybody can find out whether, I forget what it's called.
Do you remember its name?
You mentioned it was the name of this company.
Well, let's find out if it can do anything yet.
Hawkins is wealthy enough to support it for a long time,
so it should be good by now.
Yes?
Do you think we're going to solve the problem?
People first start out with some sort of classification
in their head of the kind of problem it is,
or is that not necessary?
Yes.
Well, there's this huge book called Human Problem Solving,
which was, I don't know how many of you
know the names of Newell and Simon.
Originally, it was Newell, Shaw, and Simon.
And believe it or not, in the late 1950s,
they did some of the first really productive AI research.
And then I think in 1970, so that's
after 12 years of discovering interesting things,
their main discovery was the gadget
that they called GPS, which is not
global positioning satellite, but general problem solver.
And you can look it up in the index of my book,
and there's a sort of one or two page description.
But if you ever get some spare time,
search the web for their early paper
by Newell and Simon on how GPS worked,
because it's really fascinating.
What it did is it looked at a problem
and found some features of it, and then looked up
in a table saying that if there's
this difference between what you have and what you want,
use such and such a method.
So it was sort of what I called it.
I renamed it a difference engine as a sort of joke,
because the first computer in history
was the one called the difference engine,
but it was for predicting tides and things.
Anyway, they did some beautiful work,
and there's this big book, which I think is about 1970,
called Human Problem Solving.
And what they did is got some people to solve problems,
and they trained the people to talk
while they're solving the problem.
So some of them were little cryptograms,
like if each letter stands for a digit, I've forgotten it.
Pat, do you remember the name?
One of those problems?
John plus Jane equals Robert or something.
I'm sure that has no solution, but those
are called crypt arithmetic.
And so they had dozens or hundreds
of people who would be trained to talk aloud
while they're solving little puzzles like that.
And then what they did was look at exactly what
the people said and how long they took,
and in some cases, where they moved their eyes.
They had an eye tracking machine,
and then they wrote programs that
showed how this guy solved a couple
of these crypt arithmetic problems.
Then they ran the program on a new one,
and in some rare cases, it actually
solved the other problem.
So this is a book which looks at human behavior
and makes a theory of what it's doing,
and the output is a rule-based system.
So it's not a very exciting theory,
but there had never been anything like it.
It was like Pavlov discovering conditioned reflexes
for rats or dogs, and Newell and Simon
are discovering some rather higher level.
It's almost a Rodney Brooks-like system
for how humans solve some problems that most people
find pretty hard.
Anyway, what there hasn't been is much.
I don't know of any follow-up.
They spent years perfecting those experiments
and writing about the results.
Anybody know anything like that?
What psychologists are trying to make real novels
of real people solving toy problems?
And I think there might not.
It has a green light.
It has a green light, but the switch was on.
Boo.
Oh, it doesn't.
Yes.
Did that particular study try and see
when a person gave up on a particular problem-solving
method, how they switched to another,
which one they switched to based on what they were drawing?
It has inexplicable points at which the person suddenly
gives up on that representation.
And he says, oh, well, I guess R must be 3.
Did I erase?
Well, yes, it's got episodes.
And they can't account for the little jerks in the script
where the model changes.
Sorry.
And they announce those to be mysteries and say,
here's a place where the person has decided
the strategy isn't working and starts over
or is changing something.
The amazing part is that their model sometimes
fits what the person says for 50 or even 100 steps.
The guy is saying, oh, I think 2 must be, z must be 2,
and p must be 7.
And that means p plus z is 9.
And I wonder what's 9.
And so their model fits for very long strings,
maybe two minutes of the person mumbling to themselves.
And then it breaks, and then there's another sequence.
So Newell actually spent more than a year
after doing it verbally at tracking the person's eye
motions and trying to correlate the person's eye motions
with what the person was talking about.
And guess what?
None.
It was almost as though you look at something,
and then to think about it, you look away.
Newell was quite distressed because he spent about a year
crawling over this data trying to figure out
what kinds of mental events caused the eyes to change
what they were looking at.
But when the problem got hard, you
would look at a blank part of the thing
more often than the place where the problem turned up.
So conclusion, that didn't work.
When I was a very young student in college,
I had a friend named Marcus Singer
who was trying to figure out how the nerve in the forelimb
of a frog worked.
And so he was operating on tadpoles.
And he spent about six weeks moving this sciatic nerve
from the leg up to the arm of this tadpole.
And then they all got some fungus and died.
So I said, what are you going to do?
And he said, well, I guess I'll have to do it again.
And I switched from biology to mathematics.
But in fact, he discovered the growth hormone
that he thought came from the nerve
and made that if you cut off the limb bud of a tadpole,
it'll grow another one and grow a whole.
It was a newt, I'm sorry.
It's salamander.
It'll grow a new hand.
If you wait till it's got a substantial hand,
it won't grow a new one.
But he discovered the hormone that makes it do that.
Yeah?
One of the questions from the homework that kind of relates
to the problem-solving thing, a common theme
is having multiple ways to react to the same problem.
But how do we choose which options
to add as possible reactions to the same problem?
Oh, so we have a whole lot of if-thens,
and we have to choose which if.
I don't think I have a good theory of that.
Yes, if you have a huge rule-based system,
what does Randy Davis do?
What if you have a rule-based system
and a whole lot of rules fit, ifs fit the condition?
Do you just take the one that's most often worked?
Or if nothing seems to be working,
you certainly don't want to keep trying the same one.
I think I mentioned Doug Lenat's rule.
Some people will assign probabilities
to things, to behaviors, and then
pick the way to react proportional to the probability
that that thing has worked in the past.
And Doug Lenat thought of doing that,
but instead he just put the things in a list.
And whenever a hypothesis worked better than another one,
he would raise it, push it toward the front of the list.
And then whenever there was a choice,
it would pick all the rules that fit.
It would pick the one at the top of the list.
And if that didn't work, it would get demoted.
So that's when I became an anti-probability person.
That is, if just sorting the things on a list
worked pretty well, our probability
is going to do much better.
No, because if you do probability matching,
you're worse off than what?
Ray Solomonoff discovered that if you
have a set of probabilities that something will work
and you have no memory, so that each time you come and try
the, I think I mentioned that the other day,
it's worth emphasizing, because nobody in the world
seems to know it.
Suppose you have a list of things, P equals this,
or that, or that.
And in other words, suppose there's 100 boxes here,
and one of them has a gold brick in it, and the others don't.
And so for each box, suppose the probability is 0.9,
that this one has the gold brick, and this one has 0.01,
and this has 0.01.
Let's see how many of them.
So there's 10 of these.
That makes.
Now, what should you do?
Suppose you're allowed to keep choosing a box,
and you want to get your gold brick as soon as possible.
What's the smart thing to do?
But you have no memory.
Maybe the gold brick is decreasing in value.
I don't care.
So should you keep trying 0.9 if you have no memory?
Well, of course not, because if you don't get it the first time,
you'll never get it.
Whereas if you tried them at random each time,
then you'd have 0.9 chance of getting it.
So in two trials, you'd have, what am I saying?
In 100 trials, you're pretty sure to get it.
But in E 100 trials, almost certain.
So if you don't have any memory, then probability matching
is not a good idea.
Certainly picking the highest probability
is not a good idea, because if you don't get it the first
trial, you'll never get it.
If you keep using the probabilities at,
what am I saying?
Anyway, what do you think is the best thing to do?
It's to take the square roots of those probabilities
and then divide them by the sum of the square roots
so it adds up to 1.
And so a lot of psychologists design experiments
until they get the rat to match the probability.
And then they publish it, sort of like the,
but if the animal is optimal and doesn't have much memory,
then it shouldn't match the probability of the unknown.
It should end of story.
Every now and then, I search every few years
to see if anybody has noticed this thing, which I've never
found it on the web.
Yeah.
So earlier in the course class, you
mentioned that the rule-based methods didn't work
and that several other methods were
tried between 1680s.
Could you go into a bit about what
these other methods were that have been tried?
Well, I don't mean to say they don't work.
Rule-based methods are great for some kinds of problems.
So most systems make money.
And if you're trying to make hotel reservations and things,
this business of rule-based systems has a nice history.
A couple of AI researchers, really, notably Ed Feigenbaum,
who was a student of Newell and Simon,
started a company for making rule-based systems.
And the company did pretty well for a while until,
and they maintained that only an expert
in artificial intelligence could be really good at making
rule-based systems.
And so they had a lot of customers
and quite a bit of success for a year or two.
And then some people at Arthur D. Little said, oh,
we can do that.
And they made some systems that worked fine.
And the market disappeared because it turned out
that you didn't have to be good at anything in particular
to make rule-based systems work.
But for doing harder problems like translating
from one language to another, you really
needed to have more structure.
And you couldn't just take the probabilities of words
being in a sentence, but you had to look for diagrams
and trigrams and have some grammar theory and so forth.
So but generally, if you have a ordinary data processing
problem, try a rule-based system first.
Because if you understand what's going on, it's a good chance
you'll get things to work.
I'm sure that's what the Hawkins thing started out as.
I don't have any questions.
Could I ask another one for the homeworks?
Sure.
OK.
Computers and machines can use relatively few electronic
components to run a batch of different types of thought
operations.
All that changes is data over which the operation runs.
In the critic selector model, are resources
different bundles of data or different physical parts
of the brain?
Which model?
Critic or different physical parts of the brain?
Critic selector model.
Oh, actually, I've never seen a large-scale theory
of how the brain connects its.
There doesn't seem to be a global model anywhere.
Anybody read any neuroscience books lately?
I just don't know of any big diagrams.
Here's this wonderful behavioral diagram.
So how many of you have run across the word ethology?
Just a few.
There's a branch of the psychology of animals, which
is called ethology.
And it's the study of instinctive behavior.
So these and the most famous people in that field who,
well, Nico Tinbergen and Conrad Lorenz are the most famous.
I've just lost the name of the guy around the 1900
who wrote a lot about the behavior of ants.
Anybody ring a bell?
So he was sort of the first ethologist.
And these people don't study learning because it's hard to,
I don't know why.
So they're studying instinctive behavior, which
is what are the things that all fish do of a certain species.
And you get these big diagrams.
This is from a little book which you really
should read called The Study of Instinct.
And it's a beautiful book.
And if that's not enough, then there's
a two-volume similar book by Conrad Lorenz, who
was an Austrian researcher.
They did a lot of stuff together, these two people.
And it's full of diagrams showing the main behaviors
that they were able to observe of various low-cost animals.
I think I mentioned that I had some fish,
and I watched the fish tanks.
Watched the fish tanks, what they
were doing for a very long time, and came to no conclusions
at all.
And when I finally read Tinbergen and Lorenz,
I realized it just had never occurred to me
to guess what to look for.
My favorite one was that whenever a fire engine went
by, Lorenz's sticklebacks, the male sticklebacks,
would go crazy and look for a female.
Because when the female's in heat,
or whatever it's called, estrus, the lower abdomen turns red.
I think fire engines have turned yellow recently.
I don't know what the sticklebacks do without that.
So if you're interested in AI, you really
should look at at least one of these people,
because it's the first appearance of rule-based
systems in great detail in psychology.
There weren't any computers yet.
There must be 20 questions left.
Yeah?
While we're in the topic of ethology,
so I know that early on, people were kind of,
they were careful not to apply ethology to humans.
Till about, what, the 60s, E.L. Wilson with sociobiology.
So I was wondering about your opinion on that.
And maybe you can add to those thoughts, Tom.
He's pretty controversial around this area, especially.
Oh, I don't know.
I sort of grew up with Ed Wilson,
because we had the same fellowship at Harvard
for three years.
But he was almost never there, because he was out
in the jungle in some little telephone booth
watching the birds or bees.
He also had a 26-year-old aunt.
Aunt, not aunt, aunt.
A-N-T. I'm not sure what the controversy would have been,
but of course, there would be humanists who would say,
people aren't animals.
But then, what the devil are they?
Why aren't they better than they?
You've got to read this.
It's a fairly short book.
And you'll never see an animal as the same again,
because I swear, you start to notice all these little things.
You're probably wrong.
But you start picking up little pieces of behavior
and trying to figure out, what part of the instinct system
is it?
Laurence was particularly, I think,
in chapter two of The Emotion Machine,
I have some quotes from these guys.
And Laurence was particularly interested in how animals
got attached to their parents.
That is, for those animals that do get attached to their parents.
Like alligator babies, live in the alligator's mouth
for quite a while.
It's a good, safe place.
And Laurence would catch birds just when they're hatching.
And within the first day or so, some baby birds
get attached to whatever large moving object is nearby.
And that was often Conrad Laurence, rather than
the bird's mother, who is supposed
to be sitting on the egg when it hatches,
and the bird gets attached to the mother.
Most birds do, because they have to stay around and get fed.
So it is said that wherever Laurence went in Vienna,
there were some ducks or whatever,
birds that had gotten imprinted on him,
would come out of the sky and land on his shoulder
and on no one else.
And he has various theories of how they recognize him.
But you could do that, too.
Anyway, that was quite a field, this thing called ethology.
And between 1920 and 1950, 1930, I guess, 1950,
there were lots of people studying
the behavior of animals.
And Ed Wilson is probably the most well-known successor
to Laurence and Tinbergen.
And I think he just wrote a book.
Anybody seen it?
He has a huge book called Sociobiology,
which is too heavy to read.
I've run out of things.
Yes?
I was thinking about this one.
If we were to build the society of mind,
ideas from that book, had the machinery from it,
what would the initial state of the machine
be if we were to start something?
Is that dictated by the goals given to it?
By state, I mean the different agents, the resources,
they have access to.
What would that initial state look like?
He's asking if you made a model of the program to society
of mind architecture, what would you put in it to start with?
I never thought about that.
It's a great question.
I guess it depends whether you want it to be a person
or a marmoset or whatever.
You want it to be a person or a marmoset or chicken
or something.
Are there some animals that don't learn anything?
There must be.
What do the ones at Sydney Brenner study?
The elements they learn.
Very simple associations.
The little worms?
There was a rumor that if you fed them RNA, was it them
or was it some slightly higher animal?
It was worms.
What?
RNA interference.
There was one that if you taught a worm
to turn left when there was a bright light or right
and put some of its RNA into another worm,
that worm would copy that reaction,
even though it hadn't been trained.
That was slugs.
Slugs, yes.
It's a little snail-like thing.
And nobody was ever able to replicate it.
So that rumor spread around the world quite happily.
There was a great science fiction story.
I'm trying to remember in which somebody
got to eat some of an alien's RNA and got magical powers.
I think it's Larry Niven, who is wonderful at taking
little scientific ideas and making a novel out of them.
And his wife, Marilyn, was an undergraduate here.
So she introduced me to Larry Niven.
And I once got to write an article.
I once gave a lecture, and he wrote it up.
It was one of the big thrills, because Niven
is one of my heroes.
Imagine writing a book with a good idea in every paragraph.
Werner Wenge and Larry Niven and Frederick Pohl
seem to be able to do that, or at least on every page.
I don't know about every paragraph.
To follow up on that question, it
seems to me that you almost were saying
that if this machinery exists, the difference
between these sort of animals would be the start state.
And depending on the start state,
we could either create a chicken or a human.
Well, no, I don't think that most animals have scripts.
Some might, but I'd say that I don't know
where most animals are, but I sort of make these six levels.
And I'd say that none of the animals
have this top self-reflective layer,
except for all we know, dolphins and chimpanzees and whatever.
It would be nice to know more about octopuses,
because they do so many wonderful things
with their eight legs.
How does it manage?
Have you seen pictures of an octopus picking up a shell
and walking to some quiet place?
And it's got some movies of this on the web.
And then it drops the shell and climbs under it and disappears.
It's hard to imagine programming a robot to do that.
Yeah?
So I've noticed, both in your books and in the lecture,
a lot of your models and diagrams
seem to have very hierarchical structures in them.
But as you mentioned in your book and other places,
passing between levels, feedback, and self-reference
are all very important to intelligence.
So I'm curious if you could discuss
some of the uses of these very hierarchical models,
why you've represented so many things that way,
and some of the limitations there.
Well, it's probably very hard to debug things that aren't.
So we need a sort of meta theory.
One thing is that, for example, it
looks like that all neurons are almost the same.
Now, there's lots of difference in geometric features of them,
but they all use the same one or two transmitters
and every now and then, you run across people saying,
oh, neurons are incredibly complicated.
They have 100,000 connections.
You can find it if you just look up neuron on the web
and get these essays explaining that nobody will ever
understand them, because typically, a neuron
is connected to 100,000 others, and blah, blah, blah.
So it must be something inside the neuron that
figures out all this stuff.
As far as I can see, it looks almost the opposite, namely,
probably the neuron hasn't changed for half a billion
years very much, except in sort of superficial ways
in which it grows.
Because if you changed any of the genes controlling
its metabolism or the way it propagates impulses,
then the animal would die before it was born.
That's why the embryology of all mammals is almost identical.
You can't make a change at that level
after the first, before the, you can't make changes
before the first generations of cell divisions,
or everything would be clobbered.
The architecture would be all screwed up.
So I suspect that the people who say,
well, maybe the important memories of a neuron
are inside it, because there's so many fibers and things.
I bet it's sort of like saying the important memory
01:35:32,22
's trained to do some learning.
And it's also the early days of the web,
and it starts talking to another computer in Russia.
And suddenly, it gets faster and faster
and takes over all the computers in the world
and gets control of all the missiles
because they're linked to the network.
And it says, I will destroy all the cities in the world
unless you clear off some island and start
building the following machine.
I think it's Sardinia or someplace.
So they get bulldozers, and it starts
building another machine, which it calls Colossus 2.
And they ask, what's it going to do?
And Colossus says, well, you see,
I have detected that there's a really bad AI out in space,
and it's coming this way.
And I have to make myself smarter than it really quick.
Anyway, see if you can order the sequel to Colossus.
That's the second volume where the invader actually arrives,
and I forget what happens.
And then there's a third one, which
was an anti-climax because I guess
DF Jones couldn't think of anything worse
that could happen, but Martin Rees can.
Yeah?
Going back to her question about example,
and if our mind has a state that prefers to be in it,
would that example be more of a pattern recognition example?
So instead of 10, 40, 50, 55, what if it was logistical?
Good, fine, great, and you have to come up
with a word that could potentially fit in that pattern.
And then that pattern could be ways to answer, how are you?
Let's do an experiment.
How many of you have a resting state?
Sometimes when I have nothing else to do,
I try to think of twinkle, twinkle little star happening
with the second one starting in the second measure,
and then the third one starts up the third measure.
And when that happens, I start losing the first one.
And ever since I was a baby, when
I have nothing else to do, which is almost never,
I try to think of three versions of the same tune at once
and usually fail.
What do you do when you have nothing else to do?
Any volunteers?
What's yours?
I try not to think anything at all.
You tried not to or to?
Not to.
Isn't that a sort of Buddhist thing?
Yes, though.
Do you ever succeed?
How do you get out of it?
You have to think, well, enough of this nothingness.
If you succeeded, wouldn't you be dead?
We're stuck.
Eventually some stimulus will appear
that is too interesting to ignore.
Right.
And threshold goes down till even the most boring thing
is fascinating.
Yeah.
Make a good short story.
There was actually a movie that really got to me
when I was little.
These aliens were trying to infiltrate people's brains
and their thoughts.
And to keep the aliens from infiltrating your thoughts,
you had to think of a wall, which didn't make any sense
at all.
But now, whenever I try to think of nothing,
I just end up thinking of a wall.
There are these awful psychoses.
And about every five years, I get
an email from someone who says that, please help me.
There are some people who are putting these terrible ideas
in my head.
Have you ever gotten one, Pat?
And they're sort of scary because you
realize that maybe the person will suddenly figure out
that it's you who's doing it if they.
[?
Ha ha ha.
I hear assessment would have put all them together once.
I think they married.
Ha ha ha.
Remember, there was once one of them came to visit,
actually showed up, and he came to visit Norbert Wiener, who
was famous for, I mean, he's the cybernetics person
of the world.
And this person came in, and he got between Wiener and the door
and started explaining that somebody
was putting dirty words in his head
and making the grass on their lawn die.
And he was sure it was someone in the government,
and that this was getting pretty scary.
And I was near the door.
So I went and got leth in.
It's a true story.
It was nearby, and I got leth in to come in.
And leth in actually talked this guy down and took him by the arm
and went somewhere.
And I don't know what happened, but Wiener
was really scared because the guy kept
keeping him from going out.
Leth in was big.
Wiener is not very big.
Anyway, that keeps happening every few years.
I get one, and I don't answer them.
He's probably sending it to several people,
and I'm sure one of them is much better at it than we are.
How many of you have ever had to deal with an obsessed person?
How did they find you?
I don't know.
They found a number of people in the media lab, actually.
Don't answer anything.
But if they actually come, then it's not clear what to do.
Last question.
Thanks for coming.