The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
We have any opinions about consciousness?
There's one problem in the artificial intelligence people
is there's a lot of pretty smart people like Steve Pinker
and others who think that the problem of consciousness
is maybe the most important problem
and that no matter what we do in artificial intelligence,
anybody read Pinker?
I can't figure out what his basic view is,
but there's a feeling that if you can't solve
this all-important mystery, then maybe whatever we build
will be lacking in some important property.
There was another family of AI skeptics,
like Penrose, who's the physicist,
and a very good physicist indeed,
who wrote more than, I think, three different books arguing
that AI is impossible because I'm
trying to remember what he thought was missing
from machines.
Quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics was one, and Gödel theorem, incompleteness,
was another.
And for example, if you try to prove Gödel's theorem
in any particular logic, you'll find some sort of paradox
appearing where if you try to formalize the proof,
you can't prove it in the logical system
you're proving it about.
I forget what that's called.
So there are these strange logical and semi-philosophical
problems that bother people.
And Pinker's particular problem is
he doesn't see how you could make a machine be conscious.
And in particular, he doesn't see
how a machine could have a sense called qualia, which
is having a different experience from seeing something red
and from seeing something green.
If you make a machine with two photo cells
and put a green filter on one and a red filter in front
of the other and show them objects of different colors,
then they'll respond differently.
And you can get the machine to print out green and red.
And so forth.
And he's worried that no matter what you do,
the machine will only have some logical descriptions
of these things.
And it won't have a different experience from the two things.
So I'm not going to get into that.
I wonder if word is going to do this all the time
until I kill something.
What if I put it off screen?
That's a good way to deal with philosophical problems.
[?
Laughter. ?]
Just put them in back where you can't see them.
Oh, the picture disappeared.
That's really annoying.
Everything disappeared.
Think of a good question while I reboot this.
Oops.
Well, how about pressing?
That did it.
Whoops.
That's the most mysterious problem.
Does anybody have an explanation of why
computers take the same amount of time to reboot,
even though they're 1,000 times faster
than they were?
Because they have to load 1,000 times more stuff nowadays.
Yes, but why can't it load the things
that were running last time?
For some reason, they feel they have to load everything.
Maybe there's a certain amount of time
that they think humans are able to wait.
So therefore, they will load as much as they
can during that time, right?
Maybe there might be.
If they could, they might upload even more.
But they can't, because that's kind of the human patience.
And so they always run it on that one.
Does the XO take time to boot?
Yes.
It takes several seconds.
So it keeps the memory in it?
It doesn't have a max.
I'm serious.
I guess it would.
But it doesn't cost much to keep a dynamic memory refreshed
for a month or two.
If anybody can figure it out, I'd
like to know, because it seems to me
that it should be easy to make Unix remember
what state it was in.
Well, remember exactly what state it was in.
If you read it, it wouldn't be very easy.
It would definitely change the state.
Well, I mean, it could know which applications you've
been running or something.
Anyway, it's a mystery to me.
For example, in time-sharing systems, you have many users.
And the time-shared system keeps their state working fine.
And let's see if this is actually
recovered from its bug.
Maybe one of those forms of word doesn't work.
That's a bad.
When computers hibernate and stuff,
they save their entire memory just to disk.
Reboot it, and it takes generally on the modern system
30 to 45 seconds just to load.
It takes the entire memory content from disk.
That could be the trouble.
Why can't it load the part that it needs?
But never mind.
I'm sure that there's something wrong with this all.
But now I've got another bug.
That one seems better.
Nope.
Sorry about all this.
I might have to use the backup.
Anyway, I'll talk about consciousness again.
But I'm assuming that you've read all or most of chapter 4.
And we could start out with this kind of question,
which is, I think of evolution as, is this working?
I think of us as part of the result of a 400 million year,
400 mega year process.
And because the first evidence for forms of life
occurred about 400 million years ago, which is pretty long.
The Earth appears to be about 4 billion years.
So life didn't start up right away.
And so there was 100 million years of the first one
celled animals.
Maybe there were some million years of molecules
that didn't leave any trace at all.
So before there was a cell membrane,
you could imagine that there was a lot of evolution.
But nobody has proposed a plausible theory
of what it could have been.
There are about five or six pretty good theories
of how life might have started.
There had to be some way of making a complex molecule that
could make copies of itself.
And one standard theory is that if you had just
the right kind of muddy surface, you
could get some structure that would form on that,
peel away, and leave an imprint.
But it sounds unlikely to me, because those molecules would
have been much smaller than the grains of mud.
But who knows?
Anyway, there's 100 million years of one celled things.
And then there's 100 million years
of things leading to the various invertebrates,
and 100 million years of fish, reptile-like things,
and mammals.
And we're at the very most recent part
of that big fourth collection of things.
And I think there's a, oops, is this not going to work?
All right.
That's my bug, not MIT's.
So humans' development, splitting off
from something between a chimpanzee and a gorilla,
has a history of about 4 million years.
The dolphins developed, which have very large brains,
somewhat like ours in that they have a big cortex,
developed before that.
And I forget, does anybody know?
My recollection is that they stopped developing
about 4 million years ago.
So the dolphins' brains got to a certain size.
The fossil ones of, I think, about 4 million years ago
are comparable to the present ones.
So nobody knows why they stopped.
But there are a lot of reasons why it's dangerous
to make a larger brain.
And especially if you're not a fish,
because it would be slower and hard to get around,
and it would have to eat more.
And that's a bad combination.
And other little bugs, like taking larger, longer
to mature, so if there are any dangers,
the danger of being killed before you reproduce
is a big handicap in evolution.
In fact, if you think of the number of generations of humans
since, presumably, they've been living for a 20-year lifespan
for most of that 4 million years, like other primates,
compare that to bacteria.
Some bacteria can reproduce every 20 minutes instead
of 20 years, or 10 years, or whatever it is.
So the evolution of smaller animals
is vastly faster by factors of order of hundreds.
And so generally, these big, slow, long-lived animals
have huge evolutionary disadvantages.
Anyway, here's four major ones.
So what made up for that?
And that's why chapter 4 sort of,
I don't think I wrote anything about this in chapter 4,
but that's why it's interesting to ask,
why are there so many ways to think,
and how did we develop them?
And a lot of that comes from this evolutionary problem
that, as you got smarter and heavier,
it got more and more difficult to survive.
So your collection of resourcefulness
had to keep track.
Well, in that 4 billion years, this only happened once.
Well, the octopuses are pretty smart.
And the birds, just consider how much a bird
does with its sub-P-sized brain.
But it seems to me that it's hard to generalize
from the evolution of humans to anything else because what?
We must have been unbelievably lucky.
William Calvin has an interesting book.
He's a neurologist who writes pretty interesting things
about the development of intelligence.
And he attributes a lot of human superiority
to a series of dreadful accidents, namely
five or six ice ages in which the human population was
knocked down.
Nobody knows to how small, but it
could have been as small as tens of thousands.
And we just squeaked by.
And only the very, very smartest of them
managed to get through a few hundred years
of terrible weather and shortage of food and so forth.
So that's anybody remember the title of?
Have you read any William Calvin?
Interesting neurologist out in California somewhere.
There is a very small handful of people,
including William Calvin, that I think
have good ideas about intelligence in general
and how it evolved and so forth.
And Aaron Sloman is a philosopher
at the University of Birmingham in England,
who has theories that are maybe the closest to mine.
And he's a very good technical philosopher.
So if you're interested in anything about AI,
oh, if you just search for Aaron Sloman, he's the only one.
So Google will find him instantly for you.
And he's got dozens of really deep essays
about various aspects of intelligence
and problem solving.
The only other philosopher I think is comparable
is Daniel Dennett.
But Dennett is more concerned with classical philosophical
issues and a little less concerned with exactly how
does the human mind work.
So to put it another way, Aaron Sloman writes programs,
and Dennett doesn't.
If you're facing a classical philosopher in an argument,
then I would say that that would be quite complicated.
What's that?
If you're in an argument with a classical philosopher
about issues in classical philosophy,
Dennett's arguments come back in.
Yeah, but I'm not sure you can learn very much.
No.
I love classical philosophy, but the issues they discuss
don't make much sense anymore.
Philosophy is where science has come from,
but philosophy departments keep teaching what they were.
What chapter does this story first appear in?
Is that?
Yeah.
Joan is partway across the street.
She's thinking about the future.
She sees and hears a car coming and makes a quick decision
about whether to back up or run across, and she runs across.
And I have a little essay about the kinds of issues there.
And if you ask what was going on in Joan's mind,
then this is a short version of an even larger list
that I just got tired of writing.
And I don't know how different all of these 20 or 30 things
are, but when you see discussions of consciousness
in Pinker and everyone except Dennett and Sloman,
they keep insisting that consciousness
is a special phenomenon.
And my view is that consciousness is there's
certainly a lot of questions to ask,
but there isn't one big one.
I think Pinker, very artistical art,
can't think of the right word.
He says, this is the big central problem.
And what is this amazing thing called consciousness?
And he calls that the hard question of psychology.
But if you look at this and say, how did she select a way
to choose among options, or how did she
describe her body's condition, or how
did she describe her three most noticeable
recent mental states, or whatever, each of those
are different questions.
And if you look at it from the point of view of a programmer,
you could say, how could a program that's
keeping pushdown lists and various registers and caches
and blah, blah, blah, how would a program do this one?
How do you think about what you've recently done?
Well, you must have made a representation of it.
Maybe you had a pushdown list and were
able to back up and go to the other state,
but then the state of you that's wondering
how to describe that other state wouldn't be there anymore.
So it looks like you need to have two copies of a process
or some way to time share the processor or whatever.
And so if you dwell on this kind of question for a while,
then you say, there's something wrong with Pinker.
Yes, he's talking about a very hard problem,
but he's got blurred.
Maybe 20, 30, 100, I don't know, pretty hard problems.
And each of these is fairly hard.
But on the other hand, for each of them,
you can probably think of a couple of ways
to program something that does something
a little bit like that.
How do you go from a verbal description, two blocks
supporting a third block, to a visual image if you have one?
Well, you could think of a lot of ways those.
I didn't say what shape the blocks were and so forth.
And you can think of your minds.
One part of your mind can see the other part,
trying to figure out which way to arrange those blocks.
Maybe all three blocks are just vertically like this, this,
this.
That's two blocks supporting a third block.
And so instead of saying consciousness
is the hard problem, you could say,
consciousness is 30 pretty hard problems.
And I bet I could make some progress on each of them
if I spent two or three years, or if I had 30 students
spending, or whatever.
Actually, what you really want to do
is fool some professors into thinking about your problem
when you're a student.
That's the only way to actually get anything done.
Well, I'm being a little dismissive.
And another thing that Pinker and the other people
of his ilk, the philosophers who try to find a central problem,
do is say, well, there's another hard problem, which
is the problem called qualia, which
is, what is the psychological difference between something
that's red and green?
And I usually feel uncomfortable about that because I
was in such a conversation when I discovered
that Bob Fano, who was one of our professors,
was colorblind.
And he didn't have that qualia, so it's sort of embarrassing.
In the Exploratorium, how many of you
have been at a few, maybe the best science
museum in the world somewhere near San Francisco?
But one trouble, or one feature of it,
it was designed by Frank Oppenheimer, who
was Robert Oppenheimer's brother.
He was quite a good physicist.
And I used to hang around there when
I spent a term at Stanford.
It had a lot of visual exhibits with optical illusions
and colored lights doing different things
and changes of perspective and a lot of binocular vision
tricks.
And there's a problem with that kind of exhibit.
We have them here at Science Museum, too,
which is that about 15% or 20% of people
don't see stereo very well.
And at least 10% don't view stereo images at all.
And some of these is because one eye's vision is very bad.
But actually, if one eye is 20-20 and the other eye is 20-100,
you see stereo fine anyway, because it's
amazing how blurred one of the images can be.
Then some people just can't fuse the images.
They don't have separate eye controls, whatever.
And a certain percentage don't fuse stereo for no reason
that anybody can measure and so forth.
But that means that if a big family is looking
at this exhibit, probably one of them
is only pretending that he or she can see the illusion.
And I couldn't figure out any way to get out of that,
but I thought if you make a museum,
you should be sure to include some exhibits for the what's
the name for a person who only, is there a name for non-fusers?
When you get a pilot license, you
have to pass binocular vision test, which
seems awfully pointless to me, because if you
need stereo, which only works for about 30 feet,
then you're probably dead anyway.
Maybe the last half second of landing.
So anyway, so much for the idea of consciousness itself.
You might figure out something to say about the difference
between blue and green and yellow and brown and so forth.
But why is that really more important
than the difference between vanilla and chocolate?
Why do the philosophers pick on these particular perceptual
distinctions as being fundamentally hard mysteries,
whereas they don't seem to?
They're always picking on color.
Beats me.
So what does it mean to say, in going back
to that little story of crossing the street,
to say that Joan is conscious of something?
And here's a little diagram of a mind at work.
And I picked on four kinds of processes
that are self-models, whatever you're doing.
There are probably a few parts of your brain
that are telling little stories or making
visual representations or whatever,
showing what you've been doing mentally or physically
or emotionally or whatever distinctions you want to draw.
Different parts of your brain are
keeping different historical narrations and representations
maybe over different time scales.
And so I'm imagining I'm just picking
on four different things that are usually
happening at any time in your mind.
And these two diagrams are describing or representing
two mental activities, one of which
is actually doing something.
You make some decision to get something done,
and you have to write a program and start carrying it out.
And the program involves descriptions of things
that you might want to change and looking
at records of what usually happens when you do this
so you can avoid accidents.
So one side of your mind, which is performing actions,
could be having four processes.
And I'm using pretty much the same.
They're not quite.
Wonder why I changed one and not the others.
And then there's another part of your mind
that's monitoring the results of these little actions
as you're solving a problem.
And those involve pretty much the same kinds
of different processes, making models of how
you've changed yourself or deciding what to remember.
As you look at the situation that you're manipulating,
you notice some features, and you
change your descriptions of the parts that you were.
In other words, in the course of solving a problem,
you're making all sorts of temporary records
and learning little things, stuffing them away.
So the processes that we lump into being conscious
involve all sorts of different kinds of activities.
And do you feel there's a great difference between the things
you're doing that you're conscious of
and the often equally complicated things
that you're doing that you can say much less about?
How do you recognize a tune?
Do you say, I've noticed this interval and that interval,
and then in the next four measures,
we swap those intervals and we put this one before that
instead of after?
If you look at twinkle twinkle little star,
there's a couple of inversions.
And if you're a musician, you might in fact
be thinking geometrically as the sounds are coming in
and processing them.
And some composers know a great deal about what they're doing,
and some don't have the slightest idea
and can't even write it down.
And I don't know if they produce equally complicated music.
What's this slide for?
Anyway, when you look at the issues
that philosophers discuss like qualia and self-awareness,
they usually pick what seem to be very simple examples
like red and green.
But they don't.
But what am I trying to say?
But someone like Pinker, a philosopher
talking about qualities, qualia, tends
to say there's something very different about red and green.
What is this?
What is the difference?
And I'm just saying, why did I have a slide that mentioned
common sense knowledge?
Well, if you've ever cut yourself, it might hurt.
And there's this red thing.
And you might remember unconsciously
for the rest of your life that something red signifies
pain and uncertainty and anxiety and injury and so forth.
And very likely, you don't have any really scary associations
with green things.
So when people say the quality of red,
it's so different from green, well,
maybe it's like the difference between being stabbed or not.
And it's not very subtle.
And philosophically, it's hard to think
of anything puzzling about it.
You might ask, why is it so hard to tell
the difference between pleasure and pain or to describe it?
And the answer is, you could go on for hours describing it
in sickening and disgusting detail
without any philosophical difficulty at all.
So what do you think of redness?
You think of tomatoes and blood and what
are the 10 most common things?
I don't know.
But I don't see that in the discussion of qualia.
And the qualia philosophers try to say
there's something very simple and indescribable and absolute
about these primary sensations.
But in fact, if you look at the visual system,
there are different cells for those
which are sensitive to different spectra.
But the color of a region in the visual field
does not depend on the color of that region
so much as the difference between it
and other regions near it.
So I don't have any slides to show that.
But the first time you see some demonstrations of that,
it's amazing because you always thought
that when you look at a patch of red, you're seeing red.
But if the whole visual field is red slightly,
you hardly can tell at all after a few seconds
what the background color is.
So I'm going to stop talking about those things.
But who has an idea about consciousness
and how we should think about it?
Yeah?
Maybe it's just the k lines that are in our brain.
So k lines are different for each person.
That's interesting.
If you think of k lines as gadgets in your brain
which each k line turns on a different activity
in a lot of different brain centers, perhaps.
And I'm not sure what.
So at each moment, you have a set of k lines that are active.
Right, but you mentioned in different people,
they're probably different.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So when you say red and I say red, how similar are they?
That's a wonderful question.
And I don't know what to say.
How would we measure that?
I mean, I know I can perceive some.
So for example, a frog, I think he
can perceive some with his eyes, like pixels.
And these structures are the same.
We can perceive some atomic things.
And this would be the same for us.
But when we are growing, we probably
create these k lines for red or green.
Right, the frog probably has a built-in.
Yeah, and probably it's very similar,
because we have centers in our brain.
So for example, for vision, we have a center.
And probably things that are close by
will have a tendency to come together.
And so red would be similar to each one of us,
because it's a very low-level concept.
But if you go high level, probably, for example,
for numbers, I have a different representation than you.
I think there's a story about finding that he represented
numbers by seeing them.
There is another person that represents just
by seeing the number, and then you've
got to come to see it better than you.
He has an interesting idea that maybe in the first few layers
of visual circuits, we all share.
They're pretty similar.
And so for the primary, for the first three or four levels
of visual processing, the kinds of events
that happen when red and green are together,
or blue and yellow, those are two different kinds of events.
But the processes for most of us are almost identical.
The trouble is, when you get to the level of words,
that might be 10 or 20 processes away from that.
And when you say the word red, then that
has probably closer connections to blood and tomatoes
than to patches of.
Anyway, it's a nice.
And so the animals could have consciousness,
because they would have these k-lines.
For example, monkeys or dogs.
But when you go to a rock, this rock
doesn't have the ability to create a k-line.
So it doesn't have consciousness.
And so it would have some kind of, with primitive animals,
it would have less consciousness.
It would be some linear function of how
you can represent stuff.
Yes, well, I guess if you make discrimination tests,
then people would be very similar in which color patterns.
Did I mention that some fraction of women
have two sets of red cones?
There are three colors.
There's a yellow one.
It's between the red and the green.
I thought it was very close to the red, though.
Any closer to red?
So some women have four different primary colors.
And do you know what fraction is?
I thought it was only about 10% of them, right?
Yeah, I think it's 5% of people overall.
So it'd be 10% of women.
I thought it's only women.
It might be.
Oh, well, we could look it up.
One of my friends has a 12-color printer.
He says it costs hundreds of dollars to replace the ink.
But I can't see any of it.
On my printer, which is a Tektronix phaser,
this is supposed to be red.
But it doesn't look very red to me.
Does that look red to any of you?
What's the issue?
I'll have to refer to where you found it.
It's a great printer.
You feed it four bars of wax, which are solid.
And it melts them and puts them on a rotating drum.
And the feature is that it stays the same for years.
But it's not very good.
It was made for paper.
So it might look red, more red on paper.
No, I tried it.
And then I'm sure if you put a blue light bulb in there,
we could make it all the same.
I think what I'll do is I saw a phaser on the third floor
somewhere.
Maybe I'll borrow their red one and see
if it's different from mine.
Well, let me conclude, because I think this really
raises lots of wonderful questions.
And I wonder if we wouldn't.
Does this make things too easy?
I think what happens in the discussions
of the philosophers like Pinker and most of the others
is that they feel there's a really hard problem, which
is, what is the sense of being?
What does it mean to have an experience,
to perceive something?
And how they want to argue that somehow they are saying
they can't imagine how anything that has an explanation,
how any program or any process or any mechanical system
could feel pain or sorrow or anxiety
or any of these things that we call feelings.
And I think this is a curious idea that
is stuck in our culture, which is that if something
is hard to express, it must be because it's
so different from anything else that there's
no way to describe it.
So if I say, exactly how does it feel to feel pain?
Well, if you look in literature, you'll
see lots of synonyms like stabbing or griping or aching.
You might find 50 or I mentioned this in first lecture,
that there are lots of words about emotional or I
don't know what to call them, states.
But that doesn't mean that they're simple.
That means the reason you have so many words for describing
simple states, feelings, and so forth
is that not that they're simple and a lot
of different things that have nothing to do with one another,
but that each of those is a very complicated process.
What does it mean when something's hurting?
It means it's hard to get anything done.
I remember when I first got this insight
because I was driving down from Dartmouth to Boston
and I had a toothache.
And it was really getting very bad.
That's why I was driving down because I
didn't know what to do and I had a dentist here.
And after a while, it sort of fills up my mind.
And I'm saying this is very dangerous
because maybe I shouldn't be driving.
But if I don't drive, it'll get worse.
So I really should drive very fast.
So what is pain?
Pain is a reaction of some very smart parts of your mind
to the malfunctioning of other very smart parts.
And to describe it, you would have
to have a really big theory of psychology
with more parts than in Freud or in my Society of Mind
Book, which has only about 300 pages, each of which
describes some different aspect of thinking.
So if something takes 300 pages to describe,
this fools you into thinking, oh, it's indescribable.
It must be elemental.
It couldn't be mechanical.
It's too simple.
If pain were like the four gears in a differential,
well, most humans don't.
If you show them a differential and say,
what happens if you do this, the average intelligent human being
is incapable of saying, oh, I see.
This will go that way.
A normal person can't understand those four little gears.
So of course, pain seems irreducible
because maybe it involves 30 or 40 parts.
And another 30 or 40 of your little Society of Mind
processes are looking at them.
And none of them know much about how the others work.
And so the way you get your PhD in philosophy
is by saying, oh, I won't even try.
I will give an explanation for why I can't do it,
which is that it's too simple to say anything about.
That's why the word qualia only appears once
in the Motion Machine book.
And a lot of people complained about that.
They said, why doesn't he?
They say you should read I Forget What instead.
Anyway, I don't think I have anything else
in this beautiful sets of how did it end.
If you look on my web page, which I don't think I can do,
oh, well, it'll probably there.
I just realized I could quit word.
Well, there's a paper called Causal Diversity.
And it's an interesting idea of how do you answer questions
if there's some phenomenon going on.
And something like being in pain is a phenomenon.
What do you want to say about it?
Here's a little diagram that occurred to me once, which
is what kinds of sciences or what kinds of disciplines
or ways of thinking do you use for answering
different kinds of questions?
So I got this little matrix.
And you ask, suppose something happens.
And think of it in terms of two dimensions,
namely the world is in a certain state.
Something happens, and the world gets into a different state.
And you want to know why things change.
Like if I stand this up, oh, I can even balance it.
I don't know.
No, I can't.
Anyway, what happened there, it fell over.
And you know the reason.
If it were perfectly centered, it might stand there forever.
Or even if it were perfectly balanced,
there's a certain quantum probability
that its position and momentum are conjugate.
So even if I try to position it very precisely,
it will have a certain momentum and eventually fall over.
It might take a billion years, or it might be a few seconds.
So if we take any situation, we could
ask how many things are affecting
the state of the system, and how large are they?
So how many causes?
A few causes or a lot?
And what are the effects of each of those?
A good example is a gas, if you had a cylinder and a piston.
And if it's this size, then there
would probably be a few quadrillion or trillion
anyway molecules of air, mostly oxygen and nitrogen
and argon there.
And every now and then, they would all
happen to be going this way instead of this way,
and the piston would move out.
And it probably wouldn't move noticeably in a trillion
in a billion years, but eventually it would.
But anyway, there's a phenomenon where
there's a very large number of causes, each of which
has a very small effect.
And what kind of science or what kind of computer program
or whatever would you need to predict
what will happen in each of those situations?
So if there's a very few causes and their effects are small,
then you just add them up, nothing to it.
If there's a very large number of causes
and each has a large effect, then go home.
There's nothing to say because any of those causes
might overcome all the others.
So I found nine states.
And if there are a large number of small causes,
then neural networks and fuzzy logic
might be a way to handle a situation like that.
And if there are a very small number of large causes,
then some kind of logic will work.
Sometimes there are two causes that are XORed.
So if they're both on, nothing happens.
If they're both off, nothing happens.
And if just one is on, you get a large effect.
And you just say, it's X or Y. And analogies and example
based reasoning.
So these are where AI is good, I think,
and for lots of everyday problems, like the easy ones
or large numbers and small effects,
you can use statistics.
And small numbers of large effects,
you can use common sense reasoning and so forth.
So this is the realm of AI.
And of course, it changes every year
as you get better or worse at handling things by these.
If you look at artificial intelligence today,
it's mostly stuck up here.
There are lots of places you can make money
by not using symbolic reasoning.
And there are lots of things which are
pretty interesting problems here.
And of course, what we want to do
is get to this region where the machines start solving problems
that people are no good at.
So who has a question or a complaint?
Great.
But consciousness, again.
Wouldn't it have been easier to do that?
Is this working?
No.
It goes to the camera.
Oh.
Yeah, you can hear it.
OK, well, I'll try to repeat it.
Wouldn't it have been easier if we never
created the suitcase, as you put it in one of the papers,
the suitcase with consciousness, and just kept
those individual concepts?
Second part of that question is, how do we
know this is what they had in mind when they initially
created the word consciousness?
That's a nice question.
Where did the word consciousness come from?
And would we be better off if nobody had that idea?
I think I talked about that a little bit the other day,
that there's the sort of legal concept of responsibility.
And if somebody decided that they would steal something,
then they become a thief.
And so it's a very useful idea in society
for controlling people to recognize
which things people do are deliberate
and involve some reflection and which things are
because they're learnable.
It's a very nice question.
Would it be better if we had never had the word?
I think it might be better if we didn't have it in psychology.
But it's hard to get rid of it for social reasons,
just because you have to be able to write down a law in some
form that people can reproduce.
I'm trying to think of a scientific example where
there was a wrong term that.
Can anybody think of an example of a concept
that held science back for a long time?
Certainly the idea that astronomical bodies
had to go in circles, because the idea of ellipses
didn't occur much till Kepler.
Are there any ellipses?
Euclid knew about ellipses, didn't he?
Does anybody know?
That's a nice one.
You take a string, and you put your pencil in there
and go like that.
That's a terrible ellipse.
People knew about ellipses.
Certainly Kepler knew but didn't invent it.
So I think the idea of free will is a social idea,
and we certainly still have it.
Most educated people think there is such a thing.
Just as most people think there's such a thing
as consciousness instead of 40 fuzzy sets.
How many of you believe in free will?
It's the uncaused cause.
Free will means you can do something for no reason at all,
and therefore you're terribly proud of it.
Well, that's what it is.
It's a very strange concept.
But more important, you can blame people for it
and punish them.
If they couldn't help doing it, then there's
no way you can get even.
It has the implication that there is a choice.
Yeah.
I suppose for each agent in the brain,
there's a sort of little choice, but it has several inputs.
But I don't think the word choice means anything.
Well, random things have lots of small causes.
So random is over here.
Many small causes, so you can't figure out
what will happen because even if you know 99 of those causes,
you don't know what the 100th one is.
And if they all got XORed by a very simple deterministic
logic, then you're screwed.
So but again, it's illegal.
The freedom of will is it just doesn't
make sense to punish people for things they didn't decide to do.
If it happened in a part of the nervous system that can't learn,
if they can't learn, then you can put them in jail
so that they won't be able to do it again.
But you'd have to be, but the chances
are it's not going to change the chance
that they'll try to do it if it's, in fact, a random.
Did you have?
Yeah.
So machine learning has been around for a long time.
And processors are really fast right now.
Computers are really fast.
Do you believe they are doing some mistake,
like people that are doing research in machine learning?
I mean, they are trying to.
Well, machine learning is, to me, it's an empty expression.
Do you mean are they doing some Bayesian reasoning?
I mean, nobody does machine learning.
Each person has some particular idea
about how to make a machine improve its performance
by experience.
But it's a terrible expression.
So either statistical methods, like improving methods
to machine learning to the machine
to infer what point will belong to a data set or whatever.
Sure.
Like people that do that, do you think
they are doing some mistake, like do you
think there would be more advance
if you represent that in a different way
and try to program that?
The problem is this.
Suppose you have, yes.
Here's some system that has a bunch of gadgets
that affect each other, just a lot of interactions
and dependencies.
And you want to know, if it's in a certain state,
what will be the next state?
So suppose you put a lion and a tiger in a cage,
then how do you predict what will happen?
Well, what you could do is if you've
got a million lions and a million tigers
and a million cages, then you could put a lion and a tiger
in each cage.
And then you could say the chances that the tiger will win
is 0.576239, because that's how many cases the tiger won
and the lion will win, I don't know, that many.
So that is, to me, that's what statistical learning is.
It has no way to make smart hypotheses.
So to me, anybody who's working on statistical learning
is very smart, and he's doing what we did in 1960 and quit,
50 years out of date.
What you need is a smart way to make a hypothesis
about what's going on.
Now, if nothing's going on except Brownian motion,
statistical learning is fine.
But if there's an intricate thing like a differential,
which is this thing and that thing are summing up
in a certain way, how do you decide
to find the conditional probability of that hypothesis?
And so in other words, you can skim the cream off the problem
by finding the things that happen with high probability.
But you need to have a theory of what's happening in there
to conjecture that something of low probability
on the surface will happen.
And I just, so here's the thing.
If you have a theory of statistical learning,
then your job is to find an example that it works on.
It's the opposite of what you want for intelligence, which
is, how do you make progress on a problem
that you don't know the answer to, what kind of answer?
So how do they generate?
I don't know.
Are you up on how do the statistical Bayesian people
decide which conditional probability to score?
Suppose there's 10 variables.
Then there's 2 to the 10th or 1,000 conditional probabilities
to consider.
If there's 100 variables, and so you can do it.
2 to the 10th is nothing, and a fast computer
can do many times 1,000 things per second.
But suppose there's 100 variables.
2 to the 100th is 10 to the 30th.
No computer can do that.
So I'm saying statistical learning is great.
It's so smart.
I'm repeating myself.
Anybody have an argument about that?
I bet several of you are taking courses
in statistical learning.
What do they say about that problem?
Part of the trial and error.
What?
Largely trial and error.
Yeah, but what do you try when there's 10 to the 30th?
You can't.
So do they say, I quit?
This theory is not going to solve hard problems.
So once you admit that and say, I'm
working on something that will solve lots of easy problems,
more power to you.
But please don't teach it to my students.
What do you think about the way statistical
system works in front of us?
I can't hear you too well.
So in other words, the statistical learning people
are really in this place, and they're wasting our time.
However, they can make billions of dollars
solving easy problems.
There's nothing wrong with it.
It just has no future.
What do you think about the relationship
with statistical learning methods?
Of what?
The relationship between statistical learning methods
and maybe some of these.
I couldn't get the fourth relation.
So the relationship of statistical to more abstract
ideas like boosting or something,
where you might want to admit that you're using a one
and you're voting for it.
There's a very simple answer, but it's far.
It's inductive probability.
There's a theory.
Theory.
I wonder if anybody could summarize that nicely.
Have you tried?
Basically, I can try it next time.
You should assume that everything
is generated by a program.
And your prior over-the-space and possible program
should be the description length of the program.
Suppose there's a set of data, then what's
the shortest description you can make of it?
And that will give you a chance of having
a very good explanation.
Now, what Solomonoff did was say,
suppose that something's happened
and you make all possible theories
of what all possible descriptions of what
could have happened, and then you take the shortest one
and give that a see if that works
and see what it predicts will happen next.
And then you take, say it's all binary,
then there's two possible descriptions
that are one bit longer.
And maybe one of them fits the data and the other doesn't.
So you give that one half the weight.
So Solomonoff imagines an infinite sum
where you take all possible computer programs
and see which of them produce that data set.
And if they produce that data set,
then you run the program one more step and see what it.
In other words, suppose your problem is
you see a bunch of data about the history of something,
like what was the price of a certain stock
for the last billion years?
And you want to see, will it go up or down tomorrow?
Will you make all possible descriptions of that data set
and see the shortest ones much more
than the longer descriptions?
So the trouble with that is that you can't actually
compute such things because it's sort of uncomputable.
However, you can use heuristics to approximate it.
So there are about a dozen people
in the world who are making theories of how
to do Solomonoff induction.
And that's where now another piece of advice for students
is if you see a lot of people doing something,
then if you want to be sure that you'll have a job someday,
do what's popular and you've got a good chance.
If you want to win a Nobel Prize or solve
an important problem, then don't do what's popular
because the chances are you'll just
be a frog in a big pond of frogs.
I think there's probably only half a dozen people
in the world working on Solomonoff induction,
even though it's been around since 1960
because it needs a few more ideas on how to approximate it.
But unless you want to make a living,
don't do Bayesian learning.
Yeah.
I don't know if this actually works,
but if we take Bayesian learning and we kind of
apply some kind of rules to it, let's say we see something
with very small probability and we kind of just
like discard that and never consider it again,
wouldn't that kind of stimulate what we're trying to do
with getting representations of things?
Yeah, I think.
Does it kind of make it much more discreet
and kind of make it much more easier and more tractable?
Or is it, like my question would be,
isn't bringing representations for things saying,
this chair has this representation,
isn't that kind of doing the same kind
of statistical modeling but just throwing away
a lot of the stuff that we might not want to look at
or we consider as things that shouldn't be looked at?
I think, see, there's the statistical thing
and there's the question of, suppose
there's a lot of variables, x1, x2, x10 to the 9th,
10 to the 5th.
Let's say there's 100,000 variables.
Then there's 2 to the 100,000 Pijs.
But it isn't ij.
It's ij up to 10,000 subscripts.
So what you need is a good idea for which things to look at.
And that means you want to take common sense knowledge
and jump out of the Bayesian knowledge.
The problem with the Bayesian learning system
is you're estimating the values of conditional probabilities,
but you have to decide which conditional probabilities
to estimate the values of.
And the answer is, well, look at it another way.
Look at history.
And you see 1,000 years go by.
What was the population of the world
between 500 AD, between the time of Augustine
and the time of Newton, or 1500, Tycho, Brahe, and those people?
There's 1,000 years.
And I don't know.
Is there 100 million people in the world?
Anybody know?
About how many people were there in 1500?
Don't they teach any history?
I think history starts, I changed schools
around third grade, so there was no European history.
So to me, American history is recent,
and European history is old.
So 1776 is after 1815.
That is, to me, history ends with Napoleon,
because then I got into fourth grade.
Don't you all have that?
You've got gaps in your knowledge,
because the curricula aren't.
Somebody should make a map of those.
There are about half a billion people in 1500.
That's a lot.
This is from Google?
This is from Wikipedia, actually.
Well.
So there's half a billion people not thinking of the planets
going in ellipses.
So why is that?
How is a Bayesian person going to make the right hypothesis
if it's not in the algebraic extension of the things
they're considering?
I mean, it could look it up in Wikipedia,
but Bayesian thing doesn't do that.
Our AIs will, yeah.
But when we are kids, don't we learn?
They call it sense of knowledge?
Well, I'm saying what happened in the thousand years.
You actually have to tell people to consider,
I'm telling the Bayesians to quit that and do something smart.
Somebody has to tell them.
I don't mean I'm the Newton, but they need one.
What are they doing?
What do they hope to accomplish?
How are they going to solve a hard problem?
Well, they don't have to.
The way you predict the stock market today
is Bayesian with a reaction time of a millisecond.
And you can get all the money from the poor people who
are investing in your bank.
It's OK.
Who cares?
But maybe it shouldn't be allowed.
I don't know.
Do you think that the goal of Bayesian
is to replace complete human intelligence,
like to create a computer that will be able to reason by itself?
Or is there also a way to create a system that will be better?
We have to stop getting sick and dying and becoming senile.
Yes.
Now, there are several ways to fix this.
One is to freeze you and just never thaw you out.
But we don't want to be stuck with people like us
for the rest of all time because there isn't much time left.
The sun is going to be a red giant in 3 billion years.
So we have to get out of here.
And the way to get out of here is make yourself
into smart robots.
Help.
Let's get out of this.
We have to get out of these bodies.
Yep.
So you talked a lot about emotions.
But emotions you describe as like states of mind.
And if you have like, for example, n states of mind,
they represent, I don't know, log n bits of information.
Why should we spend so much time talking about,
like, so little information?
Talking about?
Little information.
Like, if we have n states of, or n emotions,
they would represent log n bits of information.
And that's very little information
that they conceive.
So for example, if I'm happy or sad,
like if I had just two states, happy or sad.
If you just had two states, you couldn't compute anything.
I'm not sure what you're getting at.
Emotions conceive too little information.
They don't represent much information inside our brain.
Why should they be so important in intelligence since they
I don't think, I think emotions generally
are important for lizards.
I don't think they're important for humans.
You have to stay alive to think.
So you've got a lot of machinery that makes sure
that you don't starve to death.
So there's gadgets that measure your blood sugar and things
like that, and make sure that you eat.
So those are very nice.
On the other hand, if you simplified it,
you just need three volts to run the CPU.
And then you don't need all that junk.
So they are not very important for us.
They're only important to keep you alive.
But they don't help you write your thesis.
The people who consider such questions
are the science fiction writers.
So there are lots of thinking about what kind of creatures
could there be besides humans.
And if you look at detective stories or things,
then you find that there are some good people and bad people
and stuff like that.
But to me, those general literature is all the same.
When you've read 100 books, you've read them all,
except for science fiction.
It's my standard joke that I don't
think much of literature, except because the science
fiction people say, what would happen
if people had a different set of emotions
or different ways to think?
Or one of my favorite ones is Larry Niven and Jerry Purnell,
who just wrote a couple of volumes about,
what about a creature that has one big hand and two
little hands?
Do you remember what it's called?
The gripping hand.
This is for holding the work, while this one holds
the soldering iron and the solder.
That's right.
That's how the book sort of begins.
And there's imagination.
On the other hand, you can read Jane Eyre, and it's lovely.
But do you end up better than you are or slightly worse?
And if you read 100 of them, luckily, she only wrote 10.
I'm serious.
You have to look at Larry Niven and Robert Heinlein
and those people.
And when you look at the reviews by the literary people,
they say the characters aren't developed very well.
Well, Foo, the last thing you want in your head
is a well-developed literary character.
What would you do with her?
Yes.
I love your questions.
Can you wake them up?
When we are small babies, we kind of
are creating this common sense knowledge.
And we have a lot of different inputs.
So for example, I'm talking to you.
There is this input of the sound, the vision,
all these different inputs.
Aren't we somehow, when we are babies,
what's the relation between these inputs?
For example, decay lines.
Isn't the machine learning guys are
in that with a lot of variables and maybe trying
to infer what's the small set?
What would be the difference if you go deep down?
Are they trying to find, for example, a path in a graph?
I think you're right in the sense that I'll
bet that if you take each of those highly advanced brain
centers and say, well, it's got something generating
hypotheses maybe or so forth, but underneath it,
you probably have something very like a Bayesian reinforcement
thing.
So they're probably all over the place.
And maybe 90% of your machinery is made of little ones.
But it's the symbolic things and the K lines
that give them the right things to learn.
But I think you raise another question
which I'm very sentimental about because of the history of how
our projects got started.
Namely, nobody knew much about how
children develop in 1900.
For all of human history, as far as I know, generally, babies
are regarded like ignorant adults.
There aren't much theories of how children develop.
And it isn't until 1930 that we see any real substantial child
psychology.
And child psychology is mostly that one Swiss character,
Jean Piaget.
It's pronounced John for some reason.
And he had three children and observed them.
I think his first publication was something about mushrooms.
He had been in botany.
Is that right?
Cynthia, do you remember what was Piaget's original something?
But then he studied these children
and he wrote several books about how they learned.
And as far as I know, this is about the first time in history
that anybody tried to make, observe children, infants
very closely and chart how they learned and so forth.
And my partner Seymour Papert was Piaget's assistant
for several years before he came to MIT.
And I started the artificial intelligence group
with John McCarthy, who had been one of my classmates
in graduate school at Princeton in math, actually.
And then McCarthy went to start another AI group in Stanford.
And Seymour Papert appeared on my scene just at the same time.
And it was a kind of miracle because we
met at some meeting in London where we both presented
the same machine learning paper on Bayesian probabilities
in some linear learning system.
We both hit it off because we obviously fought the same way.
But anyway, Piaget had been conducting,
one of the principal people conducting the experiments
on young children in Piaget's group.
And when Piaget got older and retired in about 1985,
Cynthia, do you remember?
When did Piaget quit?
It's about when we started.
Didn't he die in 1980 or something?
Around then.
There were several good researchers there.
He was trying to get Seymour to even take over the message.
He wanted Seymour to take over at some point.
And there were several good people there, amazing people.
But the Swiss government sort of stopped supporting it.
And the greatest laboratory on child psychology
in the world faded away.
It's closed now.
And nothing like it ever started again.
So this is a strange thing, maybe
the most important part of human psychology
is what happens the first 10 years, the first five years.
And if you're interested in that,
you could find a few places where somebody
has a little grant to do it.
But what a tragedy.
Anyway, we tried to do some of it here.
But Papert got more interested in,
and Cynthia here, got more interested
in how to improve early education
than find out how children worked.
Is there any big laboratory at all doing that?
Where is child psychology?
There are a few places, but none of them
are famous enough to notice.
For a while, there was stuff in Ontario.
In Brazelton, for example.
Brazelton, yeah.
Anyway, it's curious because you'd
think that would be one of the most important things,
how do humans develop?
It's very strange.
Yeah?
So infants, when they are a year old,
I think there's a paper about it.
They learn how to achieve goals, not the means.
And then I don't know after what year
they learn how to achieve a means.
So for example, I think they do experiments
on putting a hand in the ear.
Like left ear.
And then chipmunks do the same as one year old infants.
And somehow, I believe that, for example,
vintages between infants and chipmunks are very similar.
But we can represent things better because we have this.
You're talking about chips.
Chipmunks?
Yeah.
Like apes, in general.
Yeah, right.
I believe there are some apes that can learn sign language.
I'm not sure if that's right.
And they can imitate the goals.
And for example, dogs can achieve a goal,
but they can't imagine themselves at each moment.
And maybe that's because of how they represent things.
Maybe they represent badly.
They don't have a good hierarchy.
There's some very interesting questions about that.
And that's why we need more laboratories.
But here's an example.
We had a researcher at MIT named Richard Held.
And he did lots of interesting experiments
on young animals.
So for example, he discovered that if you take a cat
or a dog, if you have a dog on a leash
and you take it somewhere, there's
a very good chance it will find its way back
because it remembers what it did.
But he discovered if you take a cat or a dog
and you take it for a walk and go somewhere, it won't learn.
Because it didn't do it itself.
So in other words, if you take it on a route passively,
even a dozen times or 100 times, it
won't learn that path if it didn't actually
have any motor reactions.
So that was very convincing.
And the world became convinced that for spatial learning,
you have to participate.
Many years later, we were working
with a cerebral palsy guy who had never locomoted himself
very much.
And I'm trying to remember his name.
Well, his name doesn't matter.
But the logo project had started.
And he was able to, by putting a hat with a stick on his head,
he was able to type keys, which is really
very boring and tedious.
And believe it or not, even though he could barely talk,
he quickly learned to control the turtle, a floor turtle.
And you could tell it to turn left and right
and go forward one unit, stuff like that.
And the remarkable thing was that no sooner
did he start controlling this turtle,
then the turtle went over here.
He turned it around, and he wanted it to go back to here.
And everybody predicted that he would get left and right
reversed because he had never had any experience in the world.
But right off, he knew which way to do it.
So he had learned spatial navigation pretty much never
having done much of it himself.
And Richard Held was very embarrassed
but had to conclude that what you learned from cats and dogs
might not apply to people.
We ran into a little trouble because there
was another psychologist we tried to convince of this.
And that psychologist said, well, maybe this was a,
it took three years for him to develop a lot of skills.
And the psychologist said, well, maybe that's a freak.
I won't approve your PhD thesis until you do a dozen of them.
I didn't mention the psychologist's name
because anyway, so we had a sort of Piaget-like laboratory,
but we never worked with infants, did we?
d the rat, that so on, nobody has any trouble,
and that's a recursion.
But if you say, this is the dog that the cat that the rat bit
ate, people can't understand that.
But it's what?
The brain of a man's tail co-optimization.
Yeah, why is language restricted,
and that you can't embed clauses past the level of two or three?
Which Chomsky never admitted.
Can't be the case that we also learned that.
We also learned that certain patterns can only
exist between words, and so when we hear a sentence,
we do parse it using a parse tree,
but we learn using a parse tree, too.
We learn that when you hear a sentence,
go after trying to parse it using three words, two words,
four words, and just try that, see if it works.
If it doesn't, try another number of words.
Can't this itself be like learning
the number of words that usually happen in the class?
Isn't this kind of a problem?
Well, I'm not sure why it's very different from learning
that you have to open the box before you take the thing out.
We learn procedures.
I'm not sure.
I don't believe in grammar.
That is.
When we were trying to teach a machine to be like a human being,
would we just lay out the very basics
and let it grow like a child with learning?
Or would we put these representations in there?
Like, put the representation in the box?
Well, a child doesn't learn language
unless there are people to teach it.
However, in that.
Maybe we can expose the machine to the web or to,
or we can expose it to the world somehow in some kind of way.
I'm not sure what question.
You're asking, is all children's learning of a particular type?
Are they learning frames, or are they learning grammar rules?
Do you want a uniform theory of learning?
I'd say which one is a better approach,
that the machine has very basic things, and it learns.
So is a machine like, should we make machines as infants
and let them learn things by, for example,
giving them a stream that's from the internet,
from communication over the internet,
or communication among other human beings,
just like a child learns from seeing his parents.
Several people have.
To actually embed all that knowledge into a machine
and then expect it to act with you from the beginning.
Well, if you look at the history,
you'll find that I'm not sure how to look it up.
But quite a few people have tried
to make learning systems that start with very little
and keep developing.
And the most impressive ones were the ones by Douglas Lenat.
But eventually, he gave up, and he
had systems that learned a few things, but they petered out.
And he changed his orientation to trying to build up
common sense libraries.
But trying to think of the name for self-organizing systems.
There are probably a dozen.
If you're interested, I'll try to find some of them.
But for some reason, people have given up on that.
And certainly worth a try.
As for language, I think the theory
that language is based on grammar is just plain wrong.
I suspect it's based on certain kinds of frame manipulation
things.
And the idea of abstract syntax is really not very productive,
or it hasn't.
Anyway, because you want it to be
able to fit into a system for inference as well.
I'm just bluffing here.
Did you have a question?
I was just going to say, it seems
that what you're saying might be considered
to be a form of example-based reasoning.
You just have lots and lots of examples,
which I'm not unlike the work that Ed Roy does,
who's a child learning the word water, hearing lots of people
use that word in different contexts and examples.
While you're here, Janet Baker was a pioneer
in speech recognition.
How come the latest systems suddenly got better?
Are they just bigger databases?
The early ones you had to train for an hour.
Yeah, but we now have so many more examples and exemplars
that you can much better characterize
their ability, which is tremendous, between people.
And you typically have multiple models,
a lot of different models, of how notes
in the space of how people say different things
and allow you to characterize them really well
so it can be a much better job.
You'll always get better at your models
of a given person speaking and modeling their voice.
But you can now model a population much better.
And you have so much more data.
They're really getting useful.
Oh, dear.
OK, unless somebody has a really urgent question.
Thanks for coming.
Thank you.