The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
So what I'm going to do in this course
is discuss mostly ideas that are already
in the book called The Emotion Machine.
I'm sorry, I used that title.
And the older book called The Society of Mind, which are,
the books are not quite the same.
They overlap a bit in material, but they're
sort of complementary.
I like the old one better because the chapters are
all one page long.
And they're moderately independent.
So if you don't like one, you can skip it.
The new book is much denser, and it has a smaller
number of long chapters.
And I think it's over the years, I
got lots of reactions from young people in high school,
for example, almost all of whom liked The Society of Mind
and found it easy to read and seemed to understand it.
There are lots of criticisms by older people
who maybe some of them found it harder
to put so many fragments together, who knows.
But most of this class, most of the things
I'd like to say are in those books.
So it's really like a big seminar.
And my hope is that everyone who comes to this class
would have a couple of questions that they'd like to discuss.
And if I can't answer them, maybe some others if you can.
So I'd like to think of this as a super seminar.
And normally, I don't prepare lectures.
And I just start off asking if there are any questions.
And if there are not, I get really pissed off.
But anyway, I'm going to start with a series of slides.
So why do we need machines?
And partly, there are a lot of problems.
Unlike most species or kinds of animals,
humans have only been around a few million years.
And they're very clever compared to other animals.
But it's not clear how long they will last.
And when we go, we might take all the others with us.
So there are a whole set of serious problems
that are arising because there are so many humans.
And here's just a little list of things.
There's a better list in a book by the astronomer royal,
Martin Lise of England.
Anybody know the title?
Our Final Hour?
Yes, Our Final Hour.
It's a slightly scary title.
And when I was a teenager, World War II
came to an end with the dropping of two atomic bombs
on Japan.
And I didn't believe the first one was real
because it was in Hiroshima.
So I assumed that the US had somehow
made a big underwater tanker with 20,000 tons of TNT
and some few grams of radium or something
and blown it up in the harbor.
And first, it flew an airplane over,
dropping some little thing.
And this was to fool the Japanese into thinking
that we have an atomic bomb.
But when they did it again over Nagasaki,
that wasn't feasible.
And when I was in grade school, sometimes if I
said something very bright, I would hear a teacher saying,
maybe he's another J. Robert Oppenheimer
because that was the name of a scientist who
had been head of the Manhattan Project.
And he was, I think, three or four years earlier
in grade school than I was.
And I thought it was very strange for a person
to have a first name as just being
a letter rather than a name.
And many years later, when I was at Princeton
in graduate school, I met the Robert Oppenheimer,
and that was a great pleasure.
And in fact, he took me to lunch with a couple
of other people I admired, namely Gödel and Einstein,
which was very exciting, except I couldn't understand
Einstein because I wasn't used to people
with a strong German accent.
But I understood Gödel just fine.
And after that lunch was over, I went and spent about a year
learning about Turing machines and trying
to prove theorems about them and so forth.
So anyway, in the course of these talks,
we'll run across a few of these people.
And here's a big list of the people
that I'm mostly indebted to for the ideas in the Society
of Mind and the Emotion Machine.
The ones in blue are people I've actually met.
It would be nice to have met Aristotle because no one really
knows much about him, but you really should read.
Just skim through some of that, and you'll
find that this is a really smart guy.
We don't know if he wrote this stuff
or if it were compiled by his students,
like a lot of Feynman's writing is.
And von Neumann's writing is edited from notes
by their students.
And anyway, the astonishing thing about Aristotle
is that he seems to be slightly more imaginative
than most cognitive scientists you'll
run into in the present day.
It would have been nice to know Spinoza and Kant and the others
also.
Freud wrote 30 or 40 books.
So did he fall off this list?
There he is.
I just made this list the other day,
and I was looking up these people
to find their birthdays and stuff.
Yes?
Why are there no Eastern philosophers?
Because they're religious, as far as I can see.
Who would you say Buddha?
No, I mean, just Eastern thinkers.
How about that?
Neymar.
Maybe I never heard of them.
Confucius?
Who?
Confucius.
Or, you know, three preaching writers here.
There are a lot of great thinkers from China.
Well, I only know of them through aphorisms.
Single proverbs.
But I don't know that Confucius had a theory of thinking.
Do you think he did?
There are a lot of different schools of thought.
But I don't know if they call it thinking.
Well, I've looked at Buddhist theories, and they're,
I don't think they would get a C plus.
And one problem is that there are cultures,
there's something about Greek culture because it had science.
It had experiments.
Somebody has a theory, and they say,
and like Epimenides, Lucretius, somewhere in the society mind,
I think I quoted Lucretius about translucent objects.
And he says they have the particular appearance
because the rays of light bounce many times before they
get to the surface.
So you can't tell where they started.
And I don't find in Eastern philosophy theories that say,
here's what I think, and here's a reason why.
I've looked at Buddhist stuff, and it's
strange lists of psychological principles,
every one of which looks pretty wrong.
And they make nice two-dimensional diagrams,
but no evidence for any of them.
So I don't know whether to take it seriously.
I think a lot of thinkers have analogies from observation.
And you're right that some of them probably
didn't really test it because a lot of ideology
cannot be tested.
On the other hand, there are scientists meaning like,
Well, what can't be tested?
I mean, some of the ideologies probably.
Then why?
I don't know.
If they can't be tested, why should one look at it twice?
If I can test it, then I can test it so many logically.
I don't know.
Like culture, can you test culture?
OK, I think this is a serious argument.
It seems to me that science began a little bit in China,
a little bit in India.
In the Arabic world, they got up to the middle
of high school algebra.
But then, what?
Well, but this wasn't as good as Archimedes, who got
to the beginning of calculus.
So if you look at most cultures, they
never got to the critical point of getting theories,
doing experiments, discussing them,
and then throwing them out.
And so if you look at Buddhist philosophy,
it's 2,500 years old.
If you look at Greek physics, yes,
Archimedes almost got calculus, and he
got lots of nice principles.
And Buddha mentions, at some point,
if you want to weigh an elephant, put him in a boat,
and then take the elephant out and put rocks in till the boat
sinks to the same level.
So there you see a good idea.
But if you look at the history of the culture,
if people still say this 1,000-year-old stuff is good,
then you should say, no, it's not.
By the way, same story about the elephants.
There's a story in Chinese history
that has the same metallic meaning.
Maybe there's no one person that can get along with it.
No, the question is, why did it stop?
Why did it stop?
Ancient wisdom is generally not very good,
and we shouldn't respect it for too long.
And that's.
So we have to look at the house.
Everybody's standing on a giant shoulder, right?
No, everybody.
No, we got rid of alchemy.
We got rid of, what do you call it?
What's caloric?
You jump off their shoulder.
You don't stay on them.
So it's good to know history, but if the history doesn't
get anywhere, then you don't want
to admire it too much, because you have to ask,
why did it stop?
What went wrong?
And usually, it went wrong because barbarians came in
and, well, you know what happened to Archimedes.
Some Roman killed him.
But anyway, no, it's a good question.
Why didn't science happen a million years ago?
Because humans are 5 million years old.
So what took it so long?
And no, it's more sure.
OK, do you have a theory of why science
didn't develop for so long?
In most cultures, it might be religion,
which is a sort of science that doesn't use evidence,
and in fact, kills people who try to get it.
And so there are systematic reasons
why most cultures failed, and maybe somebody has written it.
Is there a book on why science disappeared except once?
It's rather remarkable, isn't it?
After all, the idea, if somebody says something
and somebody else says, OK, let's do an experiment
to see if that's right, you don't have to be very bright.
So how come it didn't happen all the time everywhere?
Curious.
I don't know the answer to that, but I know Paul Davies has
sort of an anecdote about that, or he's speculating,
even in Europe, where it did happen, was the fluke.
And I think he gives the example of,
suppose an asteroid or a comet crashed in Paris in a fairly
year, he gives me 1,150 or 1,200 or something.
Then what?
Whether it was science simply never developed anywhere.
You need to sort of raise things up as a thought problem.
Well, history is full of flukes.
I'm trying to remember who wrote that nice book about the plague.
Some woman.
And she mentions that this was spread by rats and fleas
or something, and 30% or 40% of the population of many countries
in Europe died.
And the next generation had a lot of furniture.
The standard of living went way up.
So anyway, here's a list of disasters.
And oh, come on.
And Martin Rees is the Royal Astronomer
and has that book about the last hour or whatever.
And I'm making another longer list,
but he has lots of obvious disasters,
like some high school student looks up the genetic sequence
for smallpox virus has been published.
And now you can write a list of nucleotides
and send it somewhere.
They'll make it for about $0.50 or $1 per nucleotide.
So for a couple of hundred dollars,
you can make a virus or a few hundred.
So one possibility is that some high school student
makes some smallpox, only gets it wrong,
and it kills everyone.
So there are lots of disasters like that.
And no one knows what to do about that,
because the DNA synthesis machinery
is becoming less and less expensive,
and probably the average rich private high school
could afford one.
So there are lots of other things that could happen.
But one particular one is this graph, which I just made up.
An interesting fact is that since 1950,
when the first antibiotics started to appear,
as I mentioned, I was a kid in the 1940s.
I was a kid in the 1940s, and penicillin
had just hit the stands.
And there wasn't much of it.
And there was a researcher who lived a few blocks from us
whose dog had cancer.
And so its father, I don't know what you call the owner
of a dog, sneaked some penicillin out of the lab
and gave it to the dog who died anyway.
But he said, well, nobody's tried penicillin on cancer yet.
Maybe it will work.
And a lot of people were mad at him
because he probably cost some human its life.
But he said he might have saved a billion humans their lives.
So ethics.
Ethicists are people who give reasons not to do things.
And I'm not saying they're wrong, but it's a funny job.
So anyway, since that sort of thing
happened and medicine began to advance,
people have been living one year longer every 12.
So it's 60 years since 1950.
So that's five of those six.
So they're living six or seven years longer now
than they were when I was born.
And somebody mentioned that that curve stopped
the last few years for other reasons.
But anyway, if you extrapolated that,
you find that the lifespan is going to keep increasing.
How much, we don't know.
Another problem is that you might discover enough
about genetics to get rid of most of the serious diseases.
Maybe just 20 or 30 genes are responsible for most deaths.
Right now, and if you could fix those, which we can't do yet,
there's no way to change a gene in a person
because invading all the cells is
a pretty massive intervention.
But we'll get around that.
And then it might be that people will suddenly start
living 200 or 300 years.
At some point, the population has to slow down.
And so you can only reach equilibrium
with one child per family, and probably less than that.
And so all the work has to be done by two or 300-year-olds.
And let's hope they're good and healthy.
So anyway, I think it's very important
that we get smart robots because we're
going to have to stem the population.
And I hope people will live longer, and blah, blah, blah.
And so these robots have to be smart enough
to replace most people.
How do you make something smart?
Well, artificial intelligence is the field
whose goal has been to make machines that do things
that we regard as smart or intelligent or whatever
you want to call it.
And the idea of seriously making machines smart
has roots that go back to a few pioneers, like Leibniz, who
wrote about automata and that sort of thing.
But the idea of a general purpose computer
didn't appear till the 1930s and 40s in some sense.
The first form of the general purpose computer
appears really in the 1920s and 30s
with the work of a mathematician,
Emil Post at NYU, who I happened to never meet.
But we had some friends in common.
And he had the idea of production rules
and basically rule-based systems and proved
various theorems about them.
Then Kurt Gödel showed that if you had something
like a computer or a procedure that had the right kinds
of rules, it could compute all sorts of things.
But there were some things it couldn't
compute, unsolvable problems.
And that became an exciting branch of mathematics.
And the star thinker in that field
was Alan Turing, who invented a very simple kind
of universal general purpose computer.
Instead of random access memory, it
just had a tape which it could write on and read
and change symbols and would go back and forth.
And if it's in state x at c symbol y,
it will print symbol z over the x and move to the left or right.
And just a bunch of rules like that
was enough to make a universal computer.
And so from about 1936, it was sort
of clear to a large mathematical community
that these were great things.
And a couple of general purpose like computers,
very simple ones, were built in the 1930s and more in the 1940s.
And in the 1950s, big companies started
to make big computers, which were
rooms full of equipment.
And but as you know, most programs could only
do some particular thing.
And none of them were very smart,
whereas a human can handle lots of kinds of situations.
And if you have one that you've never seen before,
there's a good chance you'll think of a new way
to deal with that and so forth.
And so how do you make a machine that doesn't get stuck almost
all the time?
And I like to use the word resourcefulness,
although I left an r out of that one.
Is there a shorter word?
So here's a good example, my favorite example
of a situation where a person is born, more or less,
with a dozen different ways of dealing with something.
And the problem that I imagine that you're dealing with
is this, my favorite example, is I'm thirsty.
So I see that glass of water, and I do that and get it.
Actually, I am.
On the other hand, if I were here,
I would never in a whole lifetime do this.
You never walk out a window by mistake.
We're incredibly reliable.
So how do I know how far it is?
And that slide shows you 12 different ways
that your vision system, that's only your vision system,
has to measure distances.
So gradients, if things are sort of blurry,
then they must be pretty far away.
That's sort of on a foggy day outside.
Here's a situation.
If you assume those are both chairs of the same size,
then you know that this chair is about twice as far away
as that, although you don't well.
And you know how far away they are pretty much
by the absolute size.
If you have two eyes that work well,
then if something is less than 30 feet away,
you can make a pretty good estimate of its distance
by focusing both eyes on some feature.
And your brain can tell how far apart your eyes are looking.
So there's 12 different things.
It's more than you need.
Lots of people are missing half of those.
Lots of people have very poor vision in one eye.
And some people cannot fuse stereo images,
even though both eyes seem to have 20-20 vision.
And in some cases, nobody knows why they can't do that.
I think I once took a test for being a pilot,
and they wanted to be sure you could do stereo vision, which
seemed very strange, because if you're an airplane
and you're less than 30 or 40 feet away from something,
then yes, you could use stereo, but it's too late.
So anyway, that's interesting.
See, if you can think of an example where a person has
even more 12 of these, it's pretty amazing, isn't it?
That's more redundancy.
This is too hard to read, but somehow I
found in an Aristotle essay the idea
that you should represent things in multiple ways.
You might describe a house.
One person might describe a house
as a shelter against destruction by wind, rain, and heat.
Another might describe it as a construction
of stones, bricks, and timbers.
But a third possible description would
say it was in that form, in that material, with that purpose.
So you see, there's two different descriptions.
One is the functional description.
It's a shelter.
The second one is a structural description, how it's made.
And Aristotle says, which is the better description?
And he dismisses the material one or the functional one,
is not rather the person who combines
both in a single statement.
And then I found a paragraph by Feynman
who says, every theoretical physicist who is any good
knows six or seven different ways
to represent exactly the same physics.
And you know that they're all equivalent,
but you keep them all in your head,
hoping that they will give you different ideas
for guessing.
Guessing, I should put more dots.
Anyway, that whole argument is to say
that the interesting thing about people
is that they have so many ways to do things and perceive
things and think of things.
And in some cases, we even know that there
are different parts of the brain that
are involved in one aspect or another
of constructing those different representations or descriptions.
If you look at one of my favorite books,
weighs about 20 pounds, it's the book on the nervous system
by Kandel and Schwartz.
And the index to that book is quite a lot of pages long,
and it mentions 400 different structures in the brain.
So the brain is not like the, well,
I shouldn't make fun of the liver, because for all I know,
the liver has 400 different mini processes
for doing things.
But the brain has distinguishable areas
that seem to perform several hundred different functions.
And with a microscope, at first they all
look pretty much the same.
But if you look closely, you see slightly different patterns
of how most layers of the cortex of the brain, most parts of it,
have six layers, and each has a population
of different kinds of cells.
There are a lot of cross connections up and down
and sideways to other.
There are a range in columns of between 400 and 1,000 cells,
and you have a couple of million of those.
And there are lots of differences
between the columns in different areas,
and we know some of the functions.
Most cases, we don't know much about how any of them
actually work, with the main exception of vision,
where the functions of the cells in the visual cortex
are fairly well understood at low levels.
So we know how that part of the brain
finds the edges and boundaries of different areas
and textures and regions of the visual field.
But we do not know even a little bit
about how the brain recognizes something
as a chair and an overhead projector and a CRT screen
and that sort of thing.
So the kind of question that I got
interested in was, how can you have a system which
has a very large number of different kinds of computers,
each of which by itself might be relatively simple or might not,
I suppose?
And how could you put them together
into a larger system which could do things like learn language
and prove theorems and convince people to do things
that they would never have dreamed of,
doing five minutes earlier and stuff like that?
Now, the first sort of things I was interested in
was, in fact, how to simulate simple kinds of nerve cells
because in the 1950s, there was about almost 100 years, really
more like 50 years, of science discovering things
about neurons and nerve cells, the axons and dendrites
that they used to communicate with other neurons.
So if you go back to 1890, you find a few anatomists
discovering some of the functions or connections
of neurons in the brain.
And you find a few experimental physicists.
There was no oscilloscope yet, but there
were very high-gain amped galvanometers
which could detect pulses going along a nerve fiber.
And by 1900, it was pretty clear that part of the activity
in a nerve cell was chemical and part was electrical.
And by 1920 or 30, with the cathode ray tube appearing,
mostly because of television, it
became possible to do a lot of neurophysiology
by sticking needles in brains.
The vacuum tube appears around 1900,
and you can make amplifiers that can see millivolts and then
microvolts.
So in the beginning of the 20th century,
there was lots of progress.
By 1950, we knew a lot about the nervous system,
but we still don't know much about how you learn something
in the brain.
It's quite clear that the things called synapses are involved.
Connections between two neurons become
better at conducting nerve impulses
under some conditions.
But no one knows how higher-level knowledge is
represented in the brain yet.
And the Society of Mind Book had a lot of theories about that.
And in particular, there was a theory
called K-lines, knowledge lines or something
that came partly from me and partly
from a couple of other researchers
named David Waltz and Jordan Pollock.
And that's a sort of nice theory of how neural networks might
remember higher-level concepts.
And for some reason, although that kind of work
is from around 1980, which is 30 years ago,
it has not hit the neuroscience community.
So if you look at the Emotion Machine
Book or the Society of Mind in Amazon,
you might run across a review by a neurologist named Richard
Restak, who says that Minsky makes up
a lot of concepts like K-lines and micro-names
and stuff like that that nobody's ever heard of.
And there's no evidence for them.
And he ignores the possibility that it
isn't the nerve cells in the brain that are important,
but the supporting tissues called glia,
which hold the neurons up and feed them.
And he goes on for a couple of insane paragraphs.
It's very interesting, because it doesn't occur to him
that you can't look for something
until you have the idea of it.
And so here is this 30-year-old idea of K-lines.
And go and ask your favorite neurologist, neuroscientist,
what it is.
And he said, oh, I think that's some AI thing,
but where's the evidence for it?
What do you suppose is my reaction to that?
Who is supposed to get the evidence?
So it seems to me that there's a strange field in neuroscience,
which is that it doesn't want new ideas unless you've
proved them.
So I try to have conversations with them,
but I get somewhat tired of it.
Anyway, but in this course, I'm taking the opposite approach,
which is that we don't want a theory of thinking.
We want a lot of them, because probably psychology
is not like physics.
What's the most wonderful thing about physics?
Most wonderful thing is that they have unified theories.
There wasn't much of a unified theory until Newton,
and he got these three laws, wonderful laws.
One was the gravitational idea that bodies attract each other
with a force that's the inverse square of the distance
between them.
Another is that kinetic energy is conserved.
I forget what the third one is.
Oh, equal reaction is equal and opposite.
If two things collide, they transfer equal amount
of momentum to both.
There was a little problem up to Newton's time.
Galileo got some of those ideas,
and my impression from reading him
is that he has a dim idea that there are two things around.
There's kinetic energy, which is mv, and there's momentum is mv,
and there's kinetic energy, which is mv squared.
And he doesn't have the clear idea
that there are two different things here,
and you can't blame him.
I would think you wouldn't think that two quantities would
combine in two different ways to make
two important different concepts.
Well, that got clear to Newton somehow,
and Galileo is a bit muddled, although he
gets almost all the consequences of those things right.
But he doesn't get the orbits and things to come out.
Anyway, what's happened in artificial intelligence,
like most fields, is that people said,
well, let's try to understand thinking and psychology,
and let's use physics as our model.
And so what we want is to get a very small number
of universal laws.
And a lot of psychologists struggled around to do that,
and then they gradually separated
so that there were some psychologists,
like Bill Estes, who worked out some very nice mathematical
rules for reinforcement-based learning.
Got a simple rule.
If you designed an experiment right,
it predicted pretty well how many trials it
would take a rat or a pigeon or a dog or whatever
to learn a certain thing from trial and error.
And Estes got a set of four or five rules,
which looked like Newton's laws.
And if you designed your experiment very carefully
and shielded the animal from noise and everything else,
which is what a physicist would do for a physics experiment,
the reinforcement theories got some pretty good models
of how to make a machine learn, but they weren't good enough.
So here's a whole list of things that
happened in the early years of cognitive psychology
when people were trying to make theories of thinking
and they were imitating the physicists.
By physics envy, to borrow a term of Freud,
the idea is, can you find a few simple rules that
will apply to very broad classes of psychological phenomena?
And this led to various kinds of projects,
lots of neural network and reinforcement
and statistical-based methods led to learning machines
that were pretty good at learning
in some kinds of situations.
And they're becoming very popular,
but I don't like them, because if you
have a lot of variables, like 50 or 100,
then to use a probabilistic analysis,
you have to think of all combinations
of those variables.
Because if two of them are combined in something
like an exclusive or a manner, I just
put the light pen in a pocket.
It's either in a left pocket or a right pocket.
Can't be both.
That's an XOR that will cause a lot of trouble
to a learning machine.
And if there are 100 variables, there's
no way you could decide which of the 2 to the 100
Boolean combinations of those variables you should think about.
And so lots of statistical learning systems
are good for lots of applications,
but they just won't cut it to solve hard problems
where the hypothesis is a little bit complicated
and has 7 or 8 variables with complicated interactions.
So most statistical learning people
assume that if you get a lot of partial ones,
then you can look for combinations of ones
that have high correlations with the result.
Then you can start combining them,
and things get better and better.
However, mathematically, if an effect you're looking for
depends on the exclusive or of several variables,
there's no way to approach that by successive approximations.
If any one of the variables is missing,
there won't be any correlation of the phenomenon
with the others.
Anyway, that's a long story, but I
think it's worth complaining about because almost all
young people who start working on artificial intelligence
look around and say, what's popular?
Statistical learning.
So I'll do that.
That's exactly the way to kill yourself scientifically.
You don't want to get the most popular thing.
What am I really good at that's different?
And what are the chances that that
would provide another thing?
So you end of long speech.
Another problem in the last 30 years,
and I'm sort of, as you'll see during my lectures,
I think a lot of wonderful things
happened between 1950 when the idea of AI
first got articulated, 1950s, and then the 20 years
after that from 1960 to 1980.
A lot of early experiments, and I'll show you some of them,
looked very promising.
In fact, they may be here we go.
In 1961, Jim Slagle was a young graduate student here at MIT.
He was blind.
He had gotten some retinal degeneration thing
in his first or second year of high school.
He was told that he would lose all his vision
and there was no treatment or hope.
So he learned Braille while he could still see.
And when he got to MIT, he was completely blind.
But there was a nice big parking lot in Technology Square.
And he would ride a bicycle and people like Sussman and Winston
and whoever was around would yell at him,
telling him where the next obstacle would be.
And Jim got better and better at that.
And nothing would stop him.
And he decided he would write a program that, oh, I
wrote a program that would take any formula
and find its derivative.
It was really easy because there are just about five rules.
Like, if there's a product uv, then you
compute u times the derivative of v plus v times u dv plus v du.
So I wrote a 20-line list program
that did all the algebraic expressions.
And what it would do is put d's in the right place
and then it would go back through the expression again.
Wherever it saw a d, it would do the derivative
of the thing after that and nothing to it.
So Slagle said, well, I'll do integrals.
And we all said, well, that's very hard.
Nobody knows how to do it.
And in fact, in Providence at the home
of the American Mathematical Society,
there is a big library called the Bateman Manuscript
Project, which has been collecting
all known integrals for 100 years.
And when anybody finds a new integral
that they can integrate in closed form,
they send the formulas to the Bateman Manuscript Project.
And some hackers there have developed ways to index it.
So if you had an integral and you didn't
know how to integrate it, you could look it up.
And that was pretty big.
I should say that Slagle succeeded
in writing a program that managed
to do all of the kinds of integrals
that one usually found on the first year calculus course
at MIT and got an A in those.
Couldn't do word problems.
And the uncanny thing is that if it
was a problem that usually took a MIT student five or 10
minutes, Slagle's program would take five or 10 minutes.
It's running on a IBM 701 with 20-millisecond cycle time.
It's incredibly slow.
You can type almost that fast and 16K of words of memory.
So there's no significance whatever
to this accident of time.
It would now take a microsecond or so,
be 100 million times, 1,000 million times faster
than a student.
Quite remarkable.
I don't have a slide.
Joel Moses then, Slagle went and graduated.
Joel Moses was another student who was, is he provost now,
or what?
What?
He got tired of it.
A terrific student.
And he set up a project called Maxima for Project Mac,
Symbolic, something around algebra,
and got several people all over the country
working on integration.
And at some point, a couple of them, Bobby Kavaniss
and I forget the other one, found a procedure that
could, in fact, integrate everything,
every algebraic expression that can
be integrated in closed form.
I forget the couple of constraints on it.
And that became a widely used system.
It ultimately got replaced by Stephen Wolfram's Mathematica.
But Maxima was sort of the world class symbolic mathematician
for quite a few years.
Moses mentioned to me he had read Slagle's program, Thesis,
and it took him a couple of weeks
to understand the two pages or three pages of Lisp
that Slagle had written, because being blind,
Slagle had tried to get the thing into as compact a form
as possible.
But that's symbolic.
It's too easy.
Here's a more ambitious one, which is three years later,
Dan Bobrow, who is now a vice president doing something
at Xerox.
And it solved problems like this.
The gas consumption of my car is 15 miles per gallon.
The distance between Boston and New York is 250 miles.
What is the number of gallons used
on a trip between Boston and New York?
And it chomps away and solves that.
It has about 100 rules.
It doesn't really know what any of those words mean,
but it thinks that the word is equals the distance between.
Doesn't care what Boston and New York is.
It has a format thing which says the distance between two
things.
And it never bothers to, you see,
because the phrase Boston and New York
occurs twice in the example.
It just replaces that by some symbol.
It was fairly remarkable.
And generally, if you had an algebra problem
and you told it to Bobrow, Bobrow
could type something in and it would solve it.
If you typed it in, it probably wouldn't,
but it had more than half a chance, or less about half
a chance.
So it was pretty good.
And if you look at an out of print book I wrote called,
I compiled called Semantic Information Processing,
most of Bobrow's program is in that.
So that's 1964.
I'll skip Winograd, which is perhaps
the most interesting program.
This was a program where you could talk to a robot that I
don't have a good picture on the slide,
but they're a bunch of blocks of different colors.
They're all cubes in the rectangular blocks.
And you can say, which is the largest block on top
of the big blue block?
And it would answer you.
And you could say, put the large red block
on top of the small green block.
And it would do that.
And Winograd's program was, of course, a symbolic one.
We actually built a robot and I guess we built it second.
Our friends at Stanford built a robot
and they imported Winograd's program
and they had the robot actually performing these operations
that you told it to do by typing.
And it was pretty exciting.
My favorite program in that period
was this one because it's so psychological.
This is called a geometrical analogy test
and it's on some IQ tests.
A is to B as C is to which of the following five?
And Evans wrote a set of rules which
were pretty good at this.
Did as well as 16-year-olds and it picks this one.
And if you ask it why, it says something like,
I don't have a reason.
It moves the largest object down or something like that.
Makes up different reasons.
So you see, in some sense, we're going backwards in age
because we're going from calculus to algebra
to simple analogies.
Oh, there it is.
That's one where the largest object moves down.
Don't know why I have two of them.
These are for another lecture.
OK.
So that was a period in which we picked problems
that people considered hard because they
were mathematical.
But when you think about it more, you see, well,
those math things are just procedures.
And once you know what Laplace and Gauss
and those mathematicians, Newton and people did,
you can write down systematic procedures for integrating
or for solving simultaneous algebraic constraint equations
or things like that.
And so there's very little to it.
So in some sense, if you look at what
you're doing in math in high school, in education,
you're going from hard to easy.
It's just that most people aren't
very good at obeying really simple rules because it's
so hideously boring or something.
So we gradually started to ask, well,
why can't we make machines understand everyday things?
The things that everyone regards as common sense.
And people can do so.
You don't need machines to do them.
One of my favorite examples is, why
can you pull something with a string but not push?
And there's been a lot of publicity
recently about that interesting program written
group at IBM called Watson, which
is good at finding facts about sports people and celebrities
and politics and so forth.
But there's no way it could understand
why you could push, pull something with a string
but not push.
And I don't know of any program that
has that concept or way of dealing with it.
So that's what I got interested in.
And starting around maybe the middle 1970s or late 1970s,
several of us started to stop doing the easy stuff
and trying to make theories of how
you would do the kinds of things that people
are uniquely good at.
I don't know of animals.
Well, I don't know.
I'm sure a monkey wouldn't try to push anything with a string.
Maybe it does it very quickly and you don't notice.
And one aspect of common sense thinking
is going right back to that idea of vision
having a dozen different systems is
that whatever a person normally is doing,
they are probably representing it in several different ways.
And here's an actual scene of two kids
named Julie and Henry who are playing with blocks.
It's pretty hard to see those blocks.
And you can think that Julie is thinking seven thoughts.
I'd like to see a longer list.
Maybe a good essay would be to take a few examples
and say, what are the most common microworlds?
See, physical, social, emotional, mental,
instrumental, whatever that is, visual, tactile, spatial.
She's thinking all these things.
What if I pulled out that bottom block?
You can't see the tower very well.
Should I help him or knock his tower down?
How would he react?
I forgot where I left the arch-shaped block.
That was real.
It's somewhere over here, but I don't think we could.
Maybe it's that.
I don't know.
I remember when it happened, she mentioned
that she reached around and it wasn't where she thought it was.
So common sense thinking involves this in most cases,
I think, several representations.
I don't know if it's as many as seven or maybe 20 or what.
That's the kind of thing we want to know how to do.
OK, I think I'll stop and we'll discuss things.
But in the next lecture, I'll talk about a model
of how I think thinking works.
What's the difference between us and our ancestors?
We know we have a larger brain.
But if you think about it, if you took the brain
that you already had in, say, do I
remember the name of the little monkey that
looks like a squirrel, jumps around in trees?
Anybody know it?
What?
Maybe.
It's a squirrel-like thing.
You wouldn't know it was a monkey
till you took a close look.
Maybe.
Lemur?
I don't know.
I forget.
Anyway, if you just made the brain bigger,
then the poor animal would be slower and heavier
and would need more food and take longer to reproduce.
The joke about difficulty to give birth.
I don't know if any animal has the problem that humans have.
A lot of people die.
Very good, and so on.
So how did we evolve new ways to think and so forth?
And my first book, The Society of Mind,
had this theory that maybe we evolved
in a series of higher and higher levels or management
structures built on the earlier ones.
And this particular picture suggests
that I got this idea from Sigmund Freud's early theories.
There's been a lot of Freud bashing recently.
You can look on the web.
Forget the authors, but there are a couple of books
saying that he made up all his data,
and there is no evidence that he ever cured anyone
and that he lied about all the data mentioned in his 30
or 40 books and so forth.
Yes, right.
But the funny part is that if you
look at his first major book, 1895,
called The Interpretation of Dreams,
it sort of outlines this theory that most of thinking
is unconscious, and it's processes
you can't get access to, and it has a little bit about sex,
but that's not a major feature.
And it's just full of great ideas
that the cognitive psychologists finally
began to get in the 1960s again and never
give credit to Freud.
So he may well have made up his data,
but if you have a very good theory
and nobody will listen to you, what can you do?
His friend, Rudolf Fliess, listened to him,
and there was another paper on how the neurons might
be involved in thinking, which was also written around 1895,
but never got published till 1950 by,
I forget who, called Project for a Scientific Psychology.
And it's full of ideas that, if they had been published,
might have changed everything.
Because anyway, what's on your mind?
What would you like to hear about?
Who has another theory?
Got a question.
Great.
So earlier, you talked a little bit
about how we don't really see the neuroscience always
things like K-lines, et cetera.
Do you think it's because there's really
hard to find, or no one's actually looking for that?
Well, Restek's review says he uses vague, ill-defined terms
like K-line and micro-name and a couple of others,
and frame and so forth.
They're very well-defined.
I mean, when he talks about neurotransmitters,
it's as though he thinks that chemical
has some real significance.
Any chemical would have the same function
as any other one, provided there's
another receptor that causes something
to happen in the cell membrane.
So you don't want to regard acetylcholine or epinephrine
as having a mental significance.
It's just another pulse, but very low resolution.
And yes, a neurochemical might affect all the neurons
a little bit and raise the average amount of activity
of some big population of cells and reduce the average activity
of some others.
But that's nothing like thinking.
That's like saying, in order to understand
how a car works, what's the most insulting thing I could say?
Or to understand how a computer works,
you have to understand the arsenic and phosphorus.
And or what's the other one?
You have to understand these atoms that are what?
Well, that's the matrix.
So there are these one part in a million impurities.
And that's what's important about a computer, isn't it?
The fact that the transistor has gain and so forth.
Well, no.
The trouble with the computer is the transistors.
That's why practically every transistor in a computer
is mated to another one in opposite phase
to form a flip-flop whose properties are exactly
the same except one in a quadrillion times.
In other words, everything chemical about a computer
is irrelevant.
And I suspect that almost everything
chemical about the brain is unimportant
except that it causes it helps to make
the columns in the cortex, which are complicated arrangements
of several hundred cells, work reliably.
Whereas the neuroscientist is looking
for the secret in the sodium.
When a neuron fires, the important thing
is that that lets the sodium in and the potassium out
or vice versa.
I forget which.
At 500 millivolts, really quite a colossal event.
But it has no significant.
It's only when it's attached to a flip-flop
or to something like a K line, which
has an encoder and decoder of a digital sort,
every few microns in its length, that you
get something functional.
So the trouble is the poor neuroscientist
started out with too much knowledge
about the wrong thing.
The chemistry of the neuron firing
is very interesting and complicated and cute.
And in the case of the electric eel,
you know what happened there.
The neuron synapse, it got rid of the next neuron.
And it just, in the electric eel,
you have a bunch of synapses or motor end plates,
they're called, in series.
So instead of half a volt, if you have 300 of those,
you get 150 volts.
I think the electric shock that an electric eel can give you
is about 300 volts.
And this can cause you to drown promptly
if you are in the wrong wave when
it happens to bump into you.
I don't know why I'm rambling this way.
You're welcome to study neuroscience,
but please try to help them instead of learn from them.
Yeah.
And they just don't know what a K line is.
And that's a paper that's been widely
read, published in 1980, and Restak says ill-defined.
And I guess he couldn't understand it.
Yeah.
Why, instead of trying to make a neuroscientist,
trying to find this in the human mind,
why don't we just, as computer scientists,
program the K lines and try to prove that all this is
the human mind and then we'll produce it?
Why is that not all widespread into the computer scientists
field?
Well, I'm surprised how little has been done.
Mike Travers has a thesis, Tony Hearn.
There are three master's theses on K lines.
They sort of got them to work to solve some simple problems.
But I'd go further.
I've never met a neuroscientist who
knows the pioneering work of Newell and Simon
in the late 1950s.
So there's something wrong with that community.
They're just ignorant.
They're proud of it.
Oh, well.
I spent some time learning neuroscience when I was,
I once had a great stroke of luck when I was a,
I guess I was a junior at Harvard.
And there was a great new biology building
that was just constructed.
It's a great big thing with two rhinoceroses.
What are those two huge animals?
So this building was just finished and half occupied
because it was made with the future.
So I wandered over there and I met a professor named
John Welsh.
And I said, I'd like to learn neurology.
And he said, great.
Well, I have an extra lab.
Why don't you study the crayfish claw?
I said, great.
So he gave me this lab which had four rooms and a dark room
and a lot of equipment and nobody there.
And he had worked on crayfish.
So there was somebody who went every week up
to Walden Ponder somewhere and caught crayfish
and bring them back.
And I was a radio amateur hacker at the time.
So I was good at electronics.
So I got my crayfish and Welsh showed me how to.
Great thing about this preparation
is you can take the crayfish and if you claw
and if you hold it just right, it goes snap.
It comes off, grows another one.
Takes a couple of years.
And then there's this white thing hanging out
which is the nerve.
And it turns out it's six nerves, one big one
and a few little ones.
And if you keep it in Ringer's solution, whatever that is,
it can live for several days.
So I got a lot of switches and little inductors and things
and made a gadget and mounted this thing with six wires going
to these nerves.
And then I programmed it to reach down and pick up
a pencil like that and wave it around.
Well, that's obviously completely trivial.
And all the neuroscientists came around and gasped and said,
that's incredible.
How did you do that?
They had never thought of putting the thing back together
and making it work.
Anyway, it was always reminding myself
that I'm the luckiest person in the world
because every time I wanted to do something,
I just happened to find the right person.
And they'd give me a lab.
I got an idea for a microscope.
And it was this great professor, Purcell,
who got the Nobel Prize after a while.
And he said, that sounds like it would work.
Why don't you take this lab?
It was in the Jefferson.
Anyway, yeah.
I was just saying, part of the reason
that you don't see experimental neuroscience on things
like k-lines is that neurons are long and thin.
So if you want to do an experiment to actually measure
a real neural network, you have to trace structures
with roughly maybe tens of nanometer resolution.
But you need to trace them over what
might be a couple or even tens of millimeters to charge a week.
And you need to do this for thousands and thousands
of neurons before you could get to the point
of seeing something like a k-line and understanding it.
So it's just a massive data acquisition and processing
problem.
But they're doing that.
They're starting to try to.
They don't know what to look for.
Maybe you don't have to do so much.
Maybe you just have to do a few sections here and there
and say, well, look, there were 400 of these here.
Now there's only 200.
It looks like this is the same kind.
Maybe you don't have to do the whole brain.
Even getting a single neuron is because it might get down to,
you need to be looking at electron micrographs of brains
that are sliced at about 30 nanometer slices.
So even just having a single person
reconstruct a single neuron might take weeks.
Well, I don't know.
Maybe a bundle of k-lines is a half a millimeter thick.
Oh, so you actually do some larger scale structure
to start looking at.
Why not?
I just think they have no idea what to look for.
I could give you 20 of those in five minutes,
but nobody's listening.
So I guess you need to know what it looks like before you can
look for it at that scale.
What scale?
I don't know.
I mean, they know what neurons look like.
So you know what to look for if you're
saying the sort of neural net level.
I'm saying you may only have to look at the white matter.
Oh, OK.
Ignore the neurons.
Because the point of k-lines is, where do these go
and what goes into them and out?
I don't know.
It's just this idea of, let's map the whole brain,
100 billion things.
And then people like Resteck said, oh,
and there's 1,000 supporting cells for each neuron.
He's just glorying in the obscurity of it
rather than trying to contribute something.
Anyway, if you run into him, give him my regards.
I really wonder how somebody can write something like that.
Yes?
Excuse my ignorance, but what is a k-line?
The idea is that suppose one part of the brain
is doing something, and it's in some particular state that's
very important, like, I don't know,
I've just seen a glass of water.
Then another part of the brain would
like to know there's a glass of water in the environment.
And I've been looking for one, so I
should try to take over and do something about that.
Now, at the moment, there's no theory
of what happens in different parts of the brain
for a simple thing like that to happen.
No theory at all, except they use the word association,
or they talk about what are the purposeful neurons.
Goal, forget.
OK, so my theory is that there are
a bunch of things which are massive collections of nerve
fibers, maybe a few hundred or a few thousand.
And when the visual system sees an apple,
it turns on 50 of those wires.
And when it sees a pear, it turns on a different 100
or 50 of those wires, but about 20 of them are the same.
In other words, it's like the edge of a punched card.
Have you ever seen a card-based retrieval system?
If you have a book that has, suppose
it's about physics and biology and Sumatra,
and a typical 5 by 8 card has 80 holes in the top edge.
So what you do is, if it's Sumatra,
you punch eight of these holes at random, particular set.
They're assigned to the Sumatra.
And then if it's, I forget what my first two examples were,
but you punch eight or 10 holes for each
of the other two words.
So now there are 24 punches.
Only probably four or five of them are duplicates,
so you're punching about 20 holes.
And now, if something is looking for the cards that
were punched for those three things,
even if there are 30 or 40 other holes punched in the card,
you stick your 20 wires through the whole deck
and lift it up, and only cards fall out
that had those three categories punched for.
So you see, even though you had 80 holes,
you could punch combinations of up
to a million different categories into that.
And if you have to put a bunch of wires through,
you'll get all of the ones that were
punched for the categories you're looking for.
And you might get three or four other cards
that will come down also because all of the eight holes
were punched for some category by accident.
Do you get the picture?
I'll send you a reference.
It was invented in the early 1940s
by a Cambridge scientist here named Calvin Moores
and was widely used in libraries for information retrieval
until computers came along.
But anyway, that's the sort of thing
you could look for in a brain if you had the concept
in your head of Zeta coding.
But I've never met a neuroscientist who ever
heard of such a thing.
So you have this whole community which
doesn't have a set of very clear ideas about different ways
that knowledge or symbols could be represented
in neural activity.
So good luck to them when they get their big map.
They'll still have to say, what do I
do with 100 billion of these interconnections?
Yeah?
What are your thoughts about the current artificial intelligence
research at MIT, such as Winston's Genesis project?
Winston is just about one of the best ones in the whole world.
I don't know any other projects that
are trying to do things on that higher level of common sense
knowledge.
He's just lost a lot of funding, so one problem
is, how do you support a project like that?
Have you followed it?
I don't know if there's a recent summary of what they're doing.
We used to write a new book every year
called The Progress Report.
The nice thing is that we never wrote.
We had a very good form of support
from ARPA or DARPA, which was every year we'd tell them
what we had done.
They didn't want to hear what we wanted to do,
and things have turned the opposite.
So what would happen is every year we'd
say we did these great things, and we might do some more.
Went on for about 20 years, and then it fell apart.
One thing, it's a nice story.
There was a great liberal senator, Mike Mansfield,
and unfortunately, he got the idea
that the Defense Department was getting
too big and influential.
So he got Congress to pass a law that ARPA shouldn't
be allowed to support anything that didn't have
direct military application.
And Congress went for this, and all of a sudden,
a lot of research disappeared, basic research.
It didn't bother us much, because we made up applications
and said, well, this will make a military robot that will go out
and do something bad.
I don't remember ever writing anything at all,
but anyway, around 1980, the funding for that sort of thing
just dried up because of this political accident.
It was just an accident that ARPA,
mainly through the Office of Naval Research,
was funding basic research.
And that was a bit of history.
If you look back at the year 1900 or so,
you see people like Einstein making these nice theories.
But Einstein wasn't a very abstract mathematician,
so he had a mathematician named Hermann Weyl polishing
his tensors and things for him.
And Hermann Weyl's son, Joe, was at the Office of Naval
Research in MITE early time.
And that office had spent a lot of secret money
getting scientists out of Europe while Hitler was marching
around and sending them to places like Princeton
and other forms of heaven.
In Cambridge.
And again, one of the reasons I was lucky
is that I was here and all these.
If you had a mathematical question,
you could find the best mathematician in the world
down the block somewhere.
And Joe Weyl was partly responsible for that.
And the ONR was piping all that money
to us for work on early AI.
It was a very sad thing.
Maybe the most influential liberal in the US government
actually ruined everything by accident.
ARPA changed its name to DARPA.
It was Advanced Research Projects Agency.
And it had to call itself Defense Advanced Research
Projects Agency.
Yeah?
Student.
Do you think the achievement of artificial intelligence
is inevitable or is there an obstacle that we're just never
going to get over?
Well, Christianity wiped out science.
That might happen tomorrow.
Only choose your religion.
It's a hard problem.
The number of people working on advanced ideas in AI
has gotten smaller and smaller.
Right now, around 1980, rule-based systems
became popular.
There were lots of things to do.
Right now, statistical-based inference systems
are becoming popular.
And as I said, these things are tremendously useful.
But the problem is, if you have a statistical system,
the important part is guessing what
are the plausible hypotheses and then finding out
how many instances of that are correlated with such and such.
So that's a nice idea.
But the hard problem is the abstract symbolic problem
of what sets of variables are worth considering at all
when there are a lot of them.
So to me, the most exciting projects
are the kind that Winston is developing for reasoning
about real-life situations and the one that Henry Lieberman.
Would you stand up, Henry?
Lieberman runs a world-class group
that's working on common sense knowledge
and informal reasoning.
And it seems to me that that's the critical thing
that all the other systems will need.
In the meantime, there are people
working on logical inference, which
has the same problem that statistical inference has,
namely, how do you guess which combinations of variables
are worth thinking about?
Then it seems to me that the statistics isn't so important.
In fact, there's a great researcher named Douglas
Lenat in Austin, Texas, who once made an interesting AI system
that was good at making predictions
and guessing explanations for things.
And it was sort of like a probabilistic system.
It had a lot of hypotheses.
And every time one of them was useful in solving a problem,
it moved it up one on the list.
So Lenat's thing never used any numbers.
It didn't say, this is successful 0.73
of the time, and now it's successful 0.736, 4825
of the time.
What it would do is, if something was useful,
it would move it up past another hypothesis.
Every now and then, it would put a new one in.
Well, if you're trying to solve a problem,
what do you need to know?
You want to know what's the most likely to be useful one
and try that.
You don't care how likely it is to be useful,
as long as it's the most, right?
I mean, if it's one in a million,
maybe you should say, I'm getting out of here.
I shouldn't be working in this field at all
or get a better problem.
But Lenat's thing did rather wonderfully at making theories
by just changing the ranking of the hypotheses
that it was considered.
No numbers.
It did something very cute.
He gave it examples of arithmetic,
and it actually was a rather long effort.
And it actually learned to do some arithmetic,
and it invented the idea of division
and the idea of prime number, which
was some number that wasn't divisible by anything.
It decided that 9 was a prime, didn't do much harm,
and it crept along, and it got better and better.
And it invented modular arithmetic
by accident at some point, and it's a PhD thesis.
A lot of people didn't believe this PhD thesis
because Lenat lost the program tape.
So he was under some cloud of suspicion for people thinking
he might have faked it, but who cares?
Anyway, I think there's a lesson there, which is that let's
start with something that works, and then if it's really good,
then hire a mathematician who might
be able to optimize it a little.
But the important thing was the order.
And a good statistical one might waste a lot of time,
because here's this one that's 0.78,
and here's this one that's 0.56, and it's the next one down.
And you get a lot of experience, and it goes up to 5.7 and 5.8,
and it never might be a long time before it
gets past the other one, because you're doing arithmetic.
Whereas in Lenat's, it would just
pop up past the other one, and then it
would get tried right away.
And if it were no good, it would get knocked down again.
Who cares?
So it's a real question of, I don't know.
Mathematics is great, and I love it, and a lot of you do.
But there should be a name for when it's actually slowing you
down and wasting your time, because there's
a better way that's not formal.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Isn't it clear saying, there are people
who know the price of everything and the value of nothing?
Yes.
That's very nice.
Yeah.
I know you're also a musician, so I
have a music-related question.
What do you think is the role of music?
Why do all cultures have it?
I have a paper about it.
Oh, OK.
I've been trying to revise it, actually.
But it's a strange question, because there
is music everywhere.
On the other hand, I have several friends
who are amusical, and so when I have this theory
that music is a way of teaching you
to represent things in their orderly fashion
and stuff like that, well, I have three of my colleagues
who aren't musical, but they dance.
So it may be that I don't know the answer.
It's interesting.
The first theory in my paper is that when
you have a lot of complicated things happening,
then the only way to learn is to represent things that happen
and then look at the differences between things
that are similar and then try to explain the differences.
Right?
I mean, what else is there?
Maybe there's something else.
So in order to become intelligent and understand
things, you have to be able to compare things.
And to me, the most important feature
of what's called music is that it's divided into measures.
Ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba.
And measures are the same number of beats or whatever they are.
And so now you can say, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da,
da, da, da.
What's the difference?
You change the eighth notes in the second one.
The last four eighth notes, no.
The two before last to a quarter note.
So you're taking things that were in different times
and you're superimposing those times,
and now you can see the difference.
And the reason you can see the difference
is that you have things called measures.
And the measures have things called beats.
And so things get knocked into very good frames.
Now, there's some Indian music which
has 14 measures for a phrase.
And some of the measures go seven and five.
And I can make no sense of that stuff whatever.
And I've tried fairly hard, but not very.
So I don't understand how Indians can think.
Any of you can handle Indian music?
I guess just to add on what you said about this,
my favorite quote from your paper on music, mind,
and meaning is the one about what
good is music about how kids play with blocks
to learn about space and people play with music
to learn about time.
And I think in that sense, both music and dance
are different ways that people can arrange things in time.
And in a sense, like improvisatory music
and improvisatory movement are both ways of different blocks,
if you will, in time as opposed to space.
Yeah, my friends who see me musically,
maybe there's something different about their cochlea.
Or maybe they have absolute pitch in some sense,
which is a bad thing to have.
Because if you're listening to a piece composed by a composer
who doesn't have absolute pitch, then you're
reading all sorts of things into the music
that shouldn't be there.
And the opposite would be true.
I read music criticism sometimes.
And maybe the reviewer says, and after the second and third
movement, he finally returns to the initial key
of E flat major.
What a relief.
Well, I once had absolute pitch for a couple of weeks
because I ran a tuning fork in my room for a month.
And I didn't like it because you can't listen to Bach anymore.
Oh, well.
It's a good question.
Why do people like music?
And I don't know any other paper like mine.
If you ever find one, I'd like to see it.
Because if you go to a big library,
there are thousands of books about music.
And if you open one, it's mostly Berlioz complaining
that somebody wouldn't give him enough money
to hire a big enough chorus.
I've found very few books about music itself.
Yes?
I don't know about music anymore.
Is that all right?
Do you think that having a body is a necessary component
of having a mind?
I mean, can you do just as well, just as a sort
of a simulated creature that can have all the things?
Simulation.
I think a mind that's not in a world
wouldn't have much to do.
It would have to invent the world.
And I don't see why it couldn't, but you
might have to give it a start, like the idea of three
or four dimensions.
What happens if you sit back and just think for a while?
You wouldn't know if your body had
disappeared, would you?
There are all sorts of strange ideas about existence and why
do you think there's a world?
One of the things that bugs me is people say,
well, who created it?
And that can't make any sense, because this
is just a possible world.
Suppose there are a whole lot of possible worlds
and there's one real one.
How could you possibly know which one you're in?
And then you could say, well, didn't someone have to make it?
And what's the next thing you'd ask?
Well, who made the maker?
So the body-mind thing seems to me that once you have
a computer, it can be its own world.
It just can sit.
The program can spend half the time simulating a world
and half the time thinking about what it's like to be in it.
Yeah?
Yes, it's an empty concept.
It's all right to say this bottle exists,
because let's say this bottle is in this universe.
But what would it mean to say the universe exists?
The universe is in the universe?
Oh.
So there's something wrong with thinking about,
so there are only possible worlds.
It doesn't make any sense to pick one of them out
and say, that's the real one.
Yeah?
But existence is relative.
Yeah, you don't say, this is the world I'm in.
But you shouldn't say, that doesn't mean it exists.
Like, two is in the set of even numbers.
What's the set of even numbers in?
It doesn't stop anywhere.
Yeah?
Lots of worlds.
So in mathematics, the world is the whole world,
but physics, it only explains the current world,
or either how you combine these two sets of worlds?
Well, you can't tell, because five minutes from now,
everything might change.
So nothing ever explains anything.
You just have to take what you've got
and make the best of it.
eriments
that support this body is that we
from experiments that support this theory
might be how when people have limbs amputated,
it takes them a while to forget that they have the limb,
because their mental models still exist.
Their mental models still go away overnight.
And also, I guess, they train monkeys
to control robot arms with their brains.
Sure.
Well, but it just seems to me that a large amount of our brain
is involved with highly evolved locomotion mechanisms.
And as I said, when you're sitting back
with your eyes closed in a chair thinking about something,
then it's not clear how much of that machinery is important.
But it might be that I have a strange paper on,
I don't know if it's, I'm trying to remember its name.
It's called, do you think I can actually
get a, I can't remember the name of the title.
Oh, I give up.
The idea is that maybe in the older theories of psychology,
everything is learned by experience in the real world.
So conditioning and reinforcement and so forth.
In this theory I call internal grounding, I make a conjecture.
Suppose the brain has a little piece of nerve tissue, which
consists of a few neurons arranged to make not a flip
flop, but a, what would you call a three or a four flop?
A flip flop with three or four states.
Let's say three.
So when you put a certain input, it goes from,
I couldn't find the chalk.
So here are three states.
And here's a certain input that means
if you're in that state, you go to this.
And if you pop that input again, it does this.
And if you say, go counterclockwise, it goes.
So three of them get you back where you were.
But if I go this, this, and that,
that would mean to go like this, this, and back.
So this would be, that means that's
equivalent to just going one.
Get the idea?
In other words, imagine that there's
a little world inside your brain which is very small
and only has three states.
And you have actions that you can perform on it.
And you have an integer i which can
see which of the three points of that triangle you're on.
Then you could learn by experience
that if you go left, left, left, you're back where you were.
But if you go left, right, left, right,
you're back where you are.
And if you go left, left, right, that's like going one left.
In other words, you could imagine a brain that starts out
before it connects itself to the real world.
It starts by having the top level of the brain connected
to a little internal world which just has three or four states.
And you get very good at manipulating that.
Then you add more sensory systems to the outer world.
And you get to learn ways to get around in the real world.
So I called that the internal grounding hypothesis.
And my suggestion is maybe somewhere in the human brain
there's a little structure that's
somewhat like that which is used by the frontal part
of the cortex to make very abstract ideas.
You understand, the more abstract an idea is,
the simpler and more stupid and elementary it is.
Abstract doesn't mean hard.
Abstract means stupid.
Real things like this are infinitely complicated.
So we might have, and I wouldn't dare suggest this
to a neuroscientist, there might be some little brain
center somewhere near the frontal cortex that
allows the frontal cortex to do some predicting and planning
and induction about a few simple finite state arrangements.
Who knows?
Would you look for it?
Well, if you were a neuroscientist,
you could say, oh, that's completely different
from anything I ever heard.
Let's look for it.
And if you're wrong, you're wasted a year.
And if you're right, then you become the new Ramon E. Cajal
or someone.
Who's the currently best neuroscientist?
Maybe it's late.
One more question.
One last question.
This is Cynthia Solomon, who's one
of the great developers of the logo language.
Yay.
Yes.
Maybe it's that question for me.
One last question.
What do you think about theories such as Rodney Brooks' theories
that speak of no central nervous system?
Completely weird.
Obviously, those theories have nothing
to do with human thinking, but they're
very good for making stupid robots.
And the vacuum cleaner is one of the great achievements
of the century.
However, his projects, what was it called,
cog, disappeared without a trace.
That theory was so wrong that it got a national award.
And it corrupted AI research in Japan for several years.
I can't understand.
Brooks became popular because he said,
maybe the important things about thinking
is that there's no internal representation.
You're just reacting to situations.
And you have a big library of how to react to each situation.
Well, David Hume had that idea, and he
was a popular philosopher for hundreds of years.
But it went nowhere, and it's gone, and so is Rod.
However, he is one of the great robot designers,
and he may be the instrumental in fixing
the great Japanese nuclear meltdown
because they're shipping some of his robots out there.
The problem is, can it open the door?
So far, no robot can open the door
even though it's not locked.
Thank you.