The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
I just read chapter 5 for the first time in several years.
I was impressed with all the good quotes.
But I was wondering if anything I said
was up to anything those people said.
We don't see things as they are.
We see things as we are.
What else did Anais Nin write?
I don't know who she is, actually.
Anyone know this writer?
What else does she do?
Is it good?
Yes.
I don't know where it is.
Essentially explicit.
And the second half of the chapter
is about this wonderful project that really
ran for several years in which we tried to build robots that
could see and manipulate things.
And all sorts of wonderful things appeared in that year.
For example, the goal of the robot project
was a very simple one.
We decided that the robot would live
in a world of mostly rectangular blocks.
And a very simple job that a two-year-old cannot do,
but a four- or five-year-old has no trouble with
would be taking some particular structure.
I should have brought some blocks.
These are blocks, but they're not going to work.
Two of these are flat on the top, so.
I doubt if our robot could have built that.
I didn't know about rolling.
But the idea is you would build something out of these blocks,
little house or a more complicated structure.
And our one-armed robot would try to duplicate it.
And in order to do that, it had to be able to look at the scene
and figure out what the scene was made of
and what were the relation of the blocks
and which blocks they were.
And it had a big pile of them.
So it had to make a plan for what
it was going to do in the very first minute of the project.
We had obtained this robot and gotten the computer
to control it.
And Jerry Sussman wrote a program
and immediately to build and copy an arch.
And immediately, it started with this block first
and put it here.
And in fact, Sussman's PhD thesis
was a profound piece of work discussing
various classes of bugs, beginning
with these kind of simple ones where you
do things in the wrong order.
And as far as I know, there's no PhD thesis quite like it.
Do you know anything, Henry?
I mean, a lot of theses are about bugs in things
and fixing them.
But if you're looking for something to write about,
you can go all the way back to 1970
and look at a couple of those theses.
And generally, they were very ambitious.
There's a whole group of them I'll discuss at some point.
So you shouldn't, if you're trying to copy a structure,
you have to analyze what is supporting what.
And there's no point in trying to place something
until its supports are in place.
But how do you look at the scene and see things?
And at one point in the project, there was a remarkable thing.
And I think it was Manuel Bloom who did this particular one.
But he discovered that if you looked
at the outline of a big mess of blocks,
there was a good chance that by following
a wonderful set of rules that he made,
you could figure out what was going on.
This is a great feature of working in a restricted world
where the computer can know all of the objects in that world
that could exist.
And so you can see the process.
But he wrote this program that just looks at this outline.
Where did I put the death ray?
I just, here it is, couldn't see it because it
was supported by a napkin.
So it just looks at that and says, well, none of the blocks
have an interior angle.
So this can't be true, and those can't be true.
So what do I do about that?
And you see, I could extend that line either up
or this line out.
Maybe it does both.
I've forgotten.
But it does this, and it extends this one.
And presumably, it tries four or eight different combinations
until he finds two that make a little more sense.
So then it draws in these.
And once it's drawn in those two,
see, then it can conjecture that maybe this is a block.
And if so, you see, then it has to put in those two edges.
And that works out fine.
And then here's the six-sided thing,
and there are no hexagons in the blocks world.
So it says, this cannot be, and what could it be?
And the answer is, it could be that, and so forth.
So we were quite astounded that you could do that well.
But of course, it's always a surprise.
Maybe this is why mathematics works.
If you look at something like group theory,
here you have a little system which has five logical axioms.
And I guess Galois is the first person
to study systems that had those five simple axioms.
And every day to this day, mathematicians
around the world discover 10 or 100 new things
about the consequences of what happens in that tiny world
where there are objects.
There's an identity object.
You multiply things.
They may or may not commute.
That's two different kinds of groups.
But they all obey the associative law.
So this is sort of an example of a little
where a mathematician has invented a little system that
describes almost everything that can
happen in this tiny world.
Well, of course, the world of common sense is much larger.
And people like Henry Lieberman and several others
around the world are trying to, I don't know,
formalize is the right word.
Because if you're trying to find a million axioms
for a particular universe, then that's not that.
You can't hope that that will end up like mathematics.
Marvin, how about the word informalized?
Informalized, right.
Of course, we all hope that someday all of the not many
groups that are working on collecting and characterizing
common sense knowledge will be able to more or less get them
to all work together and start to have something that
has the abilities of a four or five-year-old.
If you can get there, then you can get it to have all the,
you can get a machine that will learn enough,
then it will keep getting smarter.
And there's no reason to think it will flatten out
the way people do.
We don't know if people would flatten out.
No one knows what would happen if somebody
kept thinking for 500 years.
You see all of these expensive government projects,
but you wonder why there isn't one to.
Well, I don't know what to say about this chapter,
because it has so many strange and interesting things in it.
So it ends with a very cryptic discussion of how do you make
a machine that will watch things happen for a long time
and then start to predict what will come after that.
And then start to predict what will come after that.
And the answer is you have to develop stories and scripts
and beautiful ways to summarize your experience
and then find ways to fit them together.
If you're writing a story, then you're
not doing that sort of thing, but you're
making a little world, and you're
inventing events in the past and future of each character
and trying to get something that looks more or less
lifelike to people.
Anyway, there's so many things in this
that I don't see any point in trying to summarize them all,
except to hope you have some questions and things
to discuss.
Yes?
So I'm with the land.
How well do we actually need to understand intelligence
in order to create a replica of it
as an artificial intelligence that
can fool, say, 99% of the world?
So as an analogy, let's say you have an art forger.
To truly create something that will fool 100% of the world,
they would have to know the exact brush strokes
and what paints and oils that the person used,
the original artist.
But if you just want to fool 99%,
you don't need to know that much.
So how much do we need to know about intelligence
to actually create something that people
will see as intelligent?
I'm not sure what you mean by fool,
because if you have a program that solves hard problems, what
would it mean to say, it's just executing instructions,
it's not really thinking?
So I guess as a better definition of fool,
so something like the Turing test, where you say,
oh, there's a person.
So how much we would have to know about intelligence
to say, if we could just put them in another room,
give them some sort of telephone,
if we could just run the Turing test
and fool 99% of the people that are testing?
A test for intelligence.
It's a test for when will people think it's intelligent.
I mean, I'm not sure.
Suppose that you didn't know that there
were foreign languages, and you came across a Norwegian,
and you couldn't understand anything it said.
You would say, what is the use of this ridiculous machine that
just makes stupid sounds?
So I think people have always wanted to measure things.
And the IQ test, Binet and Simon, that wasn't heard Simon.
I'm trying to remember which Simon that was.
That became a useful tool for seeing,
measuring things that children could do,
and deciding whether there seemed
to be something wrong with the child's development,
or whether it's getting too smart for it.
I don't know if anybody got concerned when
somebody got high IQs, but.
Well, if I could ask a different question,
how much do we need to know about intelligence
in order to create something that can create something
smarter than itself?
Well, everyone creates something smarter than oneself
in their childhood.
So that doesn't seem very, I'm not sure how hard that is.
I wonder what is the right question to ask?
How do you judge the progress of artificial intelligence?
That might be a good question.
As I see it, it took a dive in recent years,
but not, I think I've complained about it too much.
But what happened is that when we
started this kind of work, it was a sort of golden age
for science because, I've said it before,
because at the end of World War II,
there was a lot of machinery around.
Maybe it's almost a joke, but there
were a million kids who could get their hands on war
surplus electronics.
Now, of course, everybody can get their hand
on a little computer or something, or a cell phone,
or whatever.
But what's difficult is getting a job to work on.
Suppose you wanted to work for five years
on some aspect of artificial intelligence.
The machines aren't smart enough, you think.
They don't have enough common sense knowledge,
or they don't use it right, or whatever.
And you'd like to really work on that problem.
And there are lots of reasons.
I think I showed you a set of slides that
showed a lot of reasons to work on what are the problems
that civilization is facing.
This morning, I turned on WBUR, and some people
were complaining for a whole hour
that there's no way the United States can support older
people who have infirmities, either mental or physical,
because there's not enough money to hire the nurses.
There are not enough nurses to take care of them.
My bet is that instead of spending a trillion dollars
on Medicare, which is one option,
but then almost everybody will be
working to support the infirmities
of these older people.
It will be a very strange civilization
if you spend all of the resources you need.
So why not say what we need is AI to help these people?
And if the AI is smarter than a regular person,
then it's not even demeaning.
So I'd like to see a very small budget, like a billion dollars,
that has the goal of making intelligent machines in 20
years, which means that you could hire 100,000
smart young people to spend 10 or 20 years working
on this sort of thing.
It'd be terribly cheap.
Nobody's in charge, though.
And you can't buy long-term care insurance, in a sense,
because there'll be nobody to provide it.
I'm rambling, but you see that potentially it's
a very important field.
But it's not in the politician's spectrum
of things you could do to have a better future for less money.
I doubt if there's a single congressman who even knows
that this is a plausible gamble.
Anybody know a politician who understands an issue like that?
Now, is there a question I can answer?
I feel I should get Winston to say something.
Have you discussed this with students?
How many students do you have who
would like to be a professor?
And what are they doing?
Pat was one of a few students who wanted to be a professor.
We're talking the late 1960s, and it turned out
to be possible, but it's very hard now.
Well, I decided I'd leave as soon as I found work.
I told you, when Sussman was a freshman, he said,
I like this.
I'm going to stay forever.
Did you ever find work?
I had this bizarre experience when
I was a senior because I thought I might have to find work.
And I ran into somebody called Edmund C. Berkeley
who had written a book about robots.
He had edited a popular electronics magazine.
And so I went to see him.
He was actually working at the Prudential Life.
Did I tell this story?
Because he had written this book on brainiacs or something.
Geniac.
It was a little machine with three wheels of cardboard
and some wires.
And you could put in little contacts and switches
and get it to compute Boolean functions.
So it really was a, this is a 1948 computer.
Didn't do much, but it did it.
It had a little book to go with it.
So I went to visit him.
And he said, well, I don't really
know anything more about this than I described in that toy.
But I have a young friend named Martin Gardner
who has built some other kind of logic machine.
And he lives in Brooklyn.
So I went to see this Martin Gardner.
And I'm sure you all know who he was.
But he had just finished a thesis or a paper
called Order and Surprise.
And for me, it was the best thing
I had ever read since Bertrand Russell or Aristotle.
Namely, he said, suppose that an alien came down and looked
at the world, and he discovered this huge green thing
with a billion grains of grass.
They're all pointed almost the same way.
And they're all about the same height.
And this alien said, what's the probability
that such a thing could happen?
Could it be an accident?
Well, no.
Then the probability of one blade of grass
would be 0.000 something.
And the probability of two of them would be that squared.
And the probability of a billion of them
would be 2 to the 2 to the 1,000 billioners.
I can't calculate anything like that.
Anyway, Gardner convinced me, I think,
that I should just keep doing what I was doing, namely,
figure out how to build learning machines
and see if I could make them get smarter and smarter.
But it's a great digression.
The same thing happened to me at least a dozen times of just
somehow running into the right people at the right time.
And I hope that happens to you.
I don't know how you.
What's the trick, Ed?
You have to recognize them somehow.
Fredkin is an old friend of mine from the 1970s.
1950s.
50s, whatever it was.
And he was always in the right place at the right time.
In fact, he was director of Project MAC for a while
of what became the Laboratory of Computer Science.
Only he did such a good job that some of the faculty
was jealous.
End of story.
It's a bad story.
So you have to look for them.
If you like somebody's work, just go and see them.
However, don't ask for their autograph.
A lot of people come and ask me for my autograph.
And it's creepy.
What I did was read everything they'd published first
and correct them.
That's what they really want.
Every smart person wants to be corrected, not admired.
Back to reality.
So I don't know whether one.
It seems to me you don't want a Turing test.
We all know that if we could make
a machine that behaved a lot like a four-year-old,
then we could make it better.
And it would start behaving like a five-year-old.
And eventually, it would be smarter than us.
And this Turing test thing is a joke.
And Turing regarded it as a joke.
If you read his paper carefully, he's saying,
I'm not deciding whether a machine is intelligent.
I'm only deciding what performance
would be such that a person would be really impressed,
whether it deserved to be applauded or not.
And now in the case of IQ test, you
could say the same thing, except that generally people
who are good at 10 different things
are much better at 10 different things
than most other people are good candidates
for solving a new problem they haven't seen before.
So it's not useless.
What's annoying is when people think
that Turing was saying this is a test for whether a machine's
an intelligent.
Yes?
So I want to argue that representation
is really important for intelligence.
So for example, if you have a SAT sentence.
If you have what?
A SAT sentence, like x, y, y, y, y, y, y, y, y, y.
X1, or x2, and x3, or x4.
A question with several answers proposed.
You want to know if that's satisfiable or not.
It's important to know, for example,
if that sentence is important or not, if it's solvable or not,
if there is a solution that transforms that sentence
true or false.
But you can just say that, oh, there
is a solution that this is true, this sentence is true.
And I'm just transforming from one representation
to another.
So at the beginning, I have a representation,
which is a sentence.
At the end, like this sentence, x1, or x2, and x3, or x4.
And at the end, I have just, oh, this is satisfiable or not.
But they are just representations
of the same thing.
And for example, there are some theories about,
for example, Shannon.
He just states what's the optimal representation
according to the length of the word.
But maybe that's not the most important thing.
Maybe there is some trade-off about how big is the sentence
and how easy I can get to another representation
of that sentence or that thing.
It seems that we humans are very good at representing stuff
and switching between representations.
But we don't have a very good sense
of what's a good representation in that sense,
that I can change between solutions
or I can change between representations
of the same thing.
And maybe an intelligent machine is
a machine that can represent things in a good way
and can switch very well.
Well, you're asking, I think he's
asking a deep question, which is, how many of you
know Shannon's theory of information?
Almost everyone.
That is, if you have a set of things,
how many binary choices does it work?
Questions would you have to answer
to find a particular one?
That's log n.
But if you don't know the probability,
if they have different probabilities,
then you need a more complicated formula,
which is the sum of the inverse log probabilities,
blah, blah, blah.
And that's a beautiful theory.
Now, that works perfectly for well-defined situations,
for example, where you have some enormous set of messages
that you can describe with set theory in a neat way
with probabilities.
And you want to know how long it will
take to transmit information about to pick
one of that large set on a particular physical channel.
And Shannon discovered this wonderful formula,
which turned out to be the same as the formula
for entropy in physics.
And I have a long story or a short story
about that, which is that thousands of papers
were published about this new theory of Shannon's, which
came out in 1950, I think, and maybe 48.
And then suddenly, they stopped, because in some sense,
all of the important questions about that theory
had been answered by the middle 1970s.
So that's less than 25 years.
Anyway, a lot of people said, but this theory only
works for very well-defined mathematical situations
where there are signals and probabilities and symbols
and so forth.
Is there anything that could, is there
a similar theory that could describe machines?
Suppose you take an automobile, and it's
got a lot of gears and pistons and spark plugs
and electric gadgets.
And it's not enough to describe that as a list of parts.
You have to say something about what each part does,
can the shapes of parts and how they fit together and so forth.
And so shortly after Shannon's theory became popular,
lots of people said, well, is there
a similar theory for structural information?
Is there a theory like that for geometric forms
and for mechanical things and for chemical reactions
and so forth?
And no one ever found, in other words,
is there a theory of what you might call semantic information
rather than just statistical information.
And as far as I know, there isn't any.
There still might be, but it's the only case
I know where a whole scientific field appeared and then
stopped.
Look at everything else, and it keeps going.
And in fact, we had a journal of information theory,
and the editorial board was mostly MIT professors.
And this journal was published for about 10 years.
And then one day, we were picking
the papers for the next issue, and everyone rejected
all of their papers on this committee.
And the journal, we declared the journal finished.
I don't know what journals have closed lately.
There must be some, but they don't get much attention.
Will the Wall Street Journal close?
Are all the important questions about Wall Street answered?
There are a lot of people camped out on their sidewalk.
I don't know if what's bothering you.
Martin, can you say a little bit more
about what you mean by semantic information theory?
Because that's bothering me at the moment.
I don't know what I mean.
I guess the point is that if you look
at the objects in Shannon's theory,
they're just little points in some abstract space,
and they each have a probability.
And that's all there is to them.
And if you say there's a million gadgets in your catalog,
and each one has a certain probability,
and you don't know anything else about them,
then suppose you want to make a big sequence of them
and transmit to someone else how to reconstruct that sequence.
Well, if you just took the first one and the second one
and wrote a sequence which goes AB, AB, AB a million times,
then you could compress that by somehow communicating
a description of what you mean by repeating a sequence
and then say, now repeat the sequence AB a million times.
And you can presumably describe a million in some ways also.
Once you've sent those descriptions,
then the further such messages of that kind
would be very short.
But now if you go and take random samples
of these million things, then if they're all equal probability,
then it's going to take 20 bits to tell about each symbol.
And there's nothing you can do to reduce that bandwidth.
So semantic information would be somehow
transmitting other commonsensical
or informal information about the objects
you're talking about rather than just their probabilities
of the individual items.
Whatever it is, nobody ever found.
Everybody said we want semantic information theory,
and no one could say what they meant by it.
If you had a good definition, maybe one of us can do it.
Let me try.
Isn't that the kind of thing that we
do in a lot of knowledge representation
is if you make an ontology in advance
and we have a common ontology, then I just
need to index those concepts of the ontology
or if you have concept energy of open mind,
we have a default body of common sense knowledge
or some default body of semantics,
then yes, you can communicate a lot of semantics
in very short messages.
Well, for example, generally, the most useful words
in the language are the short ones.
But I don't see how you could get such a neat theory
as Shannon's, but it's like group theory or something
where arithmetic is much harder than group theory
because in arithmetic, you have a situation
where there's two different groups on the integers
where you're multiplying things and you're adding things.
And number theory is immensely complicated,
and group theory is, well, it can get complicated,
but generally, it's a very clear field where
I don't know what to say.
But very likely, out of the attempts
to build common sense systems will come some beautiful
theories at some point.
You might almost have them now.
I was trying to read some of the people from your group,
and the papers are pretty hard to read.
So they look very good, but I wish
I could get them down to one page and understand it.
Tuition for tensors.
Tensors, things with a lot of subscripts.
So who has, what do you think the AI people should do next?
I think I'm going to harp on the Turing test still.
If we were able to demonstrate, if a machine were
able to demonstrate the kind of common sense
reasoning that a four-year-old does by building that arch,
is that analogous to the imitation game
that Turing was trying to propose?
Because in the paper, he does say,
with improved performance, memory, and program
that the machine will have.
So if it were able to imitate the behavior,
is it a reflection of what was involved in getting
to that point to imitate?
I mean, deception is one part.
I think there are a lot of objections he addresses.
So in our example, if a machine actually
demonstrated the common sense of a four-year-old,
wouldn't that be an analog?
We once had a Turing test situation
where, in the early days, we had teletypes attached
to a big computer into Technology Square.
And this is all connected on one of the first beautiful time
sharing systems.
And one of the engineers who worked on the time sharing
system was a young professor named Herb Teager.
And I fooled him for a minute into thinking
that I had an AI program, but I was actually in another room.
And he would type questions, and I would answer them
in a very stilted, computer-like fashion.
And then he said, how much is this times that?
And he had two 15-digit numbers, which he must have just
typed like this.
So I very cleverly replied, accumulator overflow,
but I misspelled accumulator.
So I failed the Turing test.
Do you remember Teager?
Ed Fredkin here is one of the three or four inventors
of large-scale time-sharing computers.
Any good stories about that?
There are lots of good stories from long ago,
but I don't know if people would be interested.
Plus one.
I'll just say one thing.
Long ago, when I met Marvin and John McCarthy, who
was also a professor at MIT at the time,
was very mysterious to me.
John McCarthy was a professor of electrical engineering,
and Marvin was in the math department,
if I remember right.
And I had this idea of maybe the universe
is a computer in some sense, and physics would then
be some kind of discrete spacetime state process.
And I broached that idea to both John McCarthy and Marvin.
And Marvin told me that I should look
at what von Neumann did in cellular automata, which
was great advice, because I'd never heard of cellular
automata.
But John McCarthy's response was interesting.
I said to him, do you think I ought
to continue working on this?
And he thought about that for a second.
Then he said, yes, the world is large enough.
It can afford to have one person working on such ideas.
Yes.
There was one time when we'd, I keep telling these stories,
and I don't know if I've told you it, but when it came,
it was clear that we wanted to build a time shared
big computer.
And we went to IBM, asked them if they
would support a project to make a time shared computer.
And the head of research asked us to explain what it would do.
And the answer was, we'd have a big computer like a 701,
and we'd have 20 teletypes, and different people
would be typing on them, running their programs.
And each time somebody typed a character,
the big computer would switch to their program
and run a few steps of their program in response to that.
And the head of research at IBM said, that's a terrible idea.
You say there's 30 people, and they're typing it
five or 10 characters a second.
That means you're interrupting the computer
300 times a second.
How could it ever get any work done?
And we got the machine from Honeywell, wasn't it,
rather than IBM?
Or was it GE or Honeywell?
I forget.
I think it was GE first, and then somehow they
sold it to Honeywell.
Sometime later, IBM had some pretty good researchers working
on artificial intelligence.
And Thomas Watson, who was the president of the company,
heard about that, and he sent out an order saying,
nobody should use any expression like that,
because he didn't want the public thinking
that IBM was going to make intelligent machines,
because the customers would get very upset.
They continued research for a while,
but they never used the expression AI again.
I don't know if they use it now.
Is Watson AI?
I don't think they do.
I think they just call it deep question answering.
Deep question answering.
Well, the guy who created it was very definite in response
to that question, and he said, this
is a system to play Jeopardy and nothing else.
But later on, IBM's PR people have been
touting how smart it was and so on.
Yes, I don't know if it can do any common sense reasoning,
but yeah.
So I went to a few talks by Ferrucci, the guy who
did the Watson thing.
And also, I commented the matches online.
So I have a career as a sports commentator
for this new thing of AI sports.
A lot of people ask me, did it have common sense reasoning
or did it have AI in it?
And I think the answer is that it did,
but some, it wasn't the only thing it did.
It was kind of a raisin in Patrick Winston's phrase.
So one of the people working on the Jeopardy team
was Eric Mueller, who wrote a textbook on common sense
reasoning, among other things.
And so I can't believe that there wasn't some influence
from him in there.
I think the most important thing I think about the architecture
of Watson was that it was a society of models.
So there's a very nice article in AI magazine
that explains how it was put together.
It was using some statistical models.
It was using some models that were very stupid,
that I was very good at.
that I wouldn't endorse as a way of doing AI.
But the idea is that it had a kind of meta architecture
that was constantly evaluating them
and trying to figure out which ones of them.
So it had which ones of the methods
work best on which kinds of problems.
So it's using a lot of different methods
and deciding when to page them in and out.
Yeah, and it had a kind of evaluator.
I think one of the things that Eric worked on
was if there was a problem involving numbers,
then he got that problem.
So he probably had some kind of common sense module
about numbers, are the numbers little or big,
or is this a quantitative problem that I could figure out
by looking up a formula, or there were probably
a few heuristics of that type in it.
So I would say it had some AI in it,
probably had some common sense knowledge,
but that probably wasn't the bulk of it.
The most interesting thing about it
was the fact that it had this architecture
that was constantly trying to figure out
which one of the many methods that it was trying to use.
When the thing came out, I got a message
from the lab director, Frank Moss,
saying, well, wouldn't it be great
if they had used your common sense software on Watson?
And I said, and in fact, they had asked us
to work with them and I turned them down.
And I said to him, so he said,
wouldn't it be great if they had used your software?
And I said, well, did you hear about the CMU guys
who did work with them?
And he said, no.
And I said, well, there you go.
That's pretty good.
Yes, they don't mention that it's a society of mind idea.
No, who would you talk about that?
It was one of the articles as well.
Really?
Yeah, he does mention it.
But not the details of this.
Well, it'd be interesting.
They fired their other group, AI group, the one that
Doug Rican.
Just to add to that, I think the class forum,
I added the AI magazine that Henry spoke about
and checked with Eric.
And a couple of papers are out on the subject.
I think there's a link to all the papers that are out.
I think one other thing they did was
I think they do some question analysis where
they decompose the question.
And that's fed into some hypothesis generation
about what possible answers you can get.
They feed that answer back into the question
and they create a hypothesis of what to search.
So I'd asked one of the people working on it
if they used common sense.
And I think his answer was not yet.
But they do mind the Wikipedia for some kind of data.
That's the closest.
So like Henry said, maybe they use it in a limited context.
But a lot of six, seven papers in the forum.
As I asked Google a bunch of questions the other day,
and it really got the right articles among the first 10
for many of them.
I didn't keep a log.
It's getting good at parsing what you said.
I was just wondering if you were logged into your Gmail account
at the time, because I know that Google's starting
to personalize searches.
So you'll see search results based on your previous searches
as well.
So it might seem a bit more intelligent for that reason
Is that the Google Plus or the regular Google?
I think it's the regular Google as long as you're
signed into your account, your Gmail account.
I haven't noticed anything.
I've definitely noticed that it knows
what I'm looking for because of that.
You could try signing out, and you can see the results
are often less relevant.
It certainly says you retrieved this item five times before.
So it's keeping.
I don't know if that record is in Google or in my machine.
How does the Dragon thing work, the dictation?
I'm pretty sure all the databases that it uses
are on your machine.
They come with the Dragon software.
It's not a cloud service, but I'm not 100% sure.
That may have changed since I last used Dragon.
Janet Baker is giving a lecture.
What day is it?
Friday.
It would probably be interesting because she'll explain not only
how it works, but how to make a company, produce it.
So this is a question about Watson.
When it pages all these different methods,
is it trying every single one of them at the same time?
Or I'm just trying to clarify that bit.
It has a lot of processors, but I
don't know what it's doing, do you?
I don't know to the level of whether it's
trying all these simultaneously.
I know that in the offline experiments,
they compile cases of, so they play games against humans.
They look at records of past games.
And to some extent, the trading isn't completely automatic.
But to some extent, they learn what kinds of techniques
work best with what kinds of questions.
And so probably they have some upfront classification.
I'm sure they don't run every method at every time,
because some of these methods are probably pretty consuming.
So they probably do some classification
of what the kind of, I mean, I think the most impressive thing
is just it tries to figure out what kind of question
is being asked.
And it did a pretty impressive job about that.
So I don't really know the details of it.
Is their publication complete enough
that you can actually see how it works?
You can get the general.
They have an article in AI Magazine.
Sherad said there might be others.
I've just read that one article so far.
They've drawn out the architecture,
even in the article that you mentioned.
They actually have a picture of the flow of what's happening,
how the question comes in, how it's broken down.
The publications, they start giving you
an idea of the algorithms that they use,
but not the full picture.
Certainly would be nice if one could see the whole thing
and even experiment with it.
This question is about which comes first, the machinery
or the common sense?
And once we built it, we can, for the sake
of reasoning and intelligence, we
could feed it this database of common sense
and the rules that come with it.
But was part of the machinery built
because there was common sense?
This is going back thousands of years and millions of years
whenever.
In that context, whatever we would call common sense,
for the Neanderthal period, for example,
was the machinery in their brain probably
built because of that?
Or did that happen first as a software
started working on building common sense?
We don't have much record of what
happened in that five million years
since we were gorillas or chimpanzees or whatever.
Have you heard of finger monkeys?
I don't know if I can find it.
But they're about as big.
They're little lemurs about as big as your thumb.
And they smile.
Are you sure this is a real thing?
I wondered.
We'll put it on some web page.
So we come from those primates.
And we don't know anything about their mental development.
And since the humans split off from the pretty much
about the same time that the chimpanzees and orangutans
diverged, it's about five million years ago.
So there's a few paintings and caves.
But I believe those are all tens of thousands of years.
Are there any human habitats over a million years ago?
What?
What's the oldest ones?
The oldest artifacts?
Yeah.
75,000 years.
That's not much.
Drilled seashells presumably with these jewelry.
Well, you could use it for scraping things, probably
rather useful gadgets.
I think the initial wisdom is we've only
been anatomically modern for about 200,000 years.
Yes, I'm curious as to when dogs appeared,
because as soon as you've got dogs,
then you could normally, to survive in the jungle,
you have to have your nose near the ground,
because that's the way to detect bad things.
But once we had dogs, then people
could have the dogs look for the dangers,
and then the people could stand up.
So I'd like to know when the dogs got domesticated.
Or maybe there was some other animal that wasn't dogs that
served this function.
Or maybe it was older people who were ordered to crawl around.
Presumably, older people were 30 or 40 years old.
I think one remarkable thing is that humans live almost twice
as long as any other primate.
So it could be that for most animals, not all,
but for most animals, only the parent generation is around.
But it could be that humans had a great advantage
in having grandparents who were still around frequently, which
means that the middle generation could do other things
than take care of the children.
So it would be interesting to.
Because chimpanzees and gorillas live about twice as long
as all the other primates.
And humans live about.
So they get to be about 30 or 40.
And humans get to be about 60 or 80.
So this probably has some meaning
having to do with selection and survival.
Yeah?
So I want to know if you know how many projects there are
out there trying to do an intelligent system.
How many people?
And if you believe that what's lacking
is the right theory to be put in practice,
are just lines of code to be written,
and the theory is already out there.
That's a great question.
We ought to have a map.
Has anybody compiled a?
Heike, you know what's happening in Europe in that area?
I don't know if there is many people
doing ambitious efforts.
By the way, I just looked up on the CNN site
quite early in the lecture.
You mentioned that it would be nice to have
this one billion investment for developing AI
to care of elderly people.
So now I just looked up on the CNN website
how much Watson cost, and the estimate
is $1 to $2 billion.
$1 to $2 billion.
So they spent $1 to $2 billion developing that.
Billion?
Yes.
Program.
To develop Watson?
IBM has a large budget.
So apparently, IBM has a $6 billion research budget
every year, and they put 5% to 10% of that
directly or indirectly.
And that's how this is calculated.
So I don't know the details.
I don't know the idea.
Wow.
It's more like $100 billion.
Why is that $1 billion?
Is there any people or something for a few years?
Yeah, so that's the official estimate.
And then there's others that say it's $1 billion.
Because it's only about 10 Super Bowl ads.
How long is a Super Bowl ad?
Is it a minute?
30 seconds.
Yeah.
So they got a lot more publicity out of that
than they would have got out of 10 Super Bowl ads.
Yeah, it's a bargain.
I was wondering what's the world cost of sports?
Indirect or indirect?
Direct, I think, would be interesting enough.
Well, if you paid people $1 an hour to watch sports,
how much would it cost?
But then again, it's probably quite cheap.
If the people weren't watching sports
but instead killing each other or having stuff like that,
then that might be more expensive by human capital.
What would they do?
They would invent sports.
There must be some country that doesn't.
Yeah, just for comparison, Coca-Cola's annual advertising
budget is $1.6 billion.
What's their profit?
Does it?
I don't know.
We can find out.
At the Media Lab meeting, there were yet smaller Coke bottles,
seven ounces.
The diet.
Both.
But what?
Were they painted?
Oh, they were red.
They're red.
They look like Coke cans, but they're seven ounce size.
So an excess budget was $7.7 billion.
Oh, that's more than I thought.
Can you mix?
So whatever happened to massive parallelism?
It used to be in the business.
Well, I think the Watson is, how many processors
does it claim to use?
I don't know, a couple thousand.
It has 16 terabytes of RAM, and each processor
can only index, what, 64 gigabytes.
So that's at least hundreds of processors.
There are a lot of interesting problems
that can't be solved with parallelism.
So if you put, depends on the geometry of your search trees.
So if a process is going to require a great many steps,
then parallelism is hard to, sequential steps.
Then parallelism can't help much.
But I don't know what's happened.
And then you see an announcement that somebody
in some country has the biggest computer at the moment.
And it's usually a few hundred or thousand processors
that they got somewhere else.
So I haven't heard of any attempt
to make a really colossal machine.
Neil Gershenfeld had a project here
in which he hoped to make an extremely
efficient and inexpensive super parallel computer.
It turned out that it was hard to do
some kinds of operations like recursion in that architecture.
But does anybody know what's happened lately?
Is that project still going?
It is not.
Just stopped.
David was a vital part of it.
So he can.
It's me.
Someday he'll tell the story.
So the whole lava machine project is stuck?
Yes, I think everyone involved has acknowledged at this point
that it's not very efficient.
But the demos were really pretty.
Yes, it would be nice to know what the brain does
and how parallel it is.
And I won't repeat my complaints about neuroscientists.
But generally, we don't see architectural theories
of what the brain centers do, except
in the beautiful cases of the cerebellum, which is maybe
fairly well understood.
The visual cortex, which is fairly well understood,
at least at the first stages.
But there aren't any theories.
I've never seen any good theories
of how different brain centers communicate.
We know that there are these bundles of wires.
But we don't know if they're like K lines or ZETO
coding or whatever.
And I'm afraid most of the papers I read
go the other direction and say there's
much more in the glial cells that support the neurons
than anybody ever suspected.
And that's sort of mystical.
It's like saying that the paint on the car
is the important part.
Well, in your book, you mentioned
that the higher level processes are
more likely to be sequential, not parallel,
because it takes a lot of resources to build them
and to support them.
I found that also when you're trying to fall asleep,
if you activate your higher level resources,
like say from self-reflective and up,
if you started reflecting, it's almost impossible
to fall asleep.
It's almost like you're only able to fall asleep
when those are resting.
And your lower level processes are the only ones that are active.
You say you can't fall asleep when you're reflecting?
Yeah.
Feynman says the opposite, right?
He had the whole entire stage of his life
where he sort of reflected as he was going to sleep
and was able to sort of control his dreams.
Well, there are people.
What do you call control dreaming?
Lucid dreaming.
What's the word?
Lucid.
Lucid dreaming, where you can program yourself
for a particular topic.
How many of you can do that?
One, two, three.
Four.
It would be boring to have the same dream every time.
I mean, like recognizing what kind of thinking
is going on in yourself or trying to recognize.
Well, a good question is how much of dreaming is thinking
and how different is it from regular thinking?
Is it just that you've turned some critics off?
I don't think neuroscientists have critics, though, yet.
You know, John Cox's theory of dreams?
No.
OK.
John Cox's theory of dreams goes like this.
If you imagine that we have an optimal encoder that
stores things away by optimally encoding it, OK, well,
then you have to have the decoder.
But if it's an optimal encoder, then any random noise
would decode into a plausible sequence of events.
And if you happen to hear a barking dog while you're asleep,
that fact can be incorporated into the dream
by that same mechanism with the optimal decoding.
So something I received over on a phone call
once a long time ago.
So if you were in an anechoic chamber,
maybe you would not have such good dreams
because you wouldn't get any external signals.
Right.
Well, your brain can probably make quite a lot of noise
that we have not.
So I don't think you need to have somatic signals
to have that kind of a.
You don't need that.
The only point is it can be incorporated into a dream.
And that does happen.
When you're dreaming and there's some particular sound,
like a fire engine going by, it does
get incorporated into your dream, at least in my case.
So his mechanism explains that.
John Cock was a friend of ours who
was a first-rate mathematician who worked at IBM.
He was a great computer architect.
And he designed the PowerPC series of CPUs.
So he invented risk architecture and improved my theorem tag.
I published a paper with him.
The projector isn't on right now.
So you know.
I don't have anything new to say.
It usually shuts off at 830.
What?
815.
815?
Oh.
That's the program audio we just muted.
While the projector's going, I have a question.
Do you think it's necessary for intelligence beings to sleep?
And if so, do you think future AI will be required to sleep?
That's a great question, because I
don't think anyone really understands
why sleep is necessary.
I mean, maybe it's to empty buffers that have gotten stuck.
You can make up computer-like theories,
but I don't think there's.
I've never heard of any theory that
comes along with some evidence.
Do you have a?
They say it's good for memory, so maybe when you create your K
lines, when you're seeing stuff, you create your K lines,
and it's not the optimal way, or I don't know.
Oh, the standard theory is that REM sleep
is necessary to transfer records into long-term memory,
from short-term memory.
I don't know if anyone has a theory of how that works,
though, so it's how do you decide,
how do you root a representation of knowledge
from the hippocampus, or the amygdala,
or wherever it's stored in short-term memory?
I think it's the amygdala, supposedly.
And how does it find a place in the larger brain,
and what representation does it have, and so forth?
I've never seen any.
I don't read that literature much,
but I don't know of any popular theory
of how knowledge is represented in short-term memory
and later in long-term, and how it's transferred,
and what the locations are, and what determines them.
Any of you had any contact with that side of neuroscience?
I guess one standard computer analogy for dreaming
is garbage collection.
So you can talk about copying and copying garbage collection,
so you could imagine it's some kind of copying garbage
collection.
Yes, when do animals start sleeping?
Do crocodiles sleep?
We could ask Google.
What do they dream about?
Well, porpoises are interesting.
They sleep after rain and time.
Right.
Porpoises and albatrosses.
If they didn't, they would drown.
Have you ever seen an albatross take off?
Usually takes four tries.
It falls over, and it's lucky.
That's an Android stream of electric sheep.
It's lucky it doesn't break its neck.
It runs as fast as it can and falls over.
Wasn't that the story that became Blade Runner?
Oh.
Android stream of electric sheep by Philip K. Dick, right?
Yes.
Did they sleep in?
The replicants?
Yeah.
It came back.
Come on.
Binsky?
I want to see something in chapter 5.
That has to do with dreams.
That's interesting.
How far back do you have to go before that looks like?
No.
What?
I'm teasing.
I wouldn't recognize it either, would I?
Up there you go.
It really looked like when I swung my monitor past it.
But looking at my eyes, it doesn't do the same thing.
Can Google recognize faces yet?
Facebook?
It can search based on images.
So you can upload an image and say,
find an image like this one.
And I think it just does it by color selection
of sheep and the general thing.
And then if they use face recognition technology,
there would be a danger of violating all sorts of laws.
So they make sure that whatever they do,
it's officially not face recognition.
Martin, there's another question.
So neuroscience now, they have some sort of apparatus
or tools that I believe they can recognize,
like the waves, like the lateral magnetic waves
in your brains.
Do you think we need more powerful tools?
Or is it just that they're not asking
the right questions?
Yeah, that's the question.
Because you said that the neurons just transmit
a certain voltage.
And maybe what we just need to study
is these patterns of these wave signals
that we send between neurons.
And it doesn't seem that hard to detect that.
Information.
Martin is carrying a microphone on.
Does that trickle up?
It's in your pocket.
How could it change the system?
So it could be the brain.
It could be the brain.
How could it change the switch in my pocket?
All of the current scanning instruments
are very low resolution.
So if you had something like if one of those white matter
bundles going from one part of the brain to another
has 10,000 signals, you can't resolve any of those.
So there might be lots of bits going along one
of these fiber bundles.
And all you can see with the brain scanning techniques
is a change in metabolism of a fairly large pixel.
You're not seeing the signals themselves.
You're seeing the average of thousands of signals.
So it's going to be very hard until you actually
stick a lot of needles in one of those pathways.
And probably somebody will be able to invent some not very
dangerous way of doing that, but there aren't any now.
They put fairly high resolution things
on the surface of the cortex.
And that way, you can get a lot of information,
but not through the skull.
Anyway.
So I think what we have also was that we're also interested
to hear if you believe that more advanced or more detailed
images of the, well, I call it implementation of how
the mind is implemented in our brains or the actual data.
How helpful this would be in discovering
the actual cognitive functions or brain central operation
or whatever.
Well, it's a very hard.
No, too little to answer that question.
It's just very hard to see how you
could get thousands of electrical signals out.
So for example, there's a big channel
between the speech recognition area
and the speech production area.
Forget what it's called.
It would be wonderful to know what's
happening on those many thousands of fibers.
And then you could probably discover
how words or syntactic structures are represented.
If you could just see what's actually
happening on those neurons.
Somebody will invent some three-dimensional scanner someday.
But right now, it takes too much energy.
And it would ruin everything.
So yes, I recently read a report online about a study done
at UC Berkeley.
I don't know if you've heard of it.
But the idea is that they supposedly
found a way to make scans of brainwaves
and visualize it using fMRI software.
I think the idea was that certain brainwaves could
be associated with certain images.
Associated with what?
Certain brainwaves would be associated
with certain shapes.
And I think I actually have the report right in front of me.
But basically, they showed test subjects two different,
I think it was hour-long YouTube videos.
And on this website, they showed the YouTube video
that the test subject was shown.
And the simulated image that was derived
from the brainwaves of the particular subject.
Is that an image of what the patient is
looking at at the moment?
Or is it a mad one that he's thinking about?
It seemed to be a combination of both.
Because when I looked at the video, for just generic shapes,
it would match up pretty easily.
But when it was zooming in on someone's profile,
the image was very difficult to render.
I can show you the link if you want to take a look at it.
Well, if you open up, if you take off a piece of skull
and look at the visual, the primary visual cortex, which
is called area 17 for no particular reason.
Then if you're operating on an epileptic patient or something,
someone like that, then while you're doing the operation,
you can put an array of a lot of electrodes,
say 20 by 20 array or even more.
And in the primary visual cortex,
you can get an image because this piece of cortex
goes right to the optic nerve and gets signals
from the back of the eye.
But in a sense, that doesn't tell you much
because you know that the image has
to get inside the head somehow.
And the real question is more what's
happening in the next two areas, 18 and 19,
which do all sorts of processing.
But you can't get an image from them, or at least as far
as I know, nobody has.
Also, these images are being dated at about 10 per second.
So you get movies, which is nice, from the primary cortex.
I mean, do you think it would be possible to look at brain
waves and try to determine what, if you record someone's
brain waves while they're dreaming,
do you think it would be possible to determine
what they're dreaming about?
Well, brain wave is a specific term
for a very large scale event.
So there's not much information in that.
But if you could see the electrical activity
in the brain, then you could.
In other words, when the phrase brain wave stands for alpha,
beta, and there's about four different types of waves,
and those are very unlocalized, the reason they're interesting
is that you can pick them up with a low,
with an audio amplifier, I think,
because they are resulting from firing
a very large numbers of neurons.
And so you get millivolts rather than microvolts.
And it's easy to pick up outside the skull.
But picking up the signals from large numbers
of individual nerve cells has never really been feasible.
And maybe it won't be so hard.
In a few years, maybe you can make a little integrated
circuit that has little synthesizing modules that
make the tiny silver wires that are carbon fibers that
go down into the brain and go around obstacles a little bit.
And there's no reason why you couldn't
have fibers of the order of a micron in size,
1,000th of a millimeter, that could pick up
very large numbers of signals without damaging the brain
too much.
I guess people working on nanotechnology
are getting close to considering such things,
because they are actually doing something very much like that.
Is there any gadget that can make a carbon fiber
under controlled conditions?
Not really.
You're not at the limiting point where you need nanotubes.
He's building fibers of more like 10 micrometer diameter,
which you can make using conventional technologies,
almost like NEMS.
So it's not down to the one micron level yet,
but there's at least a few groups that are definitely
thinking about how to get very large numbers of signals
out of the brain by using thin fibers that
go around obstacles a little bit.
Well, if you could get a large number,
it might not matter much where they're from, because nobody's
ever seen any brain center working in great detail.
Right.
But you probably still wouldn't be
able to get them close enough together
to see any two neurons that are directly
connected to each other.
Also, you could put signals in and learn a lot.
That's true.
I have my own prejudice about this,
but I think a lot of the interest in the brain
is a lot like interest in how birds fly with regard
to designing airplanes or inventing airplanes.
So in inventing an airplane, the bird was a kind,
especially a soaring bird, like a hawk,
was a good thing to look at a little bit.
But then studying the feathers and laying of eggs,
if we had copied them, then a Boeing 747, after a while,
would lay this egg and out would hatch another one, which
you'd have to feed something.
I don't know what.
So it's the high-level principles
we really need from the brain, not the low-level
implementation.
Now, what do you consider to be low-level?
What?
What do you consider low-level?
What I consider, well, it's like,
where do all these neurons go, and how are they interconnected
I had a little essay in a book on Logo
complaining that if you look in a child's world,
it's very hard to find three of anything.
There's lots of twos because of symmetry,
and you have two hands and two feet and stuff,
and if you're lucky, two parents.
But if you walk around the house, which I did,
I couldn't find three of anything
that a child might consider to be significant enough
to form a concept for three-ness.
How about five?
Well, you can't get there.
Apparently, once you get to four, the rest is easy.
But why is it a whole year between two and three?
And so a great experiment, which would only cost a billion
dollars, would be to provide a million children,
two-year-olds with toys that have three parts or something
and see if they learn to count to three slightly sooner.
So this discussion made me think about the concept
of embodied cognition, which is the idea that because human
beings are born into a three-dimensional world
and are born with a body and with all the,
I guess, everything that's associated with having a body
and embodying, having a body and living
in the spatial existence, a lot of our mental structures
sort of take advantage of these things,
as in a lot of the way that we think about things
utilize space to organize our thoughts and utilize the fact
that we have bodies to help us think.
So I guess this made me sort of think about,
in order to make computers that think like humans,
would we have to fake them, make computers think
that they have human bodies, perhaps?
You could give them a little simulator.
I think you'd do just as well with stick figures
than with three-dimensionals.
That's two and a half-dimensional sort of.
But I don't know if that idea of embodied cognition
actually holds up anymore.
It was popular for a while because of,
actually it was an MIT professor, Dick Held,
who, I think I mentioned this a couple of weeks ago,
he did some experiments which showed that if you carry
an animal around, it can't find its way back in general.
But if you drag it around on a leash or something,
then it can.
And so he concluded that people couldn't do motor learning
unless they had actively engaged the environment.
But then we got reason to think that this didn't apply
to humans because of
that PhD thesis of Jose, what's his name?
Valenti.
He had a cerebral palsy patient
who had never moved around in the real world.
It was sort of bedridden.
But he observed stuff and when he was given
the controls of a logo turtle, he was able to,
he didn't have any trouble when the turtle turned around
to make it turn left instead of right
because it was facing the other way,
which was the kind of thing that Held had shown
that his lab animals couldn't learn.
So I don't, so the idea of embodied cognition
became very popular and it was why.
Thanks everyone.
The microphone.
Won't you do it now?
The battery ran out.
compelling answer
Now that it lit up.
How do you keep your hand out of your pocket?
You can get out now.
You can use it.
battery is getting recharged there. I think the problem with Brooks is that he observed
that people are smart and people have bodies, therefore we better have bodies if we're going
to be smart. And that might be sort of true at a certain level, but it's only true in
the sense that maybe it's the perceptual apparatus that's important. But just presuming that
there's something religious about having a body seems to me to be wrong-headed because
the natural tendency is to go off and spend several years soldering up a robot thinking
that you're contributing to intelligence. So it's a little bit like Ed's feather example.
It's not important to have feathers, but it can be useful to know how feathers work and
how they're hollow and all that stuff to reduce weight. So the real question is what does
having a body actually do for you? Not to go off and suppose that there's something
mystically and religiously sacred about having a body.
Yeah, there's no reason why a machine couldn't have a simulated world.
Yeah, the question is do one-year-olds do that? Who knows? Probably they do.
One last question.
So when we are imagining stuff, we don't usually imagine the smell of things. And so the smell
of things. And like, I don't know, it's important that we use our apparatus and maybe our imagination
is constrained by how much area we use. It's constrained, but cats, I don't know what's
the point that I'm trying to make, but cats have a really good representation of smell
and dogs have. And maybe why they can't find a path is because their vision apparatus in
their brain, like the part that represents the vision is not very well developed as for
humans. Because when we imagine stuff, we use more the vision than like smelling or,
I don't know, touching. Like dreams are not, you don't feel touching too much. You imagine
with your eyes, with your vision more than smelling and touching. And maybe why we are
so good is because we concentrate more in vision than smelling or touching or, I don't know, any other.
Well, that embodied cognition issue is a strange one because, oh, because some people feel very
strongly about it and I'm not sure what the psychology of those psychologists is. Anyway,
it looks like it's time to go. We could ask Google if it's still raining. You don't need a
body anymore with Google.