The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Thanks, Marvin.
I decided to call my talk Mind versus Brain Confessions
of a Defector.
I used to be an AIist.
My thesis was reviewed by Marvin.
I worked in the media lab.
I thought about models of computation
that might be more suited to building AIs.
Really, I didn't have that many good ideas,
although people thought they were good ideas.
And this kind of scared me, so I backed away a little bit.
And then I found a really cool problem
in the area of neuroscience.
And I've now left AI at MIT, and I'm a PhD student now
in biophysics at Harvard.
And I'm working on worms, and I'm
trying to figure out how they think to the extent
that they do.
And so I wanted to sort of go over not really
the details of neuroscience or the details of my work.
I mean, I'm going to do sort of what Marvin does.
I'm going to talk for a little bit,
and then we can talk about whatever you want.
And if you want to get into the details, that's great.
But first, I just wanted to kind of give
you an overview of, from my perspective, where
I see neuroscience and AI sort of fitting in with each other
and with the larger context of sort
of the history of science and the taxonomy of science.
So I sort of self-identify as a mathematician to the extent
that people have sort of discipline identities,
like gender identities or racial or cultural identities,
and my discipline identity is math.
And so I see everything as sort of springing out
from that.
So on one side, you have sort of the scientific tower,
where you have physics.
And on top of physics, you put chemistry.
And on top of chemistry, you put biology.
And on top of biology, you have neuroscience.
And there's also the sort of computer science,
where you start from theory of computation,
and then you have sort of software engineering,
and then AI.
And in both cases, what you're really stretching toward
is an understanding of what thought is.
And we sort of got to some success
in sort of figuring out what the universe is, at least down
to a certain level of description.
I can turn on the blackboard lights.
Yeah, there is a blackboard light.
No, I don't know where to buy transparencies anymore.
That would have been good to know.
What's that?
But what we're really trying to get to
is sort of this fundamental question
of what is human experience?
And human experience is sort of dominated
by consciousness, or cognition, or whatever
you want to call it.
And we really don't know what's going on there.
We have something called COGSI.
And it definitely connects to both neuro and AI.
But it's pretty fuzzy right now.
And a lot of people take the metaphor of transistors
and talking about the brain and that, oh, as neuroscientists,
we spend a lot of time looking at the details
of what happens in the nonlinear regime of this sort
of neural transistor.
But it really doesn't matter, because what matters
is when you put the things together and so on,
which is a good metaphor.
But a metaphor that I also like and I see used less often
is that we're sort of right now looking at thought
and its relation to the brain.
I think we're sort of where Copernicus was when he was
thinking about the planets.
In a sense, we had sort of the right basic idea.
We have the idea that thought happens in brains.
And Copernicus had the idea that planets orbit the sun, which
at the time was a new idea for Copernicus.
And in relative scheme of things,
it's kind of a new idea for us that thought happens in brains
and happens by electrical impulse.
But Copernicus didn't have gravity.
He didn't have Newton.
And so in describing the orbits, he
had all of these little corrections and epicycles
and deference in trying to make sense of the things that would
later all follow from this very simple theory of calculus
and of gravity, but that was yet to be discovered.
And so I think that there's something
that we're getting to in the realm of cognitive science,
some sort of new mathematical insight
that I think will be on the same par as discovery of calculus
in terms of how networks emerge to perform
complex computation in living systems.
And the way that I think about that
is when we really get down to the essence of calculus,
it's about what happens in the limit of things sort of acting
in similar ways as you cut them into smaller and smaller pieces
and have more of those pieces.
And what we're looking at in both in neuroscience
and in sociology to a lesser extent because fewer people
are doing quantitative things there,
but we're looking at scale-free networks
where as you partition the network
at different sizes of partitions,
you get the same sort of in degrees and out degrees.
And we really don't know what we're talking about when
we go into scale-free networks, but it
seems that there's something there that
relates to sort of the mysteries.
The things that we're bumping into that I feel
are the same sorts of things that people
didn't do shortly before we figured out calculus.
So anyway, that's sort of my big philosophical spiel.
I also wanted to tie into this quote from Ernst Rutherford,
who's kind of one of the greatest curmudgeons of science
history, who once said, all science is either physics
or stamp collecting, that either you're writing down
the equations and you know exactly how things work,
or you're just sort of saying, oh, this looks nice.
Let me write down what it looks like and where I found it.
And biology is definitely still largely
in the stamp-collecting realm, and it doesn't have to be.
It's not the nature of studying living systems, which
is the reason that we have biophysics.
That's the reason that I am in a biophysics program.
But there's sort of this cultural tradition in biology
that goes back to sort of Darwin, where you just sort
of look around the world, you write down what you see,
and it's a time-honored tradition,
and it certainly gets you pretty far.
But it seems to break down when we look at the brain,
because you start cataloging these things that
are so minute, and you start cataloging them in isolation
instead of considering them as dynamical systems that
interact with their surroundings.
And it seems that you really have a hard time putting
those pieces back together once you've sort of collected them
in separate observations.
So that's another point I wanted to make.
And then I was just going to talk a little bit about why
I think things are changing, especially in the neurodomain.
There is the sort of classic way that you do neuroexperiments
is you have some sort of furry creature,
and you present some sort of stimulus,
and then you stick a wire somewhere into the brain,
and you measure what happens depending on the stimulus.
And you don't know what you're looking at,
but you know that you're looking at something,
and you can get some sort of idea
as to what things are similar.
Hubel and Weasel did these great experiments
where they stuck electrodes into cats' visual cortex
and basically just kind of waved their arms around
and saw that some of the neurons were orientation sensitive,
and that's the foundation for much of our current knowledge
and research about vision in mammals.
But it doesn't tell you how the different things
that you're looking at relate to each other,
and it gives you only the merest glimpse.
I mean, even in the most dense sort of electrode applications,
you're going to get a maximum of thousands or maybe 10,000
signals out of this at once.
And most likely, none of those neurons that you're looking at
are going to be anywhere near each other
on the scale of synapses.
And so you're essentially just sampling a population.
And in fact, there's a lot of research
in this field that goes under the rubric of population
dynamics, where you're sort of just looking
at things in the aggregate.
And I heard a nice little metaphor, actually,
just today in an unrelated class about populations,
where if you're, for instance, examining
the population of people walking down Fifth Avenue in New York
City, you can measure things like the average rate
that people are walking down.
But you're never going to capture something
if you're just looking at flow across everything,
like every 100 meters, people will turn into a shop
and stop for a few minutes, and then come back out
and start again.
So you're only getting sort of very broad strokes.
Or otherwise, you're taking the neuron out
of its natural context.
And you're just saying, OK, here I
have a neuron in a dish, whatever,
in some sort of growth medium.
And I'm just going to probe it and see
what happens when I stimulate this neuron
in different places.
And then you're really just likely exploring parts
of the phase space that this neuron would never
experience in the system.
And you're getting no indication as
to which parts of the phase space it actually is in,
or how that would relate to other parts of the system.
And when you're dealing with this complex information
processing network, that's pretty critical.
That's sort of the classical state
of neuroscience, which basically plateaued, I think,
about 30 years ago, which is the reason why people like Marvin
are pretty frustrated with it.
But in more recent times, we've started
to get some different ways of looking at neural systems
that I think are really exciting.
This is why I decided now is a good time
to be a neuroscientist.
So now we have, if we zoom in to sort of our physicist's
spherical neuron, it has a cell bilayer.
And neurons are powered by channels
which interrupt the bilayer and can pass certain types of ions.
And naturally, ions carry charge.
And some channels, depending on concentrations
and the voltages, will have positive ions flowing in,
positive ions flowing out, negative in, out.
And these dynamics basically form
the basis for neural activity and action
potentials and everything.
And we found some of these channels or things
that functionally are like channels in prokaryotes,
basically single-celled organisms in algae, in archaea,
in bacteria even, that have really useful properties.
For instance, there's one called channel rhodopsin,
which turns on if and only if there's
blue light impinging upon it.
And this was discovered about 15 years ago.
And about 10 years ago, it was sequenced.
And now with the ability to synthesize genes
and introduce them into other organisms,
we can take that gene and add it
to a neuron, which is not at all where it belongs.
Nature would never put this type of channel on a neuron
because there's no reason for neurons
to be sensitive to light unless there are photoreceptors
in the retina.
But now that we have this blue light-activated channel,
we can point a laser at the cell.
And when we turn it on, if it's the right wavelength,
the cell gets activated.
When you turn it off, the effect disappears.
And so you can now do these very precise sorts of perturbations
and see what happens.
And because it's a genetically expressed channel, what
a lot of people did initially is they would just
express the channel in a certain class of cells
that has a specific promoter that's been discovered.
And then just use a wide-field blue lamp,
light up the entire brain.
And then only that class of cells in which you express
the light-sensitive channel will turn on.
So you can see, what does this class of cells actually do?
There's a similar channel that's
activated by a yellow light that removes, well, actually,
it introduces negative ions, introduces chlorine.
And that causes the cell to hyperpolarize or deactivate.
So you can selectively inhibit populations based on genetics.
And this allows you to do something like a knockout.
A lot of people do knockout mice where
you remove some class of cells, say, here's
the behavioral deficit.
But basically, you can do it with a positive control.
Because if you aren't shining yellow light into the skull,
then it's just like a regular mouse.
And this is really helpful for determining those effects.
But even so, this is still population dynamics.
You're still just talking about some broad class of cells,
all pyramidal neurons, all basal ganglia.
Here's what happens when you remove them.
So there's another piece of it.
There's another piece of this puzzle,
which is a multi-photon microscopy.
And this is something that how many people
know multi-photon or two-photon?
OK, so I recently learned about this, too.
And it's really cool, because this is a sort of thing
that when you're first eight years old
and you hear about lasers, this is a sort of thing
that you would imagine that you would do with lasers.
And then you learn a bit more about lasers,
and you realize lasers don't work that way.
And then you learn more about lasers.
You're like, whoa, actually, you can do that with lasers.
And what you do is you have one laser.
It's a femtosecond laser, which is
necessary because of the ridiculous synchronization
that's required in doing this.
Not only does it have to be a femtosecond laser,
but you actually, even though it's two-photon,
you're using two beams, you can't have two lasers,
because they won't be well enough synchronized.
So you have to split a laser into two beams.
And then you focus, using fancy optics
that I don't know enough optics to draw,
those two beams onto a single point inside your sample.
And the wavelength of this laser is twice the wavelength
necessary to excite your channel rhodopsin
or your halo rhodopsin.
And what happens is there's a small but non-vanishing
probability that two photons from the two branches of this
will arrive at exactly the same point, not quite plank time,
but in sort of molecular excitation time.
And if those two photons arrive close enough to each other,
they'll have exactly the same effect
on the state of the molecule as a photon with half
the wavelength or twice the energy,
because those two photons each deliver that amount of energy
and so it gets doubled.
So this only can happen at exactly the spot
where the two beams converge.
And so you get this extremely selective, not only z-slicing,
but also an even more selective x- and y-slicing.
And so you can use this to target an individual neuron
and you can do it repeatably.
You can do it reliably.
You can do it in any space in your working volume.
You can target using basically acousto-optic deflectors,
which again, you can't draw, so they're
going to be black boxes.
But you can do it very fast.
It's expensive, but you can direct these
at hundreds of hertz.
And so you can essentially write to anywhere in the brain.
You can turn things off or on as you wish,
as long as you know the locations.
And the other final piece of this sort of optogenetics puzzle
is there's a fluorescent protein called Gcamp, which
is sort of like a GFP, but with a calmodulin attached to it.
And the calmodulin binds calcium ions
and the GFP is a green fluorescent protein.
But when the calmodulin isn't bound to a calcium,
it sort of hangs out here and disturbs
the conformation of the GFP so that it can't fluoresce.
But when this binds a calcium, then the GFP fluoresces green.
And calcium is one of the major signalings for neuron firing,
especially for neurotransmitter release.
You need an influx of calcium.
So this basically tells you whether the neuron is active.
And as if that weren't enough, because it
is a second messenger, just this year there
is a protein developed that's a membrane protein, also
genetically encoded.
All of these can be just engineered
into a line of animals and then you
don't need to worry about it anymore, no injections
or anything.
So there's another one that originally nature
intended this as a proton pump.
It's archaeodopsin.
It's a light sensitive proton pump.
But what they were able to do is to silence the proton pumping,
basically to disable that aspect of the protein's function.
But then they discovered that it actually
then has a fluorescence which is proportional to the voltage
across the membrane that it would
be moving those protons across.
So in sum, you can activate neurons.
You can inhibit neurons.
You can measure the calcium concentration
or activation.
And you can measure the voltage.
And you can do it all anywhere you want very fast.
So this is basically a toolkit for doing experiments
that you could really only dream of with electrophysiology.
In particular, the one that I'm working on right now
is the worm, C. elegans, which is a very well studied
organism.
And in fact, it's the only organism
for which we actually know the complete connectome.
So a lot of people talk about connectomes.
And it's sort of a dark secret of neuroscience
that we already have the connectome for C. elegans
and we can't do anything with it.
Because it turns out that just knowing where you have one
neuron here and its synapses to this neuron here
and this controls the body wall muscles, that doesn't really
tell you anything like maybe this is an inhibitory synapse.
Maybe it's excitatory.
Maybe it's non-functional.
Maybe it's stronger than the other synapses on that cell.
Maybe it's weaker.
And so it basically gives you very little information
to start from if you're trying to understand
how this organism thinks or computes.
But since we know where all the neurons are,
and there are only 302 of them, it's
not crazy to think about using this microscope
and these biophysical techniques to actually build
a model pairwise, if need be, of all 90,000 pairs of how
every neuron affects the behavior of every other neuron.
So that's what I'm working on.
I think that actually doing these sorts of observations
is something that's never really been done before.
And again, to make a ridiculously grandiose
comparison, it's kind of like how
Newton only was able to do what he did because Galileo
developing the tools to observe phenomena that
had never been seen before.
And I think that advances, well, this is actually
a quote from Sydney Brenner, who is the first person
to suggest that you can study this worm
and maybe learn something from its nervous system.
Advances in science usually come from new techniques,
new discoveries, and new ideas in that order.
And so now we have the techniques.
We're working on the discoveries.
And the hope is that it will lead to new ideas.
So questions?
Yes?
So you've given us this overview of the state of the art
right now and possibly how it's going to be in five years.
But how do you think neuroscience
is going to be in about 20 years or maybe 30 years from now?
Well, what we can do right now is this most basic organism
that nature has to offer.
And the natural thing to do once that gets solved,
which we don't know how long it will take because we don't know
how much detail is really important,
but I think that we can solve the worm in three or four
years.
And then the next step is the zebrafish,
which is also optically transparent,
which is handy for using these sorts of optical microscopes.
But the zebrafish has 100,000 neurons,
so it's a big jump in complexity.
And it has a lot of the same sorts of brain regions
that you see in mammals and even humans,
though they often go by different names.
But it's a similar structure.
It's a vertebrate, and it has eyes, which the worm doesn't.
So that'll be the next thing to look at.
And I think that'll probably take another five years
or so.
And then maybe drosophila, bees are pretty complicated.
That's the first place where you get something
that resembles language.
So that might be really interesting.
And eventually, mice, cats, dogs, monkeys, and humans.
And definitely, the path that this goes on in an ideal world
is toward taking an individual human brain
and turning it into a model.
Yes?
What would you consider to be solving the worm?
How much do we need to know about this?
What are the big problems there?
What are the things that we still have to understand?
The way that I have set up the criteria,
there's a big list of publications, basically,
of behavioral results.
And there's a lot of stereotype behaviors.
There's something like 30 or 40 different conditions
where you can put the worm in these conditions,
and they exhibit particular omega turns or reversals
or things like that.
So that's sort of the baseline.
Say, well, if you put the worm, the virtual worm,
in these conditions in a virtual simulated petri dish,
they exhibit all the same behaviors.
That's sort of your first order check.
And then the next step is, well, what happens
if you remove a neuron?
You pick one of the 302 neurons in a physical worm.
You can ablate it with a laser.
You can kill a cell specifically.
Or you can just inhibit it with a haloridopsin.
Then you can see, does the virtual worm
exhibit the same behavioral differences
as the physical worm under that condition?
And you can also do larger scale sorts of things.
You can say, well, what happens if I
were to activate this neuron 10 times a second every 5 seconds?
And how would that change things?
So you could do lots of different perturbations.
And that, to me, is the best way to check
that you have what I consider a biologically relevant
model.
But what you're looking for is not anything on sort of the,
you're looking for observables, basically.
And I think that's what you have to do if you're doing science.
You have to be looking at what's observable.
And right now, what's going on inside the synapses
is not observable.
So I'm not going to be simulating that.
And part of the hypothesis, since I'm
doing this a PhD thesis, it has to answer a scientific question.
And the question is, can you capture
the qualitative aspects of behavior
as viewed externally without modeling
what's going on at the molecular dynamic level?
Yeah.
A question on connectomes.
So in my understanding of the human brain,
I thought that neurons could grow new connections
with other neurons.
So in that sense, it's like the map
of the connections between all pairs of neurons
is constantly changing.
Yes.
How would that work when we're trying
to find the connectome of a more complicated organism whose
neurons do make new connections?
So C. elegans, nicely enough, doesn't do that.
But you're absolutely right.
Mammals do.
Mammals do form new connections.
And there's also, even in C. elegans,
there's a question of development.
It's been shown, not conclusively,
but fairly convincingly, that electrical activity is not
only important for cognition.
It's also important for development.
And if you introduce genes that basically only
break action potential function of a neuron,
those neurons, as they develop from birth onward,
they don't form the connections that they should.
And so there's something going on.
There's some computation going on
that's development-specific, probably,
because in most areas of the brain,
once you reach a certain level of maturity,
those sorts of processes stop growing.
So there's some sort of computation there.
And I'm explicitly leaving that out
because I want to graduate in a reasonable amount of time,
saying, development, future work.
And it is.
It's future work.
And at the same time as, hopefully, this is a success.
Someone will go look at the zebrafish.
And someone will go look and try and figure out
how C. elegans develops from a larval stage
to an adult with all 302 neurons and how they find
each other to connect.
And that's definitely important because how
the nervous system develops gives us
some clue as to what the functional organization is.
Because the things that develop in concert and stem
from the same developmental program, in a sense,
probably have the same functions when
they're finished developing.
But separate from development, there's
also this question of learning.
And if you do just capture a connectome,
it seems to me that there is a possibility that what you could
wind up doing is sort of capturing
a connectome frozen in time.
You could wind up with some anterograde amnesia effect.
Because if you're missing some aspect of plasticity
on a short-term scale, you would get
the same sorts of responses.
But you wouldn't get the same sorts of changes over time.
So that is a possibility.
The way that you can get around that is if you have tools,
again, we're talking 20, 30 years in the future.
These are pretty recent.
Who knows what we'll have then.
If we can visualize something either at a lower level in terms
of what's going on with transcription factors,
or if we can visualize how the axonal processes grow,
then we can build models of that in the same way
that now we can build models of the steady state
dynamics in the sense of short time scale
dynamics of electrical activity.
Yeah?
Can you think, like, so how many neurons can you get at once
with that?
So it depends on how many lasers you have, right?
Number of lasers over two equals the number
of simultaneous observations.
But you can direct the lasers at hundreds of Hertz.
And so if you want to look at 100 neurons at 30 Hertz,
you can do that.
You just have to multiplex them.
And because the things, especially in C. elegans,
are on a fairly slow time scale because C. elegans doesn't
have action potentials, or at least they're not
thought to be significant for computation, it's doable.
As technology gets better again, you'll be able to scan faster.
There's actually people working on just fancier optics tricks
that let you scan faster.
And also, you can just use more lasers.
And there's nothing to say that you
have to be pointing one laser out.
You can multiplex much faster if you're
talking about pulsing lasers on and off
because they're femtosecond lasers.
So the more lasers you have, the better.
But ultimately, when we're talking about systems
like a mouse where you have to penetrate
through millimeters of tissue to get to certain regions,
it's probably not going to be optical.
And at least it's not going to be visible light.
One potential direction is called magnetoencephalography.
And when there's a neural current,
it induces a magnetic field just by Maxwell's equations.
And right now, if you have superconducting magnets, squids,
you can detect the currents of order
of 1,000 neurons activating at once.
So you have to have that level.
But when you're talking about 100 billion neurons
in the human brain, that's still pretty impressive.
It's pretty impressively fine grained.
It's much better than an MRI.
And as time goes on, again, hopefully, those things
will continue to evolve and improve to the point
where you can measure what's going on at a very low level.
And then on the control side, similarly,
we have transcranial magnetic stimulation.
And that also is rapidly increasing
in resolution and accuracy.
Sookie.
Do you have a name that works?
A friend of mine suggested Ellie for C. elegans.
But I haven't come up with any others.
Yeah.
OK.
So this question is trying to be not super well-formed.
But I'm going to have to.
No problem.
OK.
So clearly, since you're promoting
a few years of your life to this and doing your Christianity,
you do think it's important to try
to understand the low-level physics of it all
to understand the mind and thoughts, right?
Is that what is going on?
So I think what I'm trying to establish
is a lower bound on what's important.
Because there's a lot of people out there,
like Terry Szeginowski, who argue
that what's going on inside the synapse is important.
The mechanics of vesicle diffusion is important.
And if you're not keeping track of the vesicles,
you're really missing the point.
And so what I'm trying to do is, at least for one organism,
for 30 behaviors of this organism,
say, you know what, vesicle motion
is not important for this.
And then hopefully, once that's established,
we can sort of move forward and say, OK, well, maybe
the neuron, the different compartments in the neuron
aren't important either.
Maybe there are some functional units
that we can start to consider.
But I'm trying to just sort of establish that lower bound.
And in addition, I think in C. elegans,
where you have a total of 302 neurons,
that's on the same order of magnitude
as the number of sort of functional regions
that we've identified with MRI in human brains.
And I think in C. elegans, each of the neurons
really is pretty specialized to do
a certain job in the organism.
So I'm not sure that you could go that much higher
in this model system.
But at least, I'd like to say, the neurons
are the lowest level that you need to worry about.
OK, so as a follow-up to that, so that's
really cool that actually clarified something to me.
But do you think that work on higher level stuff
is still useful at this point?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
But I think that work on higher level stuff
is largely the same sort of work that
has been possible for a while.
I mean, there's certainly an argument
that we have way cheaper and more powerful computers
than we did when people started doing AI.
But I feel like most AI, it's not really about scale,
unless you're talking about Google-style AI, which
I feel like is not really the point.
So the reason that I moved into neuroscience
is because it's clear to me that there's something
that you can do now that you couldn't do before.
There's something you can see that you couldn't see before.
And so there's got to be something
that you can learn from that.
I don't think that this is the most probable path
to intelligence.
In a sense, I think there's many, many paths to intelligence.
And the collection of all of them
that don't involve looking at brains at all
is a greater probability of success
than the collection of all that involve looking at brains.
But I think this specific path is the most probable single
path.
If you were to compare it to hierarchical temporal memory
as a specific way that you can go,
or if you were to compare it to Bayesian networks
as a specific way to go, I think that this is more likely
than any specific thing.
So it's not that I think that it's the best,
but it's certainly the clearest at how to proceed.
And I like that.
All right.
Is there an estimate of how many genes control the nervous
system in the worm?
In the worm, I don't know that number, I think.
If you're talking about just like channels and transporters,
it's probably something like 100, if that.
There's a class of genes called unk for uncoordinated.
And when you remove those genes, the worm
doesn't really swim very well.
And there's about 120 genes in that class.
So I think that's sort of roughly the nervous system
genes, if you will.
I've seen estimates for the mammalian brain,
which are 20,000.
Well, 20,000 is how many genes there are in a human.
But maybe all of them are important for the brain.
Who knows?
Yeah?
When you're talking about removing some of those neurons,
are you talking about doing that in a matured worm that
doesn't have more development?
What about if you do that in a worm that hasn't developed yet
together with that?
Would you see things develop new connections?
Things get screwed up.
If you do it in a mammal, things adapt.
And you wind up kind of being OK.
Kind of being OK.
The worm developmental system is not that complicated.
And if you start killing things in the larval stage,
it kind of just isn't happy.
It'll usually live.
But the neurons that were supposed to go there
will just sort of get lost.
Is there a big point for what animal
is complex enough to adapt versus what isn't a worm?
So the word for it is non-utelic.
Utelic means that the network structure is fixed
and it won't adapt.
And I think you can get up to the level of about a snail.
And there are some utelic snails.
And then beyond that point, certainly all insects
have adaptive neural networks.
Yeah?
Can you just describe in a plain little detail
the kinds of experiments you're doing in the short term?
I mean, you've given some general sort of clues
about the method, about the experiment,
but what are the sources of experiments
you're doing in the nearest term?
The nearest term thing is actually just
to focus on the readout, which is the calcium image of readout,
to express in all the neurons, which no one has ever done.
Because there is this, again, it's
sort of a cultural bias, not that I'm unbiased,
I have one bias.
And biologists have the other bias,
which is to isolate the smallest publishable unit,
sort of say, OK, I'm going to work on this cell
and figure out its function, anything else is noise.
And so you try to minimize the expression of your transgene.
And what I'm trying to do is maximize it.
I want to know all of the cells, because I
want to be able to capture the entire system
so that I can treat it as sort of a closed system
with well-known inputs and outputs.
So in this case, the first thing I'm trying to do
is just to express calcium, just to do confocal imaging,
and to see if there's any patterns that pop out.
And right now, I'm just sort of in the process
of trying to get this gene to actually express
in all of the neurons.
Yeah.
So if every worm has the same number of neurons,
and they're all connected in the same way,
what accounts for the functional differences between worms?
Say, what makes one more uncoordinated than another?
Oh, so when you do have those mutations,
you do get different network structure.
Well, not all of the time.
Sometimes it's not different network structure.
Sometimes it's just that a certain class of neurons
is not excitable, it won't fire, because it's
missing voltage-gated channels or something like that.
Actually, none of them have voltage-gated channels.
But if it's missing receptors, for instance,
it'll just sit there, and it'll be
a roadblock to signals that are supposed to go through there.
So yeah, when you start mutating,
that breaks the rule that they're all exactly the same.
Yeah.
Follow-up to the question, how certain
are we that 80 genetically-deceased kind of case
changes the topology, and are genetically-modified
worms will behave in the same way,
in the same manner as an ordinary worm?
It's a very good question.
And the way that I've sort of dodged that is to say,
what I'm looking for is this sort of repertoire
of 30 or 40 behaviors.
And so suppose that introducing all of these foreign channels
really does change what's going on
at the level of neurodynamics.
But suppose that when you look at what the worm does
under various experimental conditions, it's still the same.
Then, yes, you're going to be simulating something
that isn't natural.
You're going to be simulating the modified state
with whatever dynamical changes are introduced.
But you're still going to be capturing the computations that
lead to the same behavior.
And so in some sense, if you can't tell the difference
right away, and what you're trying to do
is not to be able to tell the difference to your model,
then it doesn't matter if those changes are introduced.
But there is definitely a risk that some of the behaviors
drop away.
For instance, with the voltage sensor, as I said,
it's originally a proton pump.
But if you put a proton pump into a neuron,
you're not going to get any spontaneous activity
because it'll just depolarize.
It'll hyperpolarize all the time,
or all the time that that channel's being activated.
And since it's supposed to be a passive sensor,
that's not good.
So it's critical that this sort of performs
as advertised by the people who engineered it,
that it doesn't perturb the neuron.
But if it does, you're going to know.
And it's not going to do the things
that the worm will do the thing it's supposed to do.
Yeah.
Do you think that worm being able to just be
a collection of it do sort of roles,
or will be a bit more unpredictable than that?
So I think my intuition from what I've observed so far
is that it's a collection of largely autonomous local control
loops with some long distance modulatory connections that
are usually not active except in exceptional conditions.
So you're going to have in each body segment
just a tiny control loop.
In fact, there's some evidence that the control loop consists
of one cell that just happens to synapse onto muscle
and also be a sensory neuron that basically says,
if the body segment ahead of me is stretching this way,
then about 50 milliseconds later,
then I should stretch that way too.
And so this sort of propagates the undulating wave.
There isn't a pattern generator, for instance,
like you would see in higher organism, that sort of says,
OK, you, you, you, you.
They sort of coordinate with each other.
And then when something goes wrong,
then there's other connections that
seem to get brought into the loop
and modulate those typically autonomous systems.
But I don't know.
I expect that many surprises await in the full model.
Yeah.
What do you think about the current efforts
directly to the connectome of, say, a mouse?
Do you think it's possible that these projects will
succeed without insight?
Without?
I think that it's possible that they will succeed and not
provide any insight, if that's what you mean.
It's certainly physically possible
if you had enough time and resources
to do electron micrographs of an entire mouse brain.
I mean, it's not that far off if you had, say,
$80 million, you could just do it.
It just takes a lot of microscopes and a lot of time.
So it's not actually a very high-risk project in that sense.
But it's also not really that much of a high-reward project,
because no one knows what to do with that data.
Like the most advanced, I actually
did lab rotation with Jeff Lichtman, who
did the connectome project.
And what they're looking at right now
is they're looking at, well, when axons synapse
onto dendrites, are they choosing which dendrite
to synapse onto randomly or not?
And that's a sort of analysis that you can do on that data.
And it seems pretty obvious that they're not random.
And there's some sort of pattern to how
things connect in the brain.
I think that's intuitively clear.
But there is still also this community of people
out there who say, no, you know what?
We've done neural networks with random connections.
They seem to be pretty clever.
They're just as clever as the neural networks
we've built with carefully designed connections.
So there's no real reason that the brain
needs to have specific patterns of connection.
And nature is always parsimonious and efficient.
So it's probably random.
And so this is the sorts of stuff
that you see in connectomics.
And it's not exactly what I'm interested in.
What sorts of inputs and outputs does the worm have?
You mentioned muscles and things.
Yes.
So the outputs that we can observe
are pretty much all muscles.
There are body wall muscles.
There are egg-laying muscles.
There are anal muscles.
There are head muscles.
And then the inputs, there's a few light-sensitive neurons.
So it can do sort of a, it's actually
very much like a QAPD, which is the sensor that
was put on top of early heat-seeking missiles.
So it has just enough information
that it can navigate toward light or away from light.
It has a large variety of chemical sensors,
or basically odor sensors.
So that's how it finds food.
It also has chemo sensors that aren't classified
as odor sensors, like carbon dioxide sensors.
So if there's too much carbon dioxide,
it goes away from there.
It has touch sensors.
So if you poke it, it goes away.
I'm trying to think some of the other sensors.
It's mostly odor, definitely, by cell count.
Odor, touch, and light.
I think that's about it.
So in the simulation, do you intend
to just stimulate the inputs and try
to get some expected outputs, or even
improve for us all possible narrow states for the worm?
So it's 302 neurons.
So if each neuron has, say, two states,
it's a lot.
It's a big number.
I'm not going to do that.
There's a hierarchy of different sorts
of levels of data-collecting pain.
And that's the top of it.
Well, actually, the top of it is that the state of each neuron
is a real number.
And you have to sample a vector field
to the precision of its curvature,
302-dimensional vector field.
And then it goes down from there to, at the very bottom,
you just start saying, OK, each of the neurons
is a linear function of the other neurons.
And we just have to put together a 302-by-302 matrix
of synaptic weights.
And in fact, it's known that there's
only about 7,000 synapses.
So you can zero most of that out right away.
And there's only 7,000 numbers you need.
That's sort of the hyper-optimistic point
of view, which is kind of what I thought going into this.
It's probably more complicated than that.
But I think there's at least some separability where
you can say the synapses and global peptide diffusion
are basically the only ways that you
can have an impact of one neuron on another.
And you can do some sorts of things from genetics
just to say, well, here are the channels that are in there.
You aren't going to have anything
that can't be explained in terms of a potassium
current and a sodium current and a calcium current.
And so there's definitely prior information
that you can put into it from the connectome
and from genetics.
And you can even go so far, and people
have, as to put in prior information from what
you would like to get out of it.
You say, well, I want to evolve the synaptic weights
toward something that exhibits this type of undulation.
And lo and behold, it exhibits that type of undulation.
But then you don't know whether it correlates to reality
or not.
But if you have an instrument where you can check,
does this correlate to reality?
Then you can still use those sorts of approaches
as shortcuts through the sort of state space
of possible neural networks.
Yes?
What's the life cycle of a worm like?
How long does it take to create a worm that has been in that?
It's wonderful.
The life cycle is four days.
Yeah, it's very convenient.
And it's a self-fertilizing hermaphrodite, too.
So it clones by itself.
It's pretty good.
It's also the only organism that cryogenics
has proven to work on.
You can put worms into liquid nitrogen.
20 years later, you can thaw them out
and they start crawling around.
Yeah?
You said that we hope that the neurons have basically
a binary state.
What's to say that they don't have 10 binary states
or something?
Yeah, no, I don't think they do have a binary state.
And I think it's sort of, again, in some ways,
it's not the right way to think about the problem
that the neuron has a state.
Because it seems like a lot of what's going on,
especially in C. elegans, because we're essentially
talking about analog computation because there
aren't known to be spontaneous action potentials.
What you're really looking at is more like a control system.
And so some input, for instance, there's
a paper just published this month
that showed that certain networks in C. elegans
are there to compute time derivatives.
And I believe that that's just a functional block of a PID
controller.
Then we're going to find the integral part
and then something that linearly sums them and then feeds back.
So I think it's not really so much about finding
the set of states and then saying, hey, for this state,
you go to there, in the sense of sort of an if-do rule.
Because I think that it's a lot simpler than that.
In that, there are just simple equations
that govern most of the processes
and how they relate to each other and to the environment.
That's my hope.
The adults can grow to be about 700 or 800 microns long
and about the diameter of a hair, about 50 to 100 microns
in diameter, depending on stage.
And they're transparent, so they're
challenging to spot with the naked eye,
but you can in the right lighting conditions.
Yeah?
I remember in the first days, Brenner actually
read small ones.
And for example, I think the nervous system and the gut
are separate pretty much.
And with selective reading, he found
some where they were in the same plane
and half the length and so forth.
And the purpose of all that was so
that he could get a whole more into the target
of his electron microscope.
So that way, he had similar pictures of the whole thing.
I see.
It sounds like they don't have to do that anymore,
but it was an interesting case where
they controlled the evolution of this piece to be easier
to study.
And that's not a bad idea.
No, it's not.
I don't know if they reduced the number of neurons by accident.
Yeah?
What percentage of the separate do you
think is going to be devoted to combining all of these tools?
And what percentage do you think is
going to be running the aggregate to learn something?
I think once everything works, the process of taking AWIRM
and scanning it in will only take a couple of hours.
So 99.99% building the tools.
Because really, that's about how long
you have before these sorts of the dyes get photo bleached
and the laser power starts to heat things up
uncomfortably for the worm.
And then you're studying a different system.
Yeah?
What's this research?
Larry Page.
Personally, or?
Yes.
Yeah, the NIH isn't a big fan.
Although, there was a faculty member
who put in a valiant application.
He managed to tie this research in plausible ways
to cure for Parkinson's, which I was really impressed by.
But the NIH was not so impressed.
Did you guys apply to a grant from Larry?
Or did someone talk to him?
It was his idea, actually.
Well, I mean, he wasn't the first person to have the idea.
And in fact, he wasn't even the first person to tell me about it.
He was the third person to tell me about it.
But when he told me about it, I listened.
And then when I decided that I was going to do it, I said, well,
not to him, obviously.
I went through my network of many people
and eventually got a message through that I
wanted to do this for real.
And could he spare 0.0001% of his fortune to make it happen?
And yes.
So how far along are you?
How many worms do you have?
So it's not anyone's number one priority
to make these genes.
Again, because all the people who
have the skills to make the genes and breed the worms
to express them are naturally biologists who
have this bias towards, no, no, we want to do small systems.
And so I have to figure out how to do it myself.
And not having any background in biology most of my time
lately has been spent taking classes in biology.
But I've also been working on some
of the computational tools that we'll need.
For instance, when you have a worm
in this sort of wobbly conformation,
and it's changing, obviously, as it behaves,
you need to find the neurons and track them
at rates of at least 100 hertz in order
to keep your lasers pointed in the right place.
And so I've been working on that.
And I have some pretty good algorithms for that,
as well as isolating the signals.
And basically, when you're imaging something
in confocal mode, which is going to be the first thing that we
do, which is a lot cheaper than two photon,
you have to separate neurons that are on top of each other.
They have different signals.
And the way that I'm doing it is to say
each pixel is some roughly linear function
of some set of the neurons that are near that pixel in three
space.
And you can actually just use a singular value decomposition
followed by some simple heuristics derived
from Microsoft Paint to say here's where you just fit.
Literally, you flood fill in where the neurons are.
And it works incredibly well.
Yeah?
So if you had a multiple state process or something,
not just that you wanted to look at in the worm,
something like if you wanted to look at all the neurons
as it's producing a new clone or something,
like that multiple step, would you be able to?
Sorry, what do you mean by multiple state?
Yeah, instead of a stimulus and response,
instead of a stimulus and response sort of thing
if you wanted to measure something
about a process that took longer.
Oh, yeah.
So the nice thing about having control over all of the neurons
is that you can also control the sensory neurons
and thereby put the worm into the matrix.
And you can make it experience whatever you want in principle.
This has been done with zebrafish.
So the way that you do this is you use a myotoxin
to prevent any of the muscles from contracting.
And so then you have a perfectly still paralyzed animal.
And then you can feed it whatever sensory stimuli you want.
You can read out the motor stimuli and motor responses.
You can feed that back into your simulation.
It's exactly the matrix.
And then the animal is convinced that it's
in this environment that doesn't exist.
Yeah?
One thing that I don't perhaps understand
is that it's not picking up on the details here.
But one thing I don't understand is
how much of the state would the worm, so it's 300 neurons,
how much of the state do you have knowledge of
with that particular time?
Is it all those neurons?
So again, you can measure the way
that it works if you have one pair of lasers.
You can measure any neuron at any time.
And the measurement process takes about a few milliseconds.
And the time constant of these neurons
is on the order of 40 or 50 milliseconds.
So you have to be a little bit smart about which neurons
you want to look at and when.
So in that sense, you can't look at all of them simultaneously
unless you have more lasers.
Again, more lasers solve everything.
So you can look at calcium.
You can look at voltage.
And you can't do those at the same time either.
You have to say, OK, I'm going to read the voltage of this.
I'm going to read the calcium of that.
And there's actually a theory called optimal exploration
of dynamic environments, which was also just published
this year, about a way to algorithmically make
that decision of what thing do I want
to look at that is most likely to lead in the long term
to gaining the most information about the system,
given my expectations of what it might look like.
And then conversely, how much of a staking in fat is it?
And it's the same.
You can perturb, either stimulate or inhibit
any neuron at any time to any intensity.
So you have a little bit more control there.
But again, you do have to multiplex.
And you have to take advantage of the fact
that the neurons are not going to react as quickly as you can.
So how much of a staking do you think you can support?
You're basically just looking at two numbers.
But you can look at those numbers anywhere in the cell.
So you don't have to assume that the cell is isopotential,
although it probably is for most of the neurons,
not for the ones that run the whole length of the worm.
But there aren't as many of those.
So you can collect, in some sense, as many numbers
as you want if you're interested in looking
at all of the gridding a particular neuron
to a lot of different locations.
And you don't care about looking at anything else.
But you are only going to be looking at calcium or voltage,
at least with the proposal that I've got here.
There are other genetically encoded sensors.
But as far as I know, none of them
are likely to be nearly as relevant to neural activity.
At the same time, again, you're not
getting what's going on in the synapses.
You're not getting phosphorylation.
You're not getting methylation.
And all of those things are certainly
important for learning and plasticity.
But since C. elegans doesn't have that much of it,
it might be OK.
So you haven't got a complete state transition
diagram of the dynamics of that?
Right.
Yeah, like I said, a complete transition diagram
would take years to construct in the life cycle of four days.
It's not going to work.
Yeah.
Just wondering about your thoughts about higher level
questions.
For example, if you look at a neurology book,
it will explain on the basis of what happens when
people get a concussion that short-term memory
is restoring hippocampus or amygdala, or yeah, something.
And they can last there for 20 minutes or so.
And then over the next day, a memory trace
is copied into some other part of the brain,
like parietal lobe or parietal lobe or something.
And I've never seen even a paragraph
about, well, how does it figure out where to put a memory
and how the memory is represented?
So a nice question would be if you take something
like the idea of K lines, the kind of methods
you're describing might be nice for that
because the usefulness of the K line
might be that it's a bunch of neurons which
go several centimeters.
And so if you could look at neurons in 100 places
a centimeter apart, which is very low resolution,
then you might be able to find evidence
for correlated activities related to some stimulus
or whatever.
So some of these techniques might
work on a much larger brain just because you
increase in size is liberating.
It means that the instrumentation
can be closer if it's looking at all lentils and fibers.
Right.
Yeah, that's what Ed Boyden is starting to look at now.
Basically, I think he's calling it optodes.
I'm not sure if he coined that phrase,
but the optical equivalent of sticking an electrode
into a brain is that.
Is he using humans or?
Well, personally, he's doing mice,
and he's working with people who do monkeys.
The problem with humans is.
Mice have a very nice paper-thin skull.
Yes.
Yeah, humans have a thick skull.
That's part of the issue.
But the bigger issue is that the only reason
that we get to stick electrodes in humans at all
is because it's an approved treatment for epilepsy.
Now, he's working on getting optodes approved
as a treatment for blindness, which
is kind of an obvious thing.
If you can use an adenovirus to express opsins in an eye,
that doesn't have them.
It probably doesn't affect that many people.
Most blindness is caused by other things.
But for those that do, it's a very obvious intervention.
Then also PTSD and other sorts of diseases.
So as soon as it gets approved to treat
any sort of disease, then you can piggyback on that
to do human research.
But that hasn't happened yet.
In the early 60s, there were some successful experiments.
There's a guy named Ridley, who I'm not
sure what his profession was.
But he made some of the first electrodes.
And he actually got permission from his secretary,
who was blind, to put a little plate with 64 electrodes
on her occipital bone and put a little currency.
And she could recognize visible patterns.
Each of these electrodes he described
as being a little bar, which was about half a toothpick
in arm's length.
And of the 64 electrodes, about 30 of them
actually produced these, and the others didn't work.
So he did that, and then he removed them,
because it was a pretty risky thing to do anyway.
And at the time, we had a great neuroscientist here
named Warren Cullock.
And he got Ridley to come over and talk to us.
Incidentally, Ridley later discovered
the use of nitrous oxide for producing erections
in human nails.
And he gave a demonstration of that in a famous lecture.
So at the time, Cullock said, if you're
interested in stimulating vision in the human brain,
you better do it in the next five years, or you'll leave them.
That was in the early 1960s.
And this was the same time that the worm was at Renner's.
And we actually thought about that and decided not to.
But anyway, it would be nice if we could get back to that.
And it might be that low resolution things distributed
very widely would also give a lot of new information.
Yeah, I think there's a lot of promise in MEG, especially
because when you're just putting things
on the surface of the head, there aren't issues.
It's not surgery.
Even if you're performing the same effective perturbation
to the neurons.
And what people are doing with transcranial magnetic
stimulation is not that great, but it's certainly promising.
And there might be some way of getting things
into cells that actually synthesize proteins,
encoding data, and breaking out the bloodstream later.
Yeah, although there is a group working on that.
They're calling it the Molecular Ticker Tape,
where you basically, it's complicated.
I don't think I can explain it properly.
But there are a lot of people who
are looking for problems to match the solution of high
throughput sequencing.
You can take huge amounts of DNA and sequence it cheaply now.
And that's one of those.
But it would take a pretty heroic effort
to then correlate those with the actual experiment
that you performed after you've extracted them.
And you have to say where they came from
and how long they took.
Right, and I asked them, how do you
identify the barcode, the cell?
I'm like, well, we don't know.
We'll figure that out eventually.
Danny Hillis and I once consulted for Schlumberger,
who made instrumentations for oil wells.
And when they have a deep oil well,
there's a pipe that's a couple of miles longer than you
could imagine.
And they get one bit out every five or 10 seconds
by putting pressure pulses in.
And we designed hideously elaborate things
that would punch tape, and they would come floating up
a few days later.
And despite going to the meetings
where the geologists explained why each of them would work.
Any other questions?
They don't have to be about neuroscience.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, go ahead.
Oh, I was going to say, you focused
on the experimental side, reading out from the work.
At some point, you want all of that data
to drive a computational model.
Can you build a computational model now
and initialize it in various ways
and look for any kind of behavior at all?
Or do you absolutely need this biological input
to begin to drive the computational system?
I think I'm working on some leads
for building computational models.
The obvious things to do have already
been done in that department.
Like I said, using genetic algorithms
to find parameters that satisfy certain conditions.
And it doesn't seem that enlightening.
So I haven't pursued it too much.
But I'm looking at, and this is actually
another actually really interesting to me connection
in terms of AI and neuroscience, is
that when I'm looking at building
the computational model that tries to interpret this data,
the key idea that keeps coming back is critics and selectors.
Because you need to have some set of possibilities.
And you need to have some heuristics for determining,
based on what data is streaming in, what sort of model
seems to apply to it.
And then you need to have a meta model where
you need to build layers of reflection.
And you're saying, well, we need to modify this in this way.
And it's not easy to implement that from scratch.
So I'm thinking about it.
But I think that once we have real data,
it'll be more clear what needs to be
done to simulate the processes underlying it.
And again, it's just sort of my hope
that observing something that has not
been observed before, that some insight will
come out of that process.
Is there a behavioral diagram somewhere?
For example, if you feed it a lot of food,
presumably it will stop eating.
Right.
Yeah, no.
I don't remember the name of the fellow
you mentioned who spent years studying seagulls, but.
Tinbergen.
Tinbergen, right.
There isn't a tinbergen of worms, unfortunately.
All of the studies are, again, it's
this very, very stamp-collecting approach,
where you're saying, OK, at 24.6 degrees Celsius with OP20
growth media and with worms that are three days into their life
and this number of worms per this area of plate
with this brand of agar, here are the behaviors
that we see in response to this stimulus
with this number of milliseconds between repetitions and so on.
And no one goes so far as to make a plot with more than one
variable, because goodness, what's your control?
And it is a little bit frustrating
that we're going to have to build those sorts of things
ourselves, but hopefully that will
be the less hard part in building the model.
Yeah.
Could you just make some thoughts about the way
mathematics might relate to, I mean,
you said you were interested in the next subject.
Sure, might relate to?
Well, some of the theories are similar.
I think, as I said, I think there's something
missing in mathematics.
There's some sort of theory that follows
from some sort of symmetry that shows up in nervous systems
and not in many other places and maybe shows up in societies
as well, but I'm not certain of that.
But as far as math that we know, certainly
nonlinear dynamical systems is the obvious one,
because a neuron is a nonlinear dynamical system.
And I think that in simple animals, especially
in C. elegans, most of the computations that we see
are also nonlinear dynamical systems.
As I said, they're integrators or they're
derivatives and things of that nature.
And I think a lot of them will turn out
to be amenable to analysis as differential equation systems.
But at the same time, I think figuring out certainly
more complex organisms will require
a new way of thinking about how to put together a computation.
Von Neumann in 1956 started working on a monograph
to accompany a series of lectures called
The Computer and the Brain, in which he would discuss
the differences and similarities and how
he thinks that ideas from computer science
will relate to neuroscience.
And this was 1956.
And unfortunately, he got bone cancer.
He died in 1957 and left the document unfinished
and never gave the lectures.
And the document concludes very dramatically
with this sentence, however, if the brain uses
any sort of mathematics, the language of that mathematics
must certainly be different from that
which we explicitly and consciously
refer to by that name today.
And that's where it ends.
Yeah.
Do you have an idol?
What?
Do you have an idol, like fictional or non-fictional?
Von Neumann would be the closest, yeah.
I mean Iron Man, but that's just obvious.
So you're over Edison.
What?
You're over Edison.
Over Edison.
No, Edison's pretty cool, too.
Von Neumann was my hero, because when I finished my thesis,
the math department was on neural networks.
And the math department didn't know what to make of it.
So they came to Von Neumann.
Did I tell you this story?
No.
I said, is this mathematics?
And he said, if it isn't now, it's soon will be.
And I got my PhD.
Can you talk about any of the projects before yours,
whether people have already used these tools?
Yeah.
So let's see.
In terms of optogenetics, I don't know.
There's the one, I think probably the most famous one,
just because it has a really cool movie,
is that someone found a promoter for a class of neurons in mice
that is coupled to right turns.
And so you can put the mouse in some environment,
and it behaves.
You turn the light, and it starts turning to the right,
no matter what it's doing.
And it just turns around and starts going in circles.
And you turn off the light, and it goes back
to what it was doing.
It's mostly cool stuff like that.
But it's also found use as a replacement
for electrophysiology.
Anything that you could do by using micro pipettes
or microelectrodes, well, to some extent,
depending on what kind of time resolution you need
or what kind of manipulations you want to perform.
But a lot of the things that you previously
would need very precise and expensive equipment
and calibration for, you can now do much more simply
by using genetics and a blue LED.
So there's a lot of things like, for instance,
even in C. elegans, a lot of work
has been done by Cory Bargman in recent years
using calcium imaging to just sort of explore
more quickly and more thoroughly
the dynamics of sensory neurons,
which is important to me because if I'm going to simulate
the sensory neurons in some pattern that
reflects a virtual reality, then I need to know
how that pattern would relate to the real reality
that they're observing.
And so Cory Bargman has done a lot of experiments
where she just sort of flows in an odorant, for instance,
and she's got a laser pointed at the neuron
that's known to sense that odorant
and just characterizing the dynamics of how
the neuron responds and habituates,
which is something that you could do with a micropipette,
but the worm is so small that you need,
it's just really hard to get something in there
onto the specific neuron that you want and have it stick.
And it's been done, but it's only been done a few times
by people who are very skilled and very lucky.
And these types of optical tools make it a lot easier
to do those sorts of experiments, if nothing else.
So you can't change anything about the worm
once it's already in there.
Once it's already under the lasers,
you can't add more stuff.
But why would you want to?
Well, I mean, there are reasons that you might want to.
A lot of experiments are done.
It's actually really creative what a lot of cellular neuroscientists
do, because they realize that once you have something
stuck into the cell body of a neuron,
you can introduce whatever kinds of molecules you want.
And there are certain molecules that are selective blockers
of certain channels.
And so you can do things like, OK, what if you don't have
any potassium channels? What now?
And you can do those sorts of perturbations when you have
a physical connection to the cytosol,
which you can't do optically.
So those, again, are things that I hope to show,
but it is not known, that you don't need to do them
in order to model behavior at the scale of the organism.
Yeah?
Does the worm have any chemical amplifiers
that are controlled by physical organs?
In humans, there are different glands.
Yeah, so there aren't really glands in C. elegans,
but there are.
There isn't a circulatory system either,
but there's sort of like a shared body of fluid
through which waste is channeled that contacts a lot of cells.
And there's some evidence that there are a few neurons
that do diffuse transmitter into that,
thus affecting a sort of global change in excitability.
So yes, the way that that manifests in a model
is basically just as an extra node,
saying this represents the sort of global concentration
of glutamate or whatever.
Thank you.
What's the simplest animal that does a little bit of learning?
The C. elegans does a little bit.
I mean, it's really just associative learning,
so you can learn inversions or attractions to temperature
or to chemical stimuli.
But it's probably just one synapse
that represents an aversion to this thing
that synapse changes in strength or something like that.
As far as I know, and I'm not a zoologist,
so I really don't know.
But as far as sort of the set of classic neuroscientific model
organisms, I think zebrafish are the simplest
that show abstract, anything resembling abstract learning.
I just realized that I think probably we all know something
about our ancestry that is the sort of 100 million years
of being bacteria and things like that.
And if you go backwards, there have
been mammals for about 100 million years, I think.
There's 100 million years of fish
and 100 million years of amphibians
and 100 million years of those are all vertebrates of mammals,
reptiles, and so forth.
And I don't know what happens in the early period,
except that we're descended from yeast somehow.
And so it'd be nice to know what are the first few steps up
to the worm and where did it branch?
And are we in that lineage, or did that lead off
to the solenterites and other things
that we don't have any horizontal relation?
Anybody know?
I'm pretty sure that we're not descended from sea elegans.
I think that is a separate branch from the vertebrates.
But there must have been something like a paramecium.
Right.
So there's actually a really interesting work
in looking at yeast that flock.
There's typically yeast, sort of wild type yeast,
when it reproduces, the daughter cell sort of diffuses away.
But you can get yeast to adhere to itself.
So as it reproduces, it forms these globs.
And it's actually been shown that under certain environmental conditions
that are not that implausible,
that those globs are more Darwinian fitness than individuals.
And so there's a hypothesis that that's how yeast
started to become multicellular.
So they must have some extra genes that are not activated normally.
I wonder why it isn't taught in grade school.
Is that because evolution is not allowed in?
But I came from New York.
There weren't many anti-evolutionists yet.
Maybe there were.
Well, I'm impressed.
I think that sounds like a very exciting adventure.
Do any of you have a plan to pursue AI or psychology?
Who has a career plan?
I don't remember ever having one.
There was just something exciting to do next week.
Anyone have a criticism?
Should David actually do this?
Well, biology is slow.
And computers are fast and they get faster.
I think that if someone were to put as much work
as David is putting into the biological aspect of this
to try to brute force a model of the world faster than he could
and try to match it up with behaviors,
they would match up those 30 behaviors faster than he could.
I would love a competition.
I would just like to point out that lasers are also fast.
Well, there's something wonderful about an animal
that can reproduce in four days because you could actually,
as part of your four years plan, you could actually plan to breed
some that have some particular new neurological behavior
on the side.
Is there any kind of social behavior that's documented?
Or is there a small animal that you would,
with social behaviors that you could study on this?
Like interaction between...
Yeah, yeah, I know what you mean.
And C. elegans doesn't, well actually it's kind of funny
because the hermaphrodite doesn't have any social behavior,
but the male does for obvious reasons.
There's in fact 70 extra neurons in the male
for the purposes of finding the hermaphrodite to it.
But I don't know, again, not being a zoologist,
I walked onto this because it's well studied
and it's the very simplest.
But questions in the form,
what's the simplest under constraint X?
I'm less well equipped to answer.
As far as I know, the best thing in that domain would be ants,
but I'm sure there's something simpler than ants
that exhibit social behavior.
I just don't know why.
Well, isn't there some yeast that forms a...
At some stage it actually forms a sort of tower
and stands up.
I think it's yeast.
Yeast don't have neurons,
so these sorts of techniques won't apply there.
Slime mold?
Yeah, maybe that's the thing.
Yeah, slime molds are interesting
because they're sort of all neuron in a way.
They're just clumps of cells
that happen to have electrical activity.
There might be something interesting there.
I don't know if anyone's tried to express
optogenetic channels in slime molds.
They're very small.
But you can do it with a virus, maybe.
Well, what about at a higher level?
How would you find something like K-lines?
I think that you need some way of seeing
a lot more things in a lot bigger membrane.
The one thing that comes to mind
as sort of a new technique that might turn up K-lines
is diffusion tensor imaging,
which is a way of using MRI
to find quite detailed structure.
I don't know the physics of it,
but it involves following water molecules
as they diffuse or tracking their flow.
So if something is more active, the diffusion is faster?
No, it's not functional. It's structural.
It's that if there's a bundle of neurons,
then the diffusion will be highly anisotropic.
And you can measure the anisotropy.
And you can use some tensor math
to turn that into what's called a tractogram.
But you're measuring the heat flow or something?
It's MRI. It's magnetic resonance imaging.
So it has some sort of tomographic component.
And again, I don't know the physics of that.
I just, in fact, heard of it a few weeks ago.
It's a new technique.
And it's been used to create some maps of the,
particularly, I think, in monkeys.
It's been used a lot to create maps
of at least the long-range connections
between a whole lot of different areas.
But even those that are,
it really can only resolve thick bundles of neurons.
And K-lines probably aren't.
But maybe they are.
I wonder how thin the skull of a parrot is.
I just mentioned it because it might be
the smartest animal per gram or something.
Well, how smart are mice?
Mice are pretty smart.
And octopodes are supposed to be pretty smart, too,
and I don't know how much they weigh.
Which thing?
I think they're pretty heavy.
Octopodes are heavy. That makes sense.
They're in water.
Right.
Because they're dense.
I think you'd probably find ants to be the smartest per gram.
But again, that's just my guess
based on what little I know of animals.
Parrots are always trying to optimize for weight,
and ants aren't.
Ants are pretty small.
Well, they're very variable.
I think Ed Wilson had a 26-year-old ant.
It would be glorious to see a large group of ants
acting as a parrot.
Yeah.
I just have a quick question for David.
You said, well, there was an experiment
that sort of showed that we could control mice
by shining lights on them.
Do you think that there's any fear
of the possibility that someone could create a virus
that affects all humans
and then controls humans
to do more than just turn right
by shining lasers at them?
Fear or hope?
What?
Fear or hope.
Technology is a double-edged sword.
Human skulls are pretty thick.
Even my skulls are pretty thick.
In order to make this happen,
you have to have a hole in the skull
and you have to mount your LED in that hole.
There isn't, so far,
any way to do this from a distance
without having some sort of
physical surgical operation.
Space is also far away.
If you're inside a building,
most important people are inside buildings
when they're making important decisions.
Right now, there isn't any fear of that,
but it's certainly
something to think about
as technology gets better.
You never know when we might cross that threshold,
but I think for the next 10 years or so,
we're probably pretty safe.
Well, there are microscopic parasitic worms.
It would be hard to direct them
to go anywhere particular,
but you could certainly evolve some
that go into the brain
and go somewhere without destroying
anything important
and drop little packages here and there.
There are actually
none that infect humans.
Actually, there is one that
infects humans
that has a more subtle effect,
but there's actually a whole class of parasites
which do locate
to the brain of larger animals
and do, in fact, cause them
to engage in behaviors that are
suicidal for the host,
but beneficial for the parasite.
That's right.
What's the one that causes some insect
to climb up
to the top of the tree?
I don't remember the name of it,
but it gets in the brain
and makes it climb the tree
and then jump off
or whatever,
and that spreads this particular parasite.
So don't go outdoors.
There's also, what is it,
Toxoplasma Gundi,
which was on crack.com,
which causes mice to enjoy the smell of cat urine.
So it would be interesting to develop
that for humans.
I think people can actually get it from cats or something.
Yeah, humans carry it,
and it does work.
I think that's the one I was thinking of.
It has a subtle effect on humans.
It's pretty benign on humans.
It's boring.
It isn't that bad.
Like it makes girls more
cute, is there something?
01:38:45,8
nant.
And so it's sometimes given to people
with severe alcoholism so that
they are repulsed by alcohol and don't drink it
anymore, as long as they continue taking
medication.
There's something like that in my family
because
if I
drink alcohol more than a
small amount, then
these little things like ants start crawling
on my face, and they're very
unpleasant.
Any of you have that?
I do.
A lot of Asians have it, actually.
Really?
Or maybe the one that I have is like
you
lack alcohol dehydrogenase,
the thing that breaks down alcohol, and you have
two copies of the gene. And I have like one
good copy and one bad copy,
depending on whether you find this good or bad.
And so I can drink like
a glass, but any more than that, like I kind of
get really itchy.
Uh-huh.
Yeah, so I don't
have any...
But the people who have
two copies where they
lack the enzyme, then like
if they have a sip, it's like
bad things happen.
Oh.
Well,
evolution produces
all sorts of strange things.
Neutral drift racing is still legal.
What?
What's that?
It's like an organism
that goes under neutral drift.
It's two organisms competing to not change.
Ha ha ha!
Yes, why hasn't the net
been destroyed by a
virus by now?
Is there any...
Why hasn't what been destroyed?
The internet.
Oh, because it has white blood cells.
The people, the people,
the system administrators act as white blood cells
in their...
Yes.
And it is largely...
Well, it is largely immunized,
but
it's still infected by parasites
like there are botnets the size
of which we can only estimate
that are sort of parasites
running on the internet.
Interestingly, you know, just behavior.
Yeah, I just find it
surprising that there hasn't
been a really large disaster yet
because...
Partially because it's not sanity,
right? It's not Ted Nelson's
super-sexualized internet.
It's a distributed
predominance.
There have been a few attacks that took down large parts of the internet,
but not quite predominantly.
Say it again?
There were a few attacks that took down large chunks of the internet
in the past.
Yes, I think Croatia's internet was
taken down by a woman with a spade
who was trying to mine some copper.
Oh, this looks like
a lot of copper, right?
Well, I had a
Microsoft virus for years, but
it never did
any harm.
It just... I forget what it was
called.
If I got rid of it, it would come back again.
People in Croatia
still had internet access, though.
They could connect via satellite.
So the internet now has
enough redundant methods of making
connections.
People who have satellite links rarely share them.
Yeah, I guess the thing is that
the initial statement is
why hasn't the internet gone down
where the internet is whatever
is still connected to anything else
since the internet is defined by its connections.
Well,
why hasn't there
been a
smallpox epidemic
that killed everyone?
Because that has happened for
quite a few species.
But all the species
that are currently alive cannot be killed by smallpox.
Right.
That is correct.
The anthropic argument
is always correct.
I'm never quite satisfied.
I heard an
hour-long program this morning about
what's his name
on WBUR
about
making high-speed trains in
California.
It was all very interesting
and incredibly expensive.
And I wonder
and the current plan
is to make one that will take 30 years
to construct which seems
having
that's
rather odd because you can't
expect any particular government
including California to be stable.
But I wonder what
the point of people
are people
really going to travel at great
expense and cost
when they could have telepresence.
Yeah, moving maps around is kind of a ridiculous
way to transfer the information
that's inside your brain.
And at some point we might just
say
shouldn't we ban international
travel?
Just because
of the danger of a plague.
And I think the danger of a plague
is going to suddenly increase because of
high school students doing
science fair projects.
Because
the nice thing
about evolution is it doesn't have
contrary to some beliefs
it doesn't have
any intentional
agents directing it.
But once you
once you can make
gene strings in
in high school then
Darwinian evolution becomes
a
a minority.
And
I assume you've heard the recent news of
Dutch biomedical
engineers who produced a version
of H1N1 with 60 percent
mortality.
Oh, and where does he keep it?
In his basement.
For science!
Did you make that up?
Well, I assume he did it for science.
I made up a tone of voice.
Was this a military run in project?
No, no, this was
at a hospital
research institute.
I mean, presumably
it was funded by someone who's
interested in
making a cure for H1N1.
And, you know, they're trying
to make it more obvious
when you have one
in your test population of
chinchillas or whatever their model
organism is.
Okay.
Well,
next time bring some questions.
Thank you.