The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
What do you think AI people should work on next?
You know what question I was going to ask you before you
said your question?
Oh, OK.
I was going to ask you, what kind of questions
do you think that AI people should be asking right now?
That's right.
Anybody have a meta question?
One good question is, I could focus it better,
but or make it bigger.
Is that enough layers?
It's possible that I got the idea from Sigmund Freud
that who knows what Sigmund Freud's three layers were?
Sure.
Ego, superego?
Right here.
Ego, superego.
Freud wrote about 30 books, I know,
because I had a graduate student once who
decided to quit computer science and go
into emergency medicine.
He had an MD, which he wasn't using,
and he suddenly got fed up with computer science.
So he sold me his set of Freud books, which
is, but in Freud's vision, these don't seem to be a stack,
but this thing, which is basic instincts,
I shouldn't say basic, maybe to a large extent built in.
And this is learned socially.
And I think the nice thing about Freud's concept, which
as far as I know doesn't appear much in earlier psychology,
is that these conflict.
And when a child grows up, a lot of what we call civilization
or socialization or whatever comes
from taking the built-in instincts, which
is, if you see something you like, take it,
and the social constraints that say you should negotiate.
And if you want something someone else has,
you should fool them into wanting to give it to you
or whatever.
So in fact, when I make this big stack of mechanisms,
that really, well, that's actually not the organization
that the book starts to develop chapter
by chapter, which was instincts, learned reactions, and so
forth up to self-conscious.
What's the next to top layer?
What?
I've forgotten.
Self-ideology.
Yeah, I guess so.
It's hard to tell.
The reason I had six layers is that,
unlike what people do when making theories in science,
is I assume that whatever ideas I have, they're not enough.
That is, instead of trying to reduce the mind to as few
mechanisms as possible, I think you want to leave room.
If your theory is to live for a few years,
you want to leave room for new ideas.
So the last three layers, beginning
with reflective thought and self-reflective and the ideals,
it's hard to imagine any clear boundaries.
And at some point, when you make your own theory,
maybe you can squeeze it into these extra boxes that I have.
A little later in the book, another hierarchy appears.
And this is imagining as a functional diagram
to show how knowledge or skills or abilities
or whatever you want to call them,
the things that people do, might be arranged.
And as far as I know, because virtually every psychologist
in the last 100 years has suffered from physics envy,
they want to make something like Newton's laws,
the result has been that, except for the work of people
like Newell and Simon and other pioneers
who started research in artificial intelligence,
you've heard me complain about neuroscientists.
But there's pretty much the same complaint
to be leveled against most cognitive scientists who,
for example, try to say maybe the entire human mind is
a collection of rules and if-then rules.
Well, in some sense, you could make anything out
of if-then rules.
But the chances are, if you tried
to make a learning machine that just
tried to add rules in some beautifully general fashion,
I suspect the chances are it would learn for a while
and then get stuck.
And indeed, that's what happened maybe five or six times
in the history of artificial intelligence.
Doug Lennat's system called AM, Automated Mathematician,
was a wonderful PhD thesis.
And it learned arithmetic completely by itself.
He just set up the thing biased so
that it would have some concept of numbers,
like six is the successor of five and stuff like that.
And it fooled around and discovered various regularities.
I think I mentioned it the other day.
It first developed a concept of number,
which wasn't very hard because he wrote the whole thing
in the AI language called Lisp.
How many of you know Lisp?
That's a lot.
In looking at the biographies of the late John McCarthy
all week, there were lots of attempts by the writers
to say what Lisp was.
The tragedy is you probably could have described it
exactly in a paragraph because it's
saying that each structure has two parts,
and each of those has two parts.
I don't remember seeing any attempt
to say something about this programming language in.
Yes?
How do you imagine the layers interact with each other?
Those?
Yeah, those and the six layers.
I think they're layers of organization.
Yes, because a trance frame is made of two frames.
But then if there were a neuroscientist who said,
oh, maybe when you see an apple and you're hungry,
you reach out and eat it.
You could think of that as a simple reflex.
If this, then that.
Or you could say, if I'm hungry now
and I want to be not hungry, what's a possible action
could I do?
And that action might be look for an apple or yes?
So I was teaching my class on the day
that McCarthy passed away, and then I was explaining.
And then I had some students in the class of learning,
computer scientists.
And so I was thinking about the same problem,
which is how do I explain what Lisp was.
So I said, well, before that, there
were languages like Fortran that manipulated numbers.
Lisp was the fourth first language to manipulate ideas.
Yes, it can manipulate representations of.
Yes, it's manipulating the ideas that are represented
by these expressions.
And one thing that interests me is
another analog between psychology
and modern cognitive psychology and computer science
or artificial intelligence is the idea of a goal where,
what does it mean to have a goal?
And you could say, it's a piece of machinery
which says that if there's a situation, what you have now,
and if you have a representation of some future thing,
what you want.
So of course, at any time you're in a situation
that your brain is somehow representing maybe
five or 10 ways, not just one.
But what does it mean to have a goal?
And what it means is to have two representations.
One is a representation you've made
of some structure which says what things are like now.
And the other is some representation
of what you want.
And I don't think I need that.
And the important thing is, what are the differences?
And instead of saying, what's the difference,
maybe it's good to say, what are the differences?
So what does it mean to have a goal?
It means to have some piece of machinery turned on.
You can imagine a goal that you don't have, right?
Like I can say, what's David's goal?
It's to get people to go to that meeting.
So what you want is to minimize the differences between what
you have and what you want.
And so there has to be a machinery which does what?
It picks out one of these differences
and tries to get rid of it.
And how can you get rid of it?
There's two ways.
The good way is to change the situation
so that difference disappears.
The other way is to say, oh, that would take a year.
I should give up that goal.
And I'm digressing.
So you want something that removes,
the feedback has to go this way.
Let's change the world and get rid of that difference.
So well, how do you get rid of a difference?
That depends on maybe you have a built-in reflex,
like if you have too much CO2 in your blood,
something senses it and tells you to breathe.
So you've got built-in things.
And the question is, how do you represent these sorts of things?
And in fact, I think I got a lot of this idea
from the PhD thesis of Patrick Winston, who
was here a minute ago.
But the question is, how do you represent what you want,
and how do you represent what you have?
And I think the big difference between people
and other primates and reptiles and amphibians, reptiles, fish,
and going back to plants and so forth
is that we have these very high-level, powerful waves
of representing differences between things.
And this enables us to develop reflexes for getting
rid of the differences.
So this is what I think might be a picture of how
the brain is organized.
And at every level, these things are made of neurons.
But you shouldn't be looking at the neurons individually
to see how the brain works.
It's like looking at a computer and saying,
oh, I understand that.
All I have to do is know a great deal about how
each transistor works.
The great thing about a computer is
that it doesn't matter how the transistor works.
The important thing is to recognize,
oh, look, they usually come in pairs, or really 4 or 10
or whatever, called a flip-flop.
And do you ever see a neuroscientist saying,
where are the flip-flops in this or that?
Very strange.
As though they're trying to develop
a very powerful computer without using any concepts
from computer science.
It's a marvelous phenomenon.
And you have to wonder, where did they grow up
and how did they stay isolated?
In biology departments, I think.
Biology departments.
Or psychology departments.
Well, I started out in biology pretty much.
And then I ran across these early papers, one of which
was by Letvin and McCulloch and Pitts and people like that.
In the early 1940s, the idea of symbolic neurons appeared.
It had first appeared in 1895 or so with the paper
that Sigmund Freud wrote, but couldn't get published.
I think I mentioned that, called Project
for a Scientific Psychology.
And it had the idea of neurons with various levels
of activation.
And sometimes you would have a pair of them,
and one would be inhibiting the other.
And so that could store some information.
And he's not very explicit about how these things might work.
But as far as I know, it's about the first attempt
to have a biological theory of information processing at all.
And he was unable to get it published.
Yeah?
Well, since McCarthy did this, just
do you have any summary reflections on the stuff
that he did or his contributions?
There are a lot of things that he did.
And I noticed that none of the obituaries
actually had any background.
What had happened is that Newell and Simon
had started to make, they had struggled
to make programs that could do symbolic logic.
And they made a language called IPL.
And IPL was a language of very microscopic operations,
like you have several registers, put a symbol in a register,
perhaps do a piece of arithmetic on two symbols
if they're numbers.
If not, link up.
You could sort of make registers artificially
in the memory of the computer.
And you could take two or three registers,
and it had instructions for making lists or trees.
So you could arrange these in a way that.
So here are the three things.
And this is just a simple list.
But I've drawn it as though these two
were subsidiary to that.
Of course, that depends on what program
is going to look at this.
And you could have a program which
can say, here are two arguments for a function.
And it doesn't matter what order they're in.
It just depends how you wrote the function.
So Newell and Simon had written a programming language which
said put something in a register,
link it to another register, and then perform
the usual arithmetic operations.
In fact, what they were doing is mostly
performing logical operations.
Because even the early computers had
ANDs and ORs and XORs and things like that.
So I'm trying to remember what they were using.
Oh, so Newell and Simon had written
a program that could deal with Boolean functions
and prove little theorems about not A or B is not A or not B.
Is that wrong?
I forget.
Should have more nots.
Anyway, they wrote this beautiful but clumsy thing
made of very simple logical primitives.
McCarthy, at the same time, IBM had spent 400 man years
writing a program called Fortran 1 or Fortran.
I'm not sure that people had serial numbers on programming
languages yet, because we're talking
about the middle 1950s.
And McCarthy had been thinking about how
would you make AI programs that could do symbolic reasoning.
And he was, indeed, particularly interested in logic.
Backtrack.
In fact, Newell and Simon had got their program
to find proofs of most of the theorems
in the first volume of Russell and Whitehead's Principia
Mathematica, which is a huge two-volume book from about 1905,
I think, which was the first successful attempt
to reduce mathematics to logic.
And they managed to get up to calculus
and show that differentiation and integration
can be expressed as logical functions of variables.
It's a great tour de force, because logic itself
barely existed.
Boole and a few others, including Leibniz,
had invented Boolean algebra-like things.
And around Frege and others had got predicate calculus
with their exists and for all.
And that stuff was just appearing.
And Russell and Whitehead wrote this huge book,
which got all the way up to describing
continuous and differentiable functions and so forth.
The first volume was huge and just
did propositional calculus, which Aristotle
had done some of also.
And anyway, McCarthy looked at that and said,
why can't there be a functional language like Fortran that
can do symbolic reasoning?
And pretty much all by himself, he
got the basic ideas from Lisp.
They're built on the Newell and Simon experiment.
But he basically converted the symbolic system
into something like Fortran, which
was only able to manipulate numbers,
into Lisp, which was able to manipulate arbitrary symbols
in various ways.
And if you want to know more about that,
there's a great, you can find McCarthy's homepage
at Stanford just by, I think, if you Google search for McCarthy
and Sale, Sale is Stanford Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory.
And you'll get his homepage.
And there's a 1994 article about how he invented Lisp.
Yes?
Right after you started talking about Lisp, you jumped over
and you said, here's the now and the want,
which is the current state and the desired state.
And I think you were going for some kind of analogy
between the symbolic evaluation available in Lisp
and what conscious entities do.
However, one of the most beautiful things about Lisp
is the humoiconicity, the fact that you
have things such as macros.
What is there in the conscious entity that
is equivalent to the macro?
Macros?
Well, each of these levels is, each of these levels
are ways of combining things at the previous level.
So that the way I drew it, at the top,
there are stories where you, what's a story?
You mentioned some characters in a typical story.
Then you say, and here's a problem
these characters encountered.
And here's what Joe did to solve the problem.
But it didn't work.
And here are the bugs.
And the reason it didn't work is that Mary was in the way.
So he killed her.
And then blah, blah, blah.
So that's what stories are.
If you just write a series of sentences, it's not a story,
even though the New Yorker managed
to make those into stories for about a period of 20 years.
But a typical story introduces a scene.
And it introduces a problem.
And then it produces a solution.
But the solution has a bug.
And then the rest of it is how you get around that bug
and how you maybe change the goals in the worst case.
So a story is a series of incidents.
I wonder if I brought my death ray.
Looks like I didn't.
Oh, but you don't need it with this.
You have to be here.
Anyway, but what's a story made of?
Well, there are situations.
And you do something, and you get a new situation.
So what's that?
That's what this thing I call the trance frame, which
is a pair of situations.
And OK, so what's an individual situation?
Well, it's a big network of nodes and relationships.
And I'm not sure why I have semantic networks down here
rather than here.
Oh, well, a frame is a collection of representations
that's sort of stereotyped or canned that
might have a single word like, oh, just about any word
breaking something.
If I say, John broke the X, you immediately say, oh,
that's a trance frame.
Here's an object that had certain properties, parts
and relationships.
And it's been replaced by this thing, which
has most of the same objects except
but different relationships or one of the objects is missing.
And it's been replaced by another frame and so forth.
So one question is, what's the relation?
So this is a picture of cognitive representations.
Everything is made of little parts.
And in the society of mind, I described
the idea of k-lines, which is what's a k-line.
It's an imaginary structure in the nervous system, which
is there's really two kinds.
There's a sort of perceptual k-line,
which is something that recognizes that, say,
10 features of a situation are present.
And if these are all present, then
a certain bunch of neurons or neural activity goes on.
And on the other hand, when you think of something
like a word, suppose I say microphone,
then you're likely to think of something
that has a business and which collects sounds.
And it has a stand, or maybe it has a handle.
And if you're an engineer, you know
that probably it has a battery or a transmitter or a wire.
So those are the things that I call frames or k-lines, really.
And anyway, this chapter 8 of The Emotion Machine
talks about that.
And there's a lot of detail in the old book, The Society
of Mind, about what k-lines and things like that
could be made of.
Now, whatever those are, and as far as I know,
no matter how hard you look, you won't
find any published theories of what in the nervous system
is used to represent the things above that sort of midline
there of cortical columns.
I suspect that almost everything that the human brain does,
that fish and those lower animals or earlier animals,
I should say, I'm not sure that higher and lower
makes any sense, are probably symbolic processes
where it probably does more harm than good
to have elaborate theories of what's
the physiological chemistry of neurons.
But at some point, we want to know what, in fact,
the brain is made of.
The cortical column has a few hundred brain cells arranged.
And there are several projects around the world
trying to take electron microscopes
and pieces of mouse brain or cat brain
and make a huge connection matrix.
The problem is that the electron microscope,
even the electron microscope pictures still
aren't good enough to show you at each synapse what
is probably going on.
Eventually, people will get theories of that
and get slightly better instruments.
And I'm not sure that the present diagrams
that they're producing are going to be much used to anyone.
Yes, it's a nice question.
This question might be a little bit difficult.
So I'm going to start from the goal being a difference
between the now state and the desired state.
How do we reduce the difference?
Yeah, how do we get the difference?
So now I'm going to also take the fact of the animals
being different.
And I'd say that one of the biggest, big differences
is that we, as people, we cannot describe these differences.
It actually is only good for the recording.
OK, so we can describe these differences
and talk with them, talk about them with other people
without having to act on those goals or hypothetical goals.
So if everything that has to do with goals
is represented with a complex structure like this one,
and I want to implement it in a computer,
well, I can just, for every hypothetical case
that has to do with solving a certain problem,
I can just make more copies in the memory.
But if I have a human brain, then I
don't know how convenient it is to postulate
that there is a huge memory data bank where
you can make copies of everything that's going on.
Or if you have to assume some kind of a huge collection
of pointers and acting on those pointers.
So this is just a random point, and I'd
like to hear if you have any ideas on this.
That's an important question that we
know quite a bit about the functions
of some parts of the brain.
And so if you, I don't think I've ever
tried to draw a brain, but there's
a structure called the amygdala.
How do you spell it?
I believe that means almond-shaped.
Is that right?
Anybody have a Google handy?
And that's down here somewhere, and it has the property
that it contains the short-term memories.
So anything that's happened in the last couple of seconds
is somehow represented here in a transient way.
And everything that's happened in the last 20 minutes or so
leaves traces in the amygdala.
So that if somebody's in an automobile accident
or is knocked out by a real powerful boxing punch,
then when you wake up later, you can't
remember anything that happened in about 20 minutes or a half
hour before the trauma.
So that's a very good experiment to try.
And there's a lot of evidence that this
happens because the memories of the last half hour or so
are stored in the conjectures in a dynamic form.
Maybe there are huge numbers of loops
of neurons connected in circles or circle.
Anyway, nobody really knows, but if you
have a bunch of neurons connected in a big circle,
maybe 20 or 30 of them, then you can probably
put 10 or 20 bits of information in form
of different spaced pulses.
And a great mystery would be, how
does the brain manage to maintain
that particular pattern of pulses for 10 or 20 minutes?
Then no one knows where it goes after the 20 minutes.
But if a person gets enough sleep that night,
then it turns out that it's no longer in the amygdala,
and it's somewhere else in the brain.
So one question is, if there's all this stuff stored here,
and you might think of it as what's
happened in the primary memory, every computer
starts out with maybe just the first computers
had just two or three registers.
Then they got 16 and 32.
And I imagine, how many fast registers
are there in a modern computer?
I haven't been paying attention.
Maybe 64, maybe whatever.
Anyway, they're gone.
But the next day, if you've gotten some sleep,
you can retrieve them.
Somehow they're copied somewhere else.
As far as I know, there is no theory
of how the brain decides where to put them
and how it records it and so forth.
Something very strange about this big science lacking
theories, isn't there?
What would you do if you were in a profession where they're
talking about dozens and dozens of mechanisms which
clearly exist, and you say, how do you think that works?
And they say, well, I don't know.
None of my friends know either, so I guess it's OK.
So we don't know how it picks a place to put them.
And we don't know how, when you ask a question,
it gets back there so that you can reprocess it
and talk about it.
But anyway, so I made up these theories
that things are stored in the form of k lines.
And there's a lot of discussion in the society of mind
about how k lines probably have to work and so forth.
And if you look at the society of mind, in Amazon,
you'll find this enraging review by a neurologist named
Robert Restak, who says he introduces
these undefined terms called k lines and paradigms
and things like that, of which there's
whole chapters in the book.
So that's my favorite review of explaining
the problem of getting neuroscience to grow up.
Yes?
Who had a question?
So one thing that troubles me is how do you think brain
decides to do things?
How do they decide what to do?
Did you say?
Say you want to relate a story.
But hundreds of things happen.
How do you select what to tell and what not to?
It seems like you need some sort of intentionality behind it.
But how do we learn to do that in the first place?
When you describe a goal, you describe what's going on now
and what's the thing you want.
But then how do you decide which few things to be considered?
Oh, you're asking a wonderful question, which is, after all,
if I were to talk to you for an hour about your goals,
you could tell me hundreds of goals that you have.
So the question is, how do you pick the one
that you're thinking about now?
Yeah, also, how do you represent the priority of goals?
Because they're almost described as the difference
machines that's turned on all the time.
But how do you resolve conflicts?
How do you decide which one to go first
and which one gets first?
How do you represent the relations of your goals?
The standard theory for which there is no evidence
is that, in fact, you use the word hierarchy.
So if you ask a naive person, they'll
give you a pretty good theory.
Completely wrong, but good.
And the standard theory says, well, there's
one big goal at the top.
And you say, what is it?
And some people would say, well, maybe it's to reproduce.
Darwin could but didn't argue that.
Or to survive, or something like that.
So if you take that one, then it's
obvious what the next goals in the hierarchy would be.
I'm not saying this is how things work.
I don't think it does.
So there's food, and there's air.
Air gets very high priority.
If you put a pillow over somebody,
their first priority is to breathe,
and they don't even think about eating for a long time.
So that's very nice.
I don't know what comes after that.
If you're out in the cold freezing, then there's temp.
The nice thing about air and temp
is that if you have those goals, you
can satisfy them in parallel.
Because, in fact, you don't need much of a hierarchy.
The breathing thing has this servomechanism where
if there's a higher level of CO2 than normal in your blood,
then the, what is it, the vagus nerve, or I don't know.
They know a lot about which part of the brain gets excited
and raises your breathing rate, or your heartbeat rate,
or my favorite animal is the swordfish.
Because how many of you know about brown fat?
Brown fat is a particular thing found in vertebrates,
and it's fat.
It's brown, I guess.
And it has the property that it can be innervated by nerve
fibers, and they cause it to start burning calories.
And the swordfish is normally cold blooded,
but its carotid arteries have a big organ of brown fat
around them just as the blood comes into the brain.
And if you turn on the brown fat, it warms the brain,
and the IQ of the swordfish goes way up.
And it swims faster and uses better evasive tactics.
And I'm trying to remember, there
are a couple of other animals that
are known to, cold-blooded animals, that
are known to have a warm-blooded brain that they can.
Isn't that a great feature?
I wonder, does our brain do a little bit of that?
Oh, I got lost telling funny stories.
So anyway, this K-line idea is very simple.
It says that perhaps the way human memory works
is that here and there, you have big collections of nerve
fibers that go somewhere and go to lots of cells.
Let's say thousands of these cells,
and each one is connected to some particular combination.
Imagine there's 100 wires here, and each of these cells
is connected to, say, 10 of those wires.
Then how many different cells could
you have for remembering different features
of what's on this big bus bar?
How many ways are there picking 10 things out of 100?
It's about 100 to the 10th power.
So here's a simple kind of memory where you have,
of course, it'd be useless unless these bits by themselves
have some correlation with some useful concept.
And then at any particular time on this particular bunch
of fibers in the brain, maybe 20 of these are turned on.
And if something very important has happened,
you send a signal to all these cells
and say any of you cells who are seeing more than 10 or 15
of these 20 fibers at this moment should remember that
and set themselves to do something next time
you see that pattern, something like that.
Something has to decide which of these cells
is going to copy at this time and so forth.
So there's a theory of how memory, kind of symbolic memory,
might work in the brain.
And I got this idea from a paper.
I don't remember what their idea was,
but by David Waltz and Jordan Pollock.
Pollock is an AI theorist at Brandeis,
I guess, who in recent years has turned
into some kind of artist and makes
all sorts of beautiful things and simple robots
that do this and that.
David Waltz searched his web page
sometime because he was here for many years as a graduate
student and then developed beautiful theories of vision.
When did Dave move?
Do you remember, Pat?
Anyway, something like that.
But as far as I know, so I made up
this theory, which is really copied from Waltz and Pollock,
but simplified and neatened up.
And that became, then I went on and made other theories
based on that.
But without them, I would have been
stuck in some conditioned reflex theory for a long time,
I suspect.
A minute.
Yeah.
You mentioned the role that the amygdala plays
in storing the short-term memory.
And you mentioned that the memories that are stored in there
are wiped out.
Well, that's a question.
Presumably, as you grow up, your amygdala
gets better at learning what to recognize.
But I've never seen any discussion or theory
of how much of your short-term memory
is how do you learn and develop and get better
at remembering things that are worth remembering.
Sorry, go ahead.
My question is, I think, my understanding is that,
so whatever memories are stored in the amygdala during,
whatever stored in the amygdala is wiped out after you sleep.
What sort of implications does this
have about remembering dreams?
Because my understanding is that after you have a lucid dream,
you tend to forget the memories of the dream
are wiped out after a certain point later on in the day.
So what sort of implications does it
have on the ability of people to remember dreams that they have?
Good question.
There have been some theories, but I
think I mentioned Freud's theory, which is that you're not
remembering anything.
When you wake up, you make up the dream.
And I think that's surely completely wrong.
But Freud made it up because he was mad at Jung.
Jung had a theory that people have telepathic connections
with other people.
And so he had been Freud's student or disciple
for some years.
And then he went mystical, and Freud went up the wall
because Jung was obviously very smart and imaginative.
I'm trying to think of, I've had a very good student who
turned mystical, one or two, but not like that.
Anyway, that's a great question.
And when I said things hang around
in the amygdala for 20 minutes, that's just some things.
And clearly, they have to hang if it takes
sleep the next night, which is eight hours or 16 hours later
to solidify it or to copy it in some way
into the other parts of the brain.
It must still be in the amygdala or somewhere.
So in fact, maybe there's the amygdala
and some other parts of the brain
that haven't been identified that
contain slightly different copies of the memories
for a longer time and so forth.
So who knows where and how they work.
Maybe the language centers remember
paragraphs of things that you've heard or said for some time
and so forth.
I don't think anybody really knows much about,
they're very sure about the amygdala
because injuring the amygdala or injecting
novocaine into a blood vessel that goes there
has such a dramatic effect on.
You just can't remember anything for that short period
or half hour or so.
But there must be lots of other.
Maybe memories are stored in 10 different ways
in 10 different parts of the brain.
Who knows?
One problem that I think I mentioned
is that although a great deal has been learned about the brain
from modern scanning techniques, almost every result
that people talk about is obtained
by turning up the contrast so that most of the brain
is dark and nerve centers that are highly active
show up in your, you've all seen these pictures which
show three or four places in the brain lighting up.
Well, there's a good chance that for any particular event,
there might be 10 or 20 places that have just
increased a little bit.
And when they turn up the contrast,
all that evidence is lost because those regions all
become black or whatever.
Yeah, I'm not an expert on that, but I
would go as far as to say that probably if they have a finding
that where there are no specific areas,
so you have a pretty uniform picture of the changes
in metabolism, then you don't make theories
or you don't publish that result because you don't have
any clear areas where to point that.
And then nobody knows that, OK, that particular thing
was actually exciting for all of the brains.
That's just a guess.
Yeah, could be that some things involve
very large amounts of brain.
But I'm inclined to doubt it.
Probably you want to turn a lot of things
off most of the time so they don't fill up
with random garbage.
Who knows?
Yes?
I just want to follow up on that.
Why do you think the hierarchy of goals is naive?
And what specific features of goals
do you think that structure doesn't achieve?
I didn't finish that, did I?
She's asking.
I started to say, what's the hierarchy of goals?
But it looks like I got stuck on the well-defined instinctive
goals that you need to stay alive.
And I guess my answer is I don't have any good theories
of how you do that.
At any time when you're talking to somebody,
you usually have a couple of very clear goals
like, I want to explain this, I want this other person
to understand this for this reason, I'm having trouble.
Maybe I have to get his or her attention.
And then you get a subgoal of doing some social thing
to convince them to listen to you and all sorts of things.
But I just don't have a nice picture.
When you're writing an AI program,
you usually have goals and subgoals
in a very clear arrangement.
Like the theorem proving programs
are wonderful because you've proved some kind of expression,
but the particular theorem you are trying to prove
has another condition which is different from this condition.
And people have gone quite far in making
models of something like theorem proving
where the world is very simple.
If you're proving something in geometry or group theory
or a little fragment of mathematics,
then there are only five or 10 assumptions hanging around.
And so you could actually plan a little bit of exhaustive search
to go three or four levels.
And then you would do something like in a chess program
over time, discovering it never pays
to explore a tree that has this feature because of whatever.
Yes?
Are goals relevant?
Do we always have goals or is it just something related?
When I play chess, maybe I have a goal,
but why should I have a goal in life?
Why isn't that goal for a producer
created at some point of my life?
Why are goals important?
Well, the survival goals are important
because if you crossed a street without looking,
you could do that about 20 times before you're dead.
So why are there?
Well, if you don't make a living, you'll starve.
So now you have to, if you've committed yourself
to being a mathematician, now you
have to be a good mathematician or else you'll starve,
so forth.
I was a pretty good mathematician.
Only my goal is I had to be the best mathematician, so I quit.
You don't want to have a goal you can't achieve.
Yeah, but is that part of the intentions?
Well, a lot of people do have ones,
so it eats up a lot of their time, and they're wasting it.
I'm not sure what the question is.
How do you make a?
I think the feature of humans is that there's
sort of general purpose.
So there are a lot of things people do which are bad things
to do, and you can't justify them.
You could think of people as part of a huge search process,
and as a species or a genetic system,
it pays to have a few crazy ones every now and then
because if the environment suddenly changes,
maybe they'll be the only ones who survive.
William Calvin's question, how come people
evolved intelligence so rapidly in 5 million years?
And he attributes it partly to 10, 5,
how many periods of global cooling were there?
It's about six or seven ice ages in the last.
Anybody know the history of the Earth?
Anyway, some evidence, at least used to be,
I haven't paid any attention, is that the human population
has got down to maybe just tens of thousands
several times in the last million years.
And so only the really different ones managed to pull through.
Might be the ones who had all sorts of useless abilities.
Yes?
So you were talking about learning others.
The ones who ate the others, which would have
been punished before that.
Go ahead.
You were talking about representing
like the K lines and everything, like having some lines
and then activating some of these features.
So in the case of learning, would we
change some of these connections?
And if this is the case, how will this
affect the higher order, higher objects like frames
and everything?
Like if we change something that's
really the low level representation,
will this affect a lot, wouldn't the whole system
break because some subprocedure wouldn't
Oh, that's great.
That's another question I can't begin to answer.
Namely, when you learn something,
let's take the extreme form.
Do you start a new representation
or you modify an old one?
OK, that's a choice.
If you modify an old one, can you
do that without losing the previous version?
So for example, if I grow up monolingually, which I did,
so I learned English, and then I can't remember why,
but for some reason around fourth grade,
some teacher tried to teach us German.
And so for each German word, I tried very hard
to find the equivalent English word
and figure out how to move your mouth so that it comes out
German, which actually, for many words,
works fine because English is a mixture of German
and other things.
And for many words, it doesn't.
So that was a bad idea.
And if I had gotten very good at it,
I could have lost some English.
Anyway, that's a great set of questions.
When do you make new memories?
When do you modify old ones?
And the hard one is, if you can't modify an old one,
how do you make a copy that's different?
And there's a section called In Society of Mind
about how we do that in language by paraphrasing
what someone said.
Or you say something in your own head, and you misunderstand it.
I'm doing that all the time.
I say, such and such is this or that.
And then it's as though somebody else had said that,
and I have somebody say, no, that's wrong.
He meant this.
So when you're talking to yourself,
you're actually converting some mysterious inarticulate
representation to speech.
And then you're running it through your brain
and listening to it and converting the speech back
to a new representation.
So I think the wonderful thing about language
is it's not just for expressing.
It may be, how come the only animal that
thinks the way we do is the only animal that talks the way we
do?
Who knows?
Maybe whales, but nobody has decoded them,
do something like that.
But that's a question.
How do you copy a memory to make a new version?
And the answer is, you can ask anyone, and they'll say,
I don't know.
Why aren't there five theories of that?
Yeah.
I don't know if that's true, but I
believe there is kind of a sort of objective map
between words in language, like, for example,
non-nouns.
So for example, if I have a table,
I say like mesa in Portuguese.
There's sort of an objective map, even for colors,
which is sort of weird, because you're kind of dividing
all the colors into chunks of colors.
And even, I believe, for words, language that were not formed
with the same ancestry, I don't know.
For me, it seems that there's some sort of objective map
between words.
There are certain things that are just sort of naturally
more useful to talk about, and so a lot of languages
tend to have the words for the same thing,
like languages will have a word, and then it's a table.
But if there's some kind of path table,
something wrong with a path, and you say the word for table.
And regarding the colors thing, there have actually
been some interesting studies done on that.
They've done color survey, color naming survey,
with lots of languages in the world.
And it turns out that different languages,
partition the color space differently.
I was just going to ask if anybody knows.
They tend to do it similarly in the way
that people perceive colors.
The way that they divide up the space based on the number of words
that they have is actually like maximizing
the similarity of things with the same name
and the difference between things.
Yes.
But Dara Kowalczynski did some interesting studies on that.
I'm trying to remember when children use colors.
Let's see.
I had a daughter who have still, I might say.
And she suddenly started color words
and had six or seven of them in just a couple of days.
And she sort of got interested in that.
And so suddenly, I said, oh my gosh,
this is what Maria Montessori calls a,
I forget what she called it.
What's this moment when the child is open to being taught?
So I said, this is her chance to learn a lot of new color names.
So I said, and what about this?
I said, that's aqua.
And she said, that's blue green.
And I said, no, this is aqua.
And she refused.
So that was that.
So some months later, she learned some more color names,
but it wasn't the same.
When she was saying blue green, was that because somebody
had taught her blue green, or it was because she
was combining it through color?
I think she was combining it.
Do you remember?
Yeah, I think she was combining it.
She was combining blue and blue green.
So she had a concept that there were certain building
blocks of colors.
It looked like she wouldn't accept a new one.
And I always wondered if I was 15 minutes too late.
When does the Montessori door shut?
Sort of similarly, there are studies
done on different light-division points
on how well people distinguish different colors.
So in Russian, there's a different word
that means light blue and dark blue.
So Russians are better at distinguishing
different shades of blue than, say, Americans.
And there's also a lot of languages
that don't have distinct words for blue and green.
And native speakers of those languages
have trouble distinguishing blue and green.
That gives me a great idea.
If I could have found some unfamiliar objects
and colored them aqua, that might have fooled her.
There must be.
Is there a branch of psychology that worries about?
Because there must be names for sounds too.
And certainly, a lot's known about ages at which children
can't get new phonemes.
Yes?
Yeah, about storing memory and language.
So I'm bilingual.
Maybe other bilingual people in the audience
could confirm this.
I didn't know that.
What's your other language?
French.
For heaven's sake.
I've known Henry for 20-odd years.
So one thing that can happen is you
can be talking with another bilingual person.
So I can be talking with someone who also both
speaks French and English.
And then a week later, I'll remember every detail
about a complicated conversation.
We were working on this project, and we needed this,
and all this stuff.
I remember every detail except which language
we had the conversation.
My entire family is like, oh, we generally
speak a mix of Russian and English all the time.
So I can never remember even what language
I'm speaking at the time.
Yeah, that missupplies me.
Because if we started in a language,
how could I forget what language we used?
Well, I think there is a very simple answer to that one.
You have a language that's neither English or French,
and you just have a very simple tag going there.
And then you just, whenever you want
to express something in English or French,
you just encode, decode, encode whatever
is the word, those thoughts that you were having.
Well, that's the question.
Why is that a language, or do you have any thoughts on that?
I don't know.
It reminds me, I think I mentioned this,
but I was once at a meeting in Yerevan, Armenia,
and there was a translator who was practically real time.
And Francis Crick was talking, and at some point,
the translator switched, and he started
translating from English to English.
So Crick would say something, and the translator
would translate it into English very well, I thought.
It wasn't quite the same words.
And after a while, somebody asked him
why he was doing that, and he said
he didn't realize he had switched.
Do you think that could happen to you?
I suppose.
Yeah.
Do you think that there are other ways of transmitting ideas
and learning, maybe like arts or music, besides language
that can be really helpful?
I don't think there's anything nearly like language,
but art is pretty good, but it's so ambiguous.
Cartoons, they're awfully good.
How about plays?
What?
How about lisp?
Lisp.
All right.
Programming languages.
Yes, why is mathematics so hard?
I wonder if the habit of using a single letter for every
variable might make it easy and hard.
Who knows?
Yes?
You have great questions.
Last year, you mentioned that mathematics is hard.
I thought about it.
Say it again.
Last year, you mentioned that mathematics is hard.
And I thought about it, and I do feel
like there's an extreme lack of representations of ideas.
Solving a problem, we need to identify so many things.
And there's so many processes that you apply to them
without having a name for any of them for classification.
Well, you have induction and deduction.
That's about it, and contradiction.
Yes, and you have this one feature of mathematics
is completely un-redundant representations.
I wonder if there's some way to fix that or change it.
What other activity do we have where there's absolutely
no redundancy at all in a mathematical experience?
So for some people, it's delightful,
and other people, it's very hard.
I mentioned Licklider, who in programming,
he would have very long, variable names.
Sometimes they'd even be sentences,
like the register in which I put the result of.
And the great thing was you could read those programs.
They looked sort of stupid, but he didn't have to make it.
He didn't have to add.
What do you call notes?
He didn't have to have exclamation point.
This means that.
Comments, comments.
When I sit in algebraic topology class,
I just can't make myself accept the concepts
unless I can understand it algebraically
and in a geometric condition.
What kind of math do you like?
Do you do topology?
I like topology.
I love topology.
It was I once was tutoring a high school
student who couldn't do algebra.
I don't know if I mentioned this.
And it turned out he didn't know how to use parentheses.
So he would have an expression, stuff like that.
And but if there were something in there,
he didn't know what that meant because he knew sometimes
he would he didn't know how to match them.
So I couldn't figure out why.
And I asked, how come?
And he said, maybe I was sick the day
they explained parentheses.
And so I gave him little exercises
like make them into eggs.
And you see, if you make this into an egg,
then this egg won't work.
And the funny thing was he got that in five minutes.
And then he didn't have any trouble with algebra the rest.
Can you imagine?
I wonder.
I've never done much tutoring.
But if you can find the bug like that, it must be great fun.
But I bet it doesn't happen very often.
That was so funny.
I couldn't imagine not, you know.
So if you don't have language, there must be.
Well, why are some people so much better at math than others?
So it's just that they've not understood about five things.
I feel like they have a set of things
they know to go to when they face a problem.
Well, that's kind of similar to your Bayman story.
But I feel like they know exactly.
They have names for concepts of ways of solving problems.
So they look at a problem.
They're like, I'm going to try this approach.
And then if it doesn't work, I know this other approach.
I'll just try it.
Instead of looking at the problem and you think, OK,
so what possible thing, what possible method can I think of?
Oh, names for methods.
So do you have public names or are they secret names?
I feel like they're secret names.
They're just like the store.
Because they can't explain it to other people.
They can't be like, this problem, like, very few of them
can do this problem and that problem.
They generally have the general same method,
although they're very different.
I had a friend who was a composer.
And she had all sorts of sounds.
And they were filed away on tapes.
And the tapes had little symbols on them.
And if she needed a sound, she would go to the closet
and pull out the right tape.
And it had more symbols written on the reel.
And she'd get this thing, which might be a thunderstorm
or a bird or something.
So I asked her what was her notation for these sounds.
And she giggled and said, I can't tell you.
It's too embarrassing.
I never found out.
But she had developed some code for sounds.
Yeah.
So I would say that they have somewhat more representation
of things that math requires than all symbols or patterns
of solutions.
And their representation is optimal.
And if you're good at math, it doesn't
mean that you're good at playing music.
Because when you play music well,
you have maybe a good representation of the sounds.
And so it's just being optimal and representative of things.
I agree.
And so you can access, like, oh, so I
have these solutions, these patterns of solutions
that I need to solve this math problem.
I have, I don't know, by induction or by contradiction.
And in his brain or somebody that knows a lot,
the person can access very fast.
The representation itself is very well-defined.
So you can access.
That's an interesting whole.
Remember, let me interrupt.
I was once in some class.
And math class.
And it was about n-dimensional vector spaces.
And some student asked, well, how do you
imagine an n-dimensional vector space?
And there's two stories.
And the instructor, who I forget who,
thought for a while, and then he said, oh, it's very simple.
Just pick a particular n.
So that was completely useless.
So then next time, and I was a disciple
of a mathematician at Harvard named Andrew Gleason, who
was a wonderful man, only a couple of years older than me.
But he had won the Putnam three times, first prize.
And I said, what would you tell a student who
wanted to understand an n-dimensional vector space,
what it means?
And he said, well, you should give him five or six ways.
I don't know.
Imagine a bunch of arrows.
And remember that each of them is at right angles
to all the others, just like that.
And then he added, and you should make the sum.
And if there's an infinite number,
you should have the sum of the squares of their lengths
converge to a finite value.
And then he said, or you should think of it
as a Fourier series with things of different frequencies.
And then he said, or you should think
of an object in a topological space,
and each dimension is finding the boundary of the last one.
And he went on for about six or seven.
And that was a great idea.
That is, well, have seven completely different ways.
And I remember I once had the same conversation
with Richard Feynman.
And I said, well, how did you do that?
And he said, well, when I grew up, I always, whatever it was,
I always thought of three or four representations.
So if one of them didn't work, another one would.
What?
Yeah, so my idea for somebody who wanted to,
if you asked them about how to understand
what the dimension of space is, is say, read flat land.
Read flat land.
Because that would give you the analogy.
Once you have that analogy, then you
could, it would be easy to extend it to other dimensions.
Oh, good.
Has anybody written a 4D flat land
where you make fun of the 3D people who, they
can't get out of a paper bag?
Yeah.
No.
And so there will be some events that maybe will prove that.
So for example, in my case, when I do a lot of math,
when I try to talk to people, it's very hard.
And maybe I'm open to seeing my representation of solving
problems in math.
And people tend to get better in math
if they practice a lot because they are optimizing
representation in math.
And that would be the case.
That's it.
I think I understand the problem.
But I don't think I have any friends left
who are not mathematicians.
That's what happens if you live in this place long enough.
Yeah.
I feel like, so that's one way they're doing better.
I feel like the other way they're doing better
is they objectify things that we don't objectify.
Like, it's like the learning how to learn better idea.
Learning how to learn better to learn better.
So it's one thing to know what the right representation is
for predicting the problem or the right method is.
It's another thing to optimize that process.
So what process did I use in finding that representation?
And then they make that into a concept.
And then they have a lot of these concepts.
Have you ever helped somebody to learn better?
Yeah.
What did you tell them?
So she had trouble with basically true truth tables,
something like that, and or, and stuff like that.
So her way of seeing the problem is to make a chart.
I forgot what I told her.
I told her to kind of map simple problems.
You know, maybe most people don't have the word
representation in their language.
Is there any place in grade school
where you actually talk about, what's
your representation of acceleration?
Do we teach that word as part of any subject?
Parts, if you're drawing some base or something like that,
they'll ask you to represent it.
Yes.
It's, but it's hard to get out of.
Yeah, OK.
So they're radically different representations of.
Maybe that's going more far than school.
Yes, I don't know.
Did you have an idea that something maybe
did to correct your picture?
Tinker toys.
Tinker toy.
Yes, that's to represent physical structures
as tinker toys.
Yeah, I wrote a little article complaining
about the popularity of LEGO as opposed to tinker toy,
because the children who grow up with LEGO
can't understand how to make something strong
by making a triangle.
So I sort of had the conjecture that although those people
could build all sorts of wonderful houses and things,
they ended up deficient in having
the most important of all architectural concepts.
The triangle is infinitely strong,
because, I mean, you can't alter a triangle
without breaking it, whereas I don't know what.
That's a run on sentence I can't finish.
This explains the deterioration of society, Barbara.
We don't have tinker toys, and we don't have chemistry sets
of chemicals that make explosives anymore.
You have to go to terrorist school to get a good education.
So actually, in this conversation
about being good at things and learning how to learn better,
I think that a point that sort of relates
to this idea of tinker sets and playing around with things,
I think that it's not enough to simply come up
with the best representations of a concept.
In order to actually be good at something,
whether it's music or speaking a new language,
you have to not only understand it conceptually,
but you actually have to gain a certain amount of fluency.
And to gain fluency, you do have to play around
with the thing a lot, whether it's
turning it around in your mind or practicing it physically.
So in the case of math, it's like, yeah, you
can come up with all these different representations
of it, and that's the first step in understanding it.
It's great once you understand it,
but just because you understand the concept
on a conceptual level doesn't mean
that you can actually know when to use it
or know how to use it when you're solving a problem.
And similarly for music, I guess I'm
mostly talking in the case of improvisational music
when I'm trying to speak something with the music.
So I have something that I want to say,
and maybe it's something that's sort of low level.
I'm trying to resolve one chord to get to some sort of cadence.
Now, I can have multiple ways of resolving the chord,
and in order to do this, I have a vocabulary
of the different ways.
And if one way doesn't occur to me when I'm playing the piece,
I can try another way.
But the important thing is that I have some way
that I can resolve it in real time,
or else my piece is never going to come out.
And then the same thing about learning different languages
or speaking different languages.
In order to be able to speak or to express ourselves,
we have to have not only understanding
of the language, of the structure,
but the immediacy of being able to access it.
And that comes with practice, with tinkering, whatever you.
Well, maybe that goes in several directions.
One thing about where in our educational system
do we, in grade school, is there a place
where you emphasize having several representations?
Because I can't think clearly right now,
but it seems to me that you're usually trying to tell them
the one best way.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2 A, there's the idea of the one best way.
And B, there's the idea of reinforcing
the same process over and over again.
So when you learn math, it's like you learn this technique,
and you reinforce the technique by doing a bunch of homework
problems that are essentially repetitions of the same thing.
Whereas I think a better way of doing it, well,
two better ways.
A, you have multiple representations.
And two, you create problems where
you make people traverse paths differently.
And different people may have different solutions.
And each time you solve the problem,
you may have a different solution.
But the idea is you lay out a whole network of paths
in your head to solve any given type of problem.
MARVIN MINSKY So where in grade school
do you ask children to solve the same problem three ways?
Can anybody think of?
Is that part of education?
What?
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2 Closest thing I can come up with.
MARVIN MINSKY With fractions?
What about literature class?
They ask you for integrations of novels.
MARVIN MINSKY Yes.
Yes, I bet there are things that happen in literature
that don't happen anywhere else in the curriculum.
But they probably don't have, most children
don't transfer it.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 3 When I was in China and learning math,
when we try to find areas of certain geometric shapes,
we always do it in multiple ways.
MARVIN MINSKY In topology, whatever it is,
you just make it into triangles or simplexes.
It's a very strange subject.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 4 Maybe one of the reasons why topology is
so nice is because you can think about it
as logical, cosets, you count all the different points,
stuff like that.
And then you can imagine it as a picture.
Cosets.
Where in real life do you have duality?
That's a nice feature of a lot of mathematics.
Whatever you're doing in some fields,
there's a dual way where you look
at the space of the functions on the objects
rather than the objects.
I can't think of an, where is that in loop?
Is there anything like that in real life?
Because in mathematics, a lot of problems
suddenly become much easier in their dual form.
You just change everything.
I've been facing one way.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 5 I guess a couple of points.
You said why is it difficult?
Whenever I struggle, I think it's because it's constructive.
And you have to hold a lot in your head.
You hold the entire structure of almost a field.
Because if you're learning algebraic topology,
you're holding all of algebra and all
of that structure in your head.
So sometimes it becomes difficult
if you haven't abstracted it to the right level.
And what I found, I think, my advisor was just really good
many times.
And basically, he said two things.
Just really good mathematicians are really
good at making analogies in mathematics.
And I was studying algebraic geometry.
And he says, and really good algebraic geometers
can boil everything down to linear algebra.
So he says, and you can only do that
if you're abstracted to the right level.
And he never gave techniques of doing that.
But I think the difficulty is in that.
It's probably so much too bold.
I mean, an analogy is a relationship
between two objects.
And if you're good at making analogies,
you're a level above just looking at the objects.
You're looking at relationships of objects.
And regarding the practicing thing,
it's still related to representations.
Because at each practice, you're learning
something new about this type of problems
that make you better at identifying them in the future.
And it's not like numerous practices.
The number of practices doesn't matter
to your ability of solving problems.
What you learn from each practice,
if you can do a thing once.
I have a friend who basically told me how to do math.
You look at a problem and solve it once.
You go back, and you think about how you solved it.
What's the process you need to solve it?
So a good problem is make up another problem like this.
That's essentially what you were learning
when you were practicing.
It's probably too hard to grade.
You can't teach things you can't grade in the modern.
Yes?
So I would believe that math is too abstract.
And so it's difficult to go from one representation to another.
And that would be the whole problem.
I can't learn a new concept without having
a concept that's very near that concept, that's very similar.
So it's just that if I don't have good representations
of a lot of things, it's difficult to put
in a new representation.
So when I learn topology, I should know analysis.
And then I can go from there to there,
because the representation is very close.
And so people that are good at math,
maybe they have a lot of representation.
So it's easier to add a new representation of a thing,
because it's like close.
Certainly would be nice to know.
Like in the same of vectors, I already
have the concept of the perpendicular lines.
And so just adding more lines, it's easy.
32,920
But if you have new representations,
if you assume that they are symbolic representations,
in this sense, they are kind of generative things.
You can combine them, and you can make a lot of stuff.
But usually, when you learn something new,
like if you learn the rule, there's going to be exceptions.
So when you repeat things, one of the reasons for that
might be to find out bugs, which you might have learned.
Well, now, when you practice a little piece of music
by repeating, do you change your representation?
Or do you just repeat and hope it gets better?
So I think there's a difference between, OK,
so there's practice in this sense
of traditional classical music practice.
And then there's the idea of tinker practice, if you will.
So I think that the type of practice that I'm advocating
is the type of practice where you're actually
turning around the concept or the thing, the object,
in your head so that you're looking
at it from many different perspectives
and connecting it to many different things, which
is actually conducive to expanding your representation,
connecting it to different concepts,
all the good things that help us remember it and better use it.
This is very different from the classical music practice,
which, having been a classical pianist for 18 years,
it's not a really good way of doing things.
Well, I was wondering, has there been any studies of children?
Have there been any children who have just
played piano or some keyboard instrument
and used it all their lives?
And then they suddenly have something
where when you press it, where you can control the volume?
A theramin.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But if a child were very suddenly
to learn a completely new dimension,
that's the dynamics and how would it react to that.
So I don't know if there are any such cases.
But I would suspect that you would
go to a suitably backward place in the nowadays
and find some children who don't have much.
There was a nice period in the Media Lab
when we were building three-dimensional theramins
for Penn of Penn and Teller, because he's
quite a good musician.
We're making gadgets so he could wave his hands.
But I wonder, in classical music,
there ought to be some very short pieces that
come in 10 variations.
Because we make children learn fairly long pieces
where it's just repeating.
There's the Belvedere pieces, which
is like 32 or 33 really short pieces.
Well, but only eight people in the world can play it.
But I guess the thing with classical music
is that it kind of just makes you learn this one thing.
And you learn it by repeating it over and over again.
Whereas in something like jazz that's more improvisational,
it's like you have a template.
And each time you go through it, you
can traverse a different path through it.
But even more classical, classical music
where you're playing the same thing each time,
I think that there's still a good way of doing it
and a not so good way.
The good way being each time you practice it,
you suddenly vary it somehow.
You change the expression a bit.
You play it faster, slower, things like that.
And I guess this goes back to the whole,
it's like each time you reinforce an idea,
simply repeating it, well, in the beginning,
it might help you familiarize yourself with the idea.
But if you repeat it and vary it slightly each time
to look at different dimensions of it,
then you learn it better.
How many of you know that piece?
Beethoven's DIABEL?
Well, you should Google it up and listen to it.
It has 32.
Is it 32?
I think it's 32, and then there's the original theme.
So it's like 33 total, maybe.
The one I like is the next to last, which is
ba-da-bop-bop-bop-bop-bop-bop-bop-bop-bop the fugue.
So that'll give you another view of classical music,
because the pieces are fairly short.
And they all have some ideas in common.
And it's sort of like poetry.
How do you make it?
What do you call those poems where there are many verses,
and each verse ends with the same line,
but it means something different each time?
It's a very what?
What's an example of a duet cake, Beethoven poem?
I couldn't hear you.
Well, there's like the villanelle.
It's like a rondo, except that it changes its meaning each time.
And it's the same words.
They're pretty hard to make, I guess.
There's the villanelle, which has a bit of that.
That does it?
There's the famous one that's what, like,
do not go gentle into the night or something.
Rage, rage against the coming of something.
Anyway, I'll email you the Diabelli.
I had a friend, Manfred Kleins, who
wrote this book called Centics, who
used to play that particular Beethoven thing.
Well, last important question.
Thanks for coming.
Thank you.