The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Well, I don't have the lecture.
So good.
I have a random question.
Great.
So you've been a teacher for a very long time.
Have you noticed any patterns in students
over the years or decades?
Have I noticed any pattern in students?
Yeah, or like intellectual patterns
or things that people are interested in, just anything.
Well, a few.
The foreigners seem better educated than the Americans.
There are more girls.
When I came to MIT, it was about 20%.
And I think now it's 53%.
Does anyone know?
What?
48?
I read that it actually went past 50 for a few minutes.
No, I think I've complained about the future, though,
which is that a large proportion of my students, by students,
I mean the ones whose thesis I hate to say supervised,
because in the case of Pat Winston, for example,
I learned much more than I or Sussman.
But most of the students became researchers or faculty
members eventually, and now very few of them do.
I'm not sure of all the reasons, but in the 1960s,
which is a long time ago, the universities were still
growing.
And as an after-effect of World War II, I suppose,
I really don't know what caused these major trends.
But there were also a lot of career research institutions
that were large and growing.
Even General Motors had places where
there was some basic research.
IBM was a big research laboratory
that was supporting some very abstract and basic research
of various sorts.
I don't think there's very much of that now.
Even CBS Laboratory.
Westinghouse was doing interesting robotics
and, of course, Stanford Research Institute,
which had no relation to Stanford, still exists,
and it's still pretty good.
But in those early days, it was one
of the three or four richest computer
science and artificial intelligence research places.
There was a place called the Rand Corporation, which
I think still exists.
Does anybody?
I don't know what it does.
Any idea?
They do government-assaulting sort of things,
just translate writing in bigger fonts.
Basically war games, but not necessarily
about war, sort of economy games or politics games.
But in the 60s, it had a lot of basic research.
It had Newell and Simon and me and a few other people.
And we just went there and could walk on the beach in Santa
Monica and go to your office and talk and do things.
And no one ever bothered us, and we
wrote lots of little papers.
And anyway, grumble, grumble.
Another feature was that places like the National
Institute of Health had five-year fellowships.
And now you have to renew.
There are very few appointments of that sort anywhere.
And usually, no sooner do you get funded
than you're starting to write proposals for the next year.
And some people want reports every quarter.
And Neil Gershenfeld, who was running a big lab here,
wanted reports every month.
And some of us finally gave up on that.
That's a long answer.
So if you want a career in being a professor,
it's just harder to find now than it was then.
And so a lot of people recognize this pretty early
and find some place to work in Wall Street and stuff like that.
There are lots of jobs for smart people,
but then you have to sneak your research in on the side.
Anybody can think of a way to fix it?
In the last 20 years, Taiwan made 100 new math departments.
I read somewhere.
I don't know if any of you know anything about Taiwan.
I just wonder if that where they succeed.
Successful?
Is there a lot of research there?
No.
Very often, when a government decides on the right thing
to do, it doesn't work.
Because I had some friends in Italy
who were trying to start an AI group.
And they had accumulated a critical mass in what's
a big city in the north, Milan.
And then some government committee said,
oh, there's a bunch of computer scientists there,
but there's no good computer scientists in Pisa and Verona.
So the government can order a professor to leave one place
and go somewhere else.
So the next year, there were no groups.
And occasionally, there are people like Isaac Newton
who like to work alone.
But I got the impression that the product of the Italian
researchers diminished after that.
Might be wrong.
I'll bet a more technical question.
Thanks.
You had a complicated diagram concerning story.
Do you recall the many layers?
Yeah.
Was that meant to be a bi-directional diagram
or does it work from the bottom up and goes to the top down?
I'm confused about whether that, let's see if I can find it.
Why did this shut down?
Do I dare press Start?
It's alive on the screen.
Oh my gosh.
I never saw that phenomenon before.
Contact displays?
Yeah, I can't.
Is that a shift button that changes?
Oh, there we are.
What?
Did it go on?
It's a strange person.
Oh, it's on.
Oh, well.
It might be in this random lecture.
How do I get rid of those?
Yes, there's a sort of bug in the.
In the toolbox thing on the Macintosh,
which is if you make one of these too long,
there's no way to get rid of it except to restart
the machine in some other mode.
I can't catch it.
Anyway, maybe this works.
Oh, well.
That diagram.
There's two hierarchical diagrams.
The theme of the motion machine book
is mostly the six layers of instinctive built-in reactions,
learned conditioned reactions, and going up
to reflective and self-reflective and so on.
And the other diagram starts out with just a neural net
and then things like K lines, which
are ways to organize groups of activities
and then frames and trance frames.
The trance frame is a way of representing knowledge
in terms of how action affects a situation
or a particular situation and action produces a new one.
And then a story is usually a chain of trance frames.
And of course, a meaningful story
is one which I didn't have a level for.
Good stories and useless stories.
So somewhere at a very high level,
we all have knowledge of, if you're
facing some sort of problem, what kind of strategy
might be good for solving that kind of problem.
And in that case, each layer is made
of things in the lower layer, whereas in the society of mind
hierarchy, each layer does different things
that operates on the result of the other layers.
So there's sort of, I guess if you look at any mechanism,
you'll have a diagram of what the parts do
and how they relate.
And you'll have a diagram of which
isn't in the machinery of what are
the functions of the different sets of parts
and how are those functions related.
So that might be a bug in both books
that I drew the diagrams to look pretty similar.
And it's a bad analogy.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's certainly interesting.
There's a stimulus response model
where if you put a story beneath it,
where the interpretive mechanism.
But does it flow the other way?
Is it generative from bottom to top as well?
Well, in some sense, this trance frame says,
here's a piece of knowledge which says,
if you're in such a situation, this
is a way to get to another situation.
In the traditional behavioristic, behaviorist
is a word for the class of generations of psychologists
who try to explain behavior just in terms
of reacting to situations.
And that wasn't connected to what am I trying to say?
In the standard behaviorist models,
which were sort of occupied most of psychology
from the 19th century up to the 1950s
when modern cognitive psychology really started,
you just looked at the animal as a collection of reactions.
And then in cognitive psychology,
you start to look at the animal as having goals and problems.
And then some machinery is used to go
from the way you describe your situation
to generating a plan for what you're going to do about that.
And then the plan ends up being made of little actions,
of course.
But before 1950, there were only a few psychologists who,
and philosophers, I should say, going all the way back
to people like David Hume and Spinoza and maybe
Immanuel Kant, they made up.
If you read their stuff and ignore the philosophy,
you see that there was a very slow progress over, really,
three centuries of trying to get from logic, which sort of first
appears around the time of Leibniz.
When is Leibniz?
1650 or so?
Yes, they never met, I believe.
So a lot of philosophy has, I don't know
how to describe the rest of it, but a lot of it
is trying to make high-level theories of how thinking works.
And it's, of course, mixed with all sorts of problems
about why the world exists and ethics
and what are good things to do and bad
and all sorts of mixed-up things.
And psychology doesn't appear.
I don't think there is a name for that field
until the 1880s or so.
Who's the first psychologist you can think of?
William James?
William James is around 1890.
There's a guy named Wundt in Austria, I think.
Sigmund Freud starts publishing around 1890.
Francis Galton in England is maybe the first recognizable
psychologist.
He has a big book called An Inquiry into Human Faculty,
which makes good reading right now,
because each chapter is about a different aspect of what
would be called modern cognitive psychology.
How do people recognize things?
What kinds of memory cues do you use to retrieve stuff?
All sorts of sort of term papers, the chapters,
some little theory.
And you'd say, I can do better than that.
And indeed, you could.
But at that time, no one could.
Yes?
What psychology is thinking about how people think,
which I think people have been dealing with in Aristotle
and in a lot of them?
Aristotle has more good ideas than, as far as I'm concerned,
everyone else put together for the next 1,000 years.
It's just very remarkable.
And we don't know anything about that,
because there are no manuscripts.
Anybody?
There's that wonderful play by, who's the Italian?
What?
No, no, a recent one.
No.
No, he's sort of contemporary.
Anyway, he has a play about searching for the lost.
There's some record that Aristotle had a book of jokes,
or rather a book.
He has books on ethics and things like that.
And there's a book about humor, which is lost.
And most scholars think it's not important,
because if you look at the 10 existing books on Aristotle,
I think there's about 10 allegedly by him.
They're students' notes.
And almost every subject appears in at least two of them anyway.
So one conjecture is that there really isn't any very much
lost from ancient times.
Anyway, if you ever read books, you might as well
read one or two of Aristotle's, because the translations,
I'm told, are pretty good.
And you can actually get ideas from it.
Yes?
I don't know if you ever heard about the theory of Giulio
Tonini.
Humberto Eco is the writer.
Sorry.
How does memory work?
Something about your extension.
Sorry.
Giulio Tonini, he tries to explain consciousness.
You say that consciousness is a suitcase word.
But I don't quite agree with his definition.
But basically, his definition is that the more
the information is integrated, the more conscious being is.
The more information you have?
The more integrated the information is.
So for example, I don't know.
He gives an example of a MacBook that has a lot of information
that's not integrated.
It's not correlated, and so it's not very conscious.
That sounds like an important idea,
and there ought to be a name for it.
Yeah, it has a name.
I think it's IDT.
And this guy is a neuroscientist and a psychologist.
And he sees some edge cases of people
that split the brain in half.
And it seems that both halves are kind of conscious.
But I don't agree, because that people, they still
have the information that's integrated.
But it seems that they are not conscious.
So there must be some action into that information,
even if it's passive or active.
But it seems very interesting.
Well, which of my 30 features that go into that suitcase
do they have?
It doesn't make any sense to say something is conscious or not,
does it?
You just said it yourself, that there's
some degree of integration, perhaps.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But can you say what you mean by integration?
You probably need to say 20 things,
and many of them might be independent.
Here's an example of something.
Many years ago, people in the 1950s and 60s,
it was very popular to talk about the left and right brain.
Have you heard people say, what's
the difference between the left brain and the right brain?
It's supposed to be cream versus rational.
Rational versus emotional?
Now, I haven't heard anybody discuss that
for the last 15 or 20 years.
Although it seems to have become really a mesh
with popular culture now.
If you ask anybody what they know about the brain,
one of the first things they'll say
is, well, I'm more of a right brain person
or a left brain person.
That seems to be a sticking thing.
They used to, but I haven't heard that
for at least 15 years.
I have not heard a single person, psychologists,
mention it.
Have you?
I think fMRI has all the obsolete of that theory.
There's one thing that's good for it.
It's disproving that.
Anyway, I mentioned in the Society of Mind,
I think I had a grumble about it, which is that,
as far as I can tell, it appears to be true
that language is located in most people
in two very definite areas in the left brain,
but occasionally in the right brain of some people.
But other than that, as far as I can see,
when you actually catalog the differences
that the psychologists reported in the 1960s and 70s,
then the things in the left brain
were largely adult kinds of thinking,
and the things in the right brain were largely childish.
It wasn't that they were rational or not.
It was that they weren't very hierarchical and tower-like.
And I think there was a nice romantic idea
of contrasting emotions and intellect
and all those dumbbell distinctions.
And projecting them onto the brain.
But I don't know what started me on that track.
But it's interesting that it was very, very popular,
and psychologists talked about it all the time
when I was a student.
And I haven't seen it mentioned by any cognitive psychologist
for, yeah?
So he mentioned his theory.
But I believe we don't test our theory with edge cases.
So mental ill people, or people that, probably
there are a lot of people that, not a lot,
but some percentage of people that are mental ill
or don't form so well in some part of the brain.
And maybe we can have some idea of what
consciousness is, just by seeing people
that don't have some part of the brain that might interfere
with something.
Like the split brain may give a reason why what's consciousness.
Because maybe some half of brain,
like both halves are consciousness.
But I don't understand what you're trying to,
you're trying to construct a meaning for the word
consciousness.
Well, Tononi is definitely onto something interesting.
And I think the reason that he uses the word consciousness
is that it's in the sense that people talk about losing
or regaining it.
And so he can actually experimentally test his theory.
People who are asleep, or in a coma, or dreaming,
or locked in a persistent vegetative state,
in each of those cases, his theory actually
agrees with the common sense idea of whether this person is
conscious in a temporary way.
But then, is that different from,
if you use the word thinking instead,
you could say when somebody is in a coma,
they're not thinking and they're not there.
I don't think that it's good for him
to use the word consciousness.
And I think that the word consciousness, to many people,
refers to a lot of things that his theory does not
treat at all.
See, it's really dangerous if you like,
is it Pinker who likes consciousness?
I forget.
It's dangerous to feel sure that there's
something very important, and a central mystery,
and what does he call it, the hard problem of psychology.
And so here's a really very smart guy, Steven Pinker.
And as far as I can see, he does nothing but harm
to the people he talks to, because he gets them
to do bad experiments and waste their time.
So instead of trying to revive consciousness,
it's worth considering that might be a very bad thing
to do to yourself and other people.
What problem are you trying to solve?
Is there any way, or the problem of qualia, for example?
Because the standard view, and this
is something that still is a serious disease even today
in philosophy.
That is, the idea that the redness of red things
is a very fundamental thing.
It's indivisible.
It's not describable.
It's like, to those philosophers,
that's just as important as when, who was the Greek?
Democritus, was it?
Who discovered atoms?
Yeah, Democritus.
The idea of atoms was an enormous breakthrough.
Of course, it took 2,000 years before people realized that,
yes, there are atoms, and they're not.
They're actually complicated systems
made of quarks and five or 10 other things.
So now we don't have atoms anymore.
But I think Pinker has the idea that red is irreducible.
And you can't describe it.
It's like the atom of thought.
And these qualia are the fundamental problem
of psychology.
To me, it's exactly the opposite.
Why do we have a word for it?
When I say red, do you experience the same thing
as anyone else who says red?
And it seems to me that somebody who
got sick after eating a tomato has a different qualia for red.
Blood, violent things, bad.
Maybe another child has all sorts
of pleasant associations with things that are red.
And the concept of red is it's not
that it's inexpressible because it's indivisible.
It's inexpressible because it's connected
with thousands of other ideas and experiences.
And therefore, there's no way to make a compact definition
of it.
But it's exactly the opposite.
It's not the hard problem of psychology.
It's something that will fall out automatically
without any effort when you have a pretty good theory
of psychology.
But why do we have this qualia of things that are red?
Why do we have descriptions of things?
Because the animals that don't have compact descriptions
of things get eaten very quickly because they can't recognize
things that might hurt them.
It's very important to have machinery
for recognizing real things.
And real things have features.
In fact, there is such a thing as redness, namely
the frequencies of light of, what, around 400 nanometers?
What's the frequency?
700 nanometers.
What?
Other end, 700 nanometers.
That far?
That's infrared, isn't it?
A little bit, 650, 680.
Anyway, one of the things somebody pointed out to me
in later life is that there's only one yellow.
There are a lot of shades of red.
Interesting how tiny the yellow spectrum is.
I don't know what it means.
If you look around a room, I don't see a single one.
If you saw one, it might be a lion.
Is there a what?
It might be a lion.
Oh, a lion.
Yes, does anybody see anything yellow in here?
It's probably really hard to generate the frequency
of the yellow light.
I can't do it because I have a lot of money.
Yes, what element has a bright yellow line?
Sodium.
Yeah, orange-ish.
It's orange, yeah.
Yellow is the sun.
Yes.
Maybe that's very important.
Probably.
There's yellow chalk in the bin.
Yeah, yeah, that's right.
It's in the bin.
That's great.
These lights are really hot.
So this color is called warm white.
There's a yellow one.
In the store, yeah.
Wow, you're on the table.
Warm white.
What is it in Finland?
I don't know.
It's called the lights like that which comes from the tungsten.
They're awful, outlawed tungsten light bulbs,
which are not tungsten anymore.
Yes, that's right.
I've stocked up on 20 watt tungsten bulbs
because my house is full of fluorescent bulbs
that are remote controlled by things.
And if there's no incandescent bulb in one of the sockets,
then the remote controller breaks.
These are the things you buy with what are they called?
Little units that.
X10.
X10, right.
The old X10 units are the receivers
burn out if there's no resistive load on them.
So I have to have enough incandescent bulbs
for the next 20 years or get rid of the X10s.
I think they're illegal in Japan, aren't they?
In Japan, they are still out there.
They're still there?
You can still find them in some shops,
and people buy them so that they can still get 70-year-olds
and get a lot of something else.
I bought a lot of LED light bulbs
at the swap fest the other day.
Back to AI.
So in the reading, you seem to imply
that evolution is a bad strategy for creating AI because, one,
it'll take a lot of time, and two,
because it'll get stuck in local minima maximum.
But if we had infinite time and enough mutation,
do you think it would be possible to create
a good artificial intelligence using evolution?
Well, if there's somebody in charge,
if there's somebody in charge, if you have evolution
on a big planet, then you get a lot of life forms.
And so the problem is that you might
have some really stupid life form that eats the smart ones.
So but I have a more serious objection to evolution.
See, there have been several projects in the last,
well, since computer science started,
of trying to make problem solvers smart
by imitating evolution, which is variation and selection.
So I know of about five or six such projects which were
fairly well-funded and serious.
Most interesting, maybe, was the one
of Doug Lenitz, which was just him by himself.
So if you look up Douglas Lenitz's thesis, which
was called AM, Automated Mathematician,
and a second publication called Eurisco, E-U-R-I-S-K-O,
those were projects in which he did variation and selection.
And he imitated chromosomes by having strings
of simple operations, which were usually things like adding
and subtracting and conditional jump and so forth.
But there are several bugs with organic evolution.
And the most serious one, which is that evolution doesn't
remember what killed the losers.
So there's no record in the genes
of the mutations which were lethal.
And in fact, it's almost the opposite.
I'm told that in the human genome,
I believe it's still 90% doesn't do anything,
some large fraction.
Some people think they didn't think they did something,
actually, to do stuff.
But they once did, presumably.
About 90% of the human genome and a lot of other animals
is not transcribed into proteins.
And a fair amount of it is old inactive viruses.
So it has maybe 90% of some really deadly virus
that got incorporated into the genome and gets copied.
So the big bug in evolution to me
is that if you're going to build a system that's
going to try to develop a new kind of program by trial
and error, the standard approach is to imitate Darwin.
And you mutate these programs, you give them a test,
and you then copy the programs that pass the test
and repeat the cycle.
So what happens is you collect, because you're mutating them
as you go along, you're collecting genes
that help solve problems.
But you're not collecting information
about genes that make the animal worse
or make it fail to solve problems.
So this is true of all of evolution, as far as I can see,
that there's no record kept of the worst
things that can happen.
And so every lethal mutation eventually kills someone.
A lethal mutation is one, you know,
you have two copies of every gene, one from a mother
and one from a father.
And if you get two copies of the same gene,
and most genes are have a lot of genes
are recessive in the sense that unless you get two of them,
they're not expressed.
If you have a lethal recessive gene,
that usually means that you can have one of that gene
and you're not sick, but if you have two of them,
it eventually kills you.
And it might kill you before birth,
so you don't even get an embryo.
Or it might kill you when you're 40 years old,
as in that horrible Huntington's disease,
where you can carry one and not suffer, but if you get two,
it kills you in middle age, which
is very expensive for society.
Anyway, there's no record.
What you want to do is for each problem solver that
doesn't work, you want your evolution program
to see why it doesn't work and not make that kind of gene
again or whatever was responsible for it.
So that's a big bug in Darwinian evolution.
And the interesting fact is that every lethal recessive gene
will eventually, on the average, kill someone.
This is not a well-known.
You see the arithmetic?
Because it has to wait till there are two of them,
and then it kills that person.
And if you calculate the probabilities,
there's a half chance of getting each of them
in each generation.
The math shows that eventually, there's
one premature death for each recessive gene.
It's kind of funny.
So it would be nice if we had some way to clean them up once
and for all, and then everybody would be a lot healthier.
I bet within the next 20 or 30 years,
we'll see some project which is to get rid of,
just take somebody's genome, sweep out
all the lethal recessives, and get rid of 100 diseases
or more.
And suddenly, everybody will live
to be 150 years instead of 100.
Something like that ought to happen.
Yeah?
There's some theories about why recessive genes
stay in the population despite killing off people.
And there are some genes for which it seems to be the case
that when you get to a recessive gene, you die.
But having the heterozygous combination
gives you some benefit, like you benefit
against a different disease, and that's why they persist.
So just getting rid of all of the recessive lethal genes
might cause problems.
Wow, I hadn't thought of that.
Are there some examples?
Sickle cell, malaria.
Yeah, sickle cell, malaria.
So if you have sickle cell, you cannot get malaria.
If you have heterozygous from the sickle cell disease,
you're not mutating as well.
But that's not very beneficial, because you usually
die when you're around 40.
No, no, no.
If you have heterozygous for sickle cell disease,
then you don't have sickle cell disease,
but you have benefits against malaria.
Oh, I didn't know that.
That's the example commonly given in all biology classes,
but I'm sure there must be other examples.
I never took a biology class.
That's good.
So we could probably find one that we just
have to tailor it a little bit.
So the mosquitoes don't like it.
Is that what it is?
It's just bad enough blood that the mosquitoes will adore you,
but not bad enough if you die.
Does it keep the mosquito from biting you,
or does it make the mosquitoes sick, or what?
It makes the entire sense.
It's just, yeah.
Some stuff I've read about viruses,
people changing their theory about viruses.
One thing is that maybe in some sense,
we're symbiotic with viruses in some sense.
Like you say, the jump comes in the genome,
maybe some process, but it takes advantage of that.
So one thought I had is maybe the viruses
are the things that remember why the losers lost.
That's a good point.
There's still lots of things we don't know and wrongly believe.
With this synthetic life rule, there
are two groups starting to make maybe more.
There are probably some secret groups trying to make them too.
Also, in some sense, the bacteria that live in the human body
might be far more than the cells that are dealing with lures
and so forth.
And so they're starting to think that maybe
the entire genome of all the bacteria that colonize you
are also part of that equation in some way.
So it could be that some of the genetic information
in evolution is not kept in your own genome,
but kept in all the organisms that
live with you externally.
Yeah, it's a what?
Is there a comix for that?
Yes, there is, that somebody was trying to sequence the.
Bacteriomics?
Yeah, I don't know what you did, biologists.
Do you know what that's called?
How many different?
Somebody's trying to sequence every genome of everything
that lives in your gut.
Yeah, how many different?
I understand there are more bacterial cells
than somatic cells by a factor of 100 or something,
because bacteria are so small.
But how many different bacteria infests a person?
Is it hundreds, or tens, or thousands?
I guess that's what they're trying to find out.
Yeah?
So when you say, like in evolution,
wouldn't it be nice if you kept everything that went bad?
And then you said, and then we could analyze it
to see what went wrong, right?
But isn't it that when we're doing evolution algorithms
or anything like that, we don't have a clear idea of what
helps and what doesn't help to solve the problem?
So even though we have the information of the solver
that didn't work, I feel like if we had a way to know what went
wrong, then we would already have information enough
to know what is right.
Oh, yes.
So how do you decide what went wrong?
I was thinking of a fairly high-level system,
because when Lenit or Larry Fogel,
I was another one of these learning by evolution systems,
I'm not suggesting that we could make a simple evolution
simulation that would think of reasons why it failed.
So this would be a high-level one
if you're writing a big AI program.
For example, when you learn arithmetic, after a while,
you learn not to divide by 0.
So what do we call negative knowledge?
What are the common-sense things?
Is there a name for the things you should never do?
Because when people talk about, you know,
they search tree as a possibility to prune the tree.
You prune the tree.
But we have rule-based systems, and they
got very popular around 1980 and wiped out
most of the symbolic AI for a long time.
But there aren't any rules that say don't do X.
Are there ever?
Do they have some?
So the question is, when are they invoked?
In a certain situation, turn off this bank of rules, maybe.
So I'm not suggesting that you could make a very simple system
do that because, in fact, figuring out
why this mutation was bad might be a very hard problem.
But as you build smarter and smarter ones,
then you want to put, well, what I called critics,
or what I don't know if Freud had a name for them.
At some point, you want to have prohibited actions.
And in Sigmund Freud's early model of psychology,
there was a place for things that you would go away from
or not do, and these sensors, he called them.
And they never appeared in the main line of psychology.
When they threw out Freud, who had a few bad ideas,
they threw out all his good ideas, practically.
You might be pleased to hear that some
of the monkey neuroscientists are
starting to find some critics.
It's pretty hand-wavy stuff as of now,
but at least they're thinking about it.
There's certain tasks where the monkey is cued
to pay attention to one thing or another, usually
if any, it's color versus orientation.
And what they've found is that orientation has dominance.
And so when the cue is telling the monkey
that they have to ignore the orientation
and pay attention to the color, the part
of those neurons which are responsible for looking
at the orientation are being actively inhibited
by another group of neurons, which they're now
calling a critic.
Are these in the same organ, or is it a little nearby nucleus
that's inhibited?
That's nice.
So that would be a good place for a word
for a negative knowledge.
Why do you call it negative knowledge?
It would have too many different senses, but advice not to take.
So this question would imply that there's
a metric for intelligence, but is there a limit to intelligence?
Is it possible to say one day we have this artificial intelligence
that is the most intelligent possible being?
Seems unlikely, because presumably the survival
value of a particular system depends
on the world the thing is in.
It might be that for all worlds above a certain complexity,
maybe there are some overall strategies that are universally
better than others or something.
Measuring intelligence doesn't make any sense,
because I think you have to go the way Howard Gardner did
and say, well, there's social intelligence,
and I don't know.
Can anybody rattle off his list?
What are his eight ways of thinking?
Just look up Howard Gardner.
So the amount of intelligence is clearly
it's a useful intuitive idea that
for any particular machine, you could imagine another one that
can do everything that one can do and more,
but you're going to get a lattice, not an ordered thing,
and the lattice won't.
At some point, it'll start getting inconsistent,
and this will be better than that one for this and not that.
Go ahead.
Go ahead with about nine different types
of intelligences according to this Wikipedia article.
Logical, mathematical, spatial, linguistic, bodily,
kinesthetic, musical, interpersonal, intrapersonal,
naturalistic, and existential.
There you go.
And if you take any one of those,
when I was a mathematician, I was really good at topology
but not at algebra.
And at some point, that stopped me
from being even better at topology.
So if you take any one of those, I
think Howard wants to keep it simple,
but I wonder if he has a subpsychologist who's chopped
up mathematics into the right.
What are the right eight feet?
How many of you are bad at some kind of mathematics
and know why?
Really bad at Fourier series, just because I don't like them.
I wonder what Newton would have thought about them.
In my PhD thesis, it was mostly about neural networks.
And there were some people who thought
that you could put information, if you had
a bunch of neurons in a circle, then you
could put in a string of signals of different durations
and store the bits in this circular thing.
Because in World War II, there were no digital computer
memories, but there were some computer-like things
that stored signals in a tube of mercury
with a speaker and a microphone.
And it was possible to store a lot of information
in sort of analog bits for a long time.
But what you would do is you would
have something that would regenerate them
and synchronize them with a clock each time around.
And I was trying to prove a theorem that,
given what we knew about the delay in neurons,
if you stimulate a neuron very strongly,
it reacts more quickly than if you just stimulated a little bit
above threshold, that it takes a longer time to fire.
So I was trying to prove that in neural networks in something
like a human brain, you couldn't store a lot of information
in circular loops.
And I kept having trouble proving that,
and I ran into John Nash, who was another student a bit ahead
of me.
And he listened to me for a minute,
and he said, expand it in Fourier series.
And after about two days, I figured out
what he probably meant, and I proved this nice theorem.
And it turned out it's also, and it had been discovered
a long time ago, was called a Lipschitz condition.
And if you have a certain condition like this,
then the information will go away.
But if you don't, you can keep the information
around for a very long time.
So in this case, the proof showed
that you couldn't store, unless you had a renormalizer
or a clock somewhere, you couldn't
store circular information in a mammalian brain very well.
It's a nice example of something where one person had
a different way of looking at it.
Nash was pretty famous for his result in game theory,
but I suspect he might have been responsible for five or 10
other things that he.
Norbert Wiener had this habit of talking to a student,
and he says, what are you working on?
And the student would explain it, and Wiener said,
oh, well, you just do this.
And I was present at a meeting of the,
I was in the math department, where
they had a meeting about who would tell Wiener
not to do that anymore.
Some student had, oh, well, it's a true story.
I wonder what else I've forgotten.
Yes?
I'm curious.
You say this could be updated with a clock.
Is there any evidence to suggest that biologically one
could or could not construct a clock?
There are lots of clocks.
I suspect that if I had thought about it more,
I would have, because I'm talking the middle 1950s,
and people knew a lot about brain waves.
And there are three or four fairly large synchronous
activities in the brain.
And I don't think anybody knows much about what they're for.
Do you know?
Have you heard any rumors of what is the delta wave for?
Well, actually, the monkey experiment
I was just talking about relies on sort of assumption
that the beta wave is for suppression,
and the alpha wave is for activation.
And I think people are still sort of debating
about the delta and beta waves.
The alpha wave, what's the 10%?
I think that's the big one.
And it goes away when you are thinking hard.
That is, if you're not focusing much on anything,
then it's a fairly nice regular 10 per second.
And if anything gets your attention and you focus on it,
then the alpha wave pretty much gets noisy and disappears,
I think.
I don't know what the others do.
Is that correlated with any event?
The usual room shutting down.
I brought all this, but I decided not to use it anyway.
I think it's correlated with a certain period of time
after the signal from the computer stops changing.
Oh, you mean it might wake up again.
No, it shifts down at the same time every five.
It's not always the same time.
It's usually at 8.30.
I wonder if Steve Jobs had this little thing has two batteries.
And at one end, there's a dot.
And the other end, there's a slot,
which is for a screwdriver.
But it's also the minus sign of the battery.
It could have been plus, but what's that?
It's for a quarter, so you can put a coin in it.
Any coin, actually.
Yeah, so you don't actually need a screwdriver.
I don't have a coin.
Of course, it's usually one.
It's somewhere.
No tips.
Good question.
Yeah?
Do you think or I just want to close,
will there ever be elected as a leader of a government?
In most science fiction stories, it doesn't give us a choice.
The moon is a harsh mistress.
That was Robert Heinlein, wasn't it?
It had a really smart computer emerged
from the internet on the moon.
Yeah?
Yes?
I was curious whether you have any ideas how
we could attempt to determine the representations
of information that our people or animals use
to solve problems.
Clearly, this is a crucial problem to intelligence.
And lots of AI has gone into various ways
of representing information.
So it would be really interesting to see how it's done.
And I was wondering if you had ideas
of how that could be tested.
That's wonderful.
What are the cognitive psychologists
doing about representations?
Have you run across any?
They study reaction times, you know,
with scientific or colloquial ways of starting
to determine the representations.
You know, they don't have very good ways of studying that
directly from experiments.
Yeah.
All right, these rule-based systems are still the,
I haven't read a modern cognitive psycho.
Has anybody read a modern cognitive psychology book?
Do they have trance frames or scripts?
What's happening in that realm?
I'm trying to remember what, I guess
I've never seen any Winston-like diagrams in anything but AI.
But there must be some somewhere.
That's 1970.
Who has taken a psychology course?
Is that true?
What's in it?
They talk about babies a lot.
Well, there's a little industry of trying
to show that Piaget was wrong.
Is that what they say about babies?
When do babies get conservation of quantity or something?
Yeah, basically just go throughout the whole
development stage and explain that.
But I have not seen Winston in any of my psychology readings.
Well, there is a problem with the low resolution of brain
scanning.
So if you can only tell when a square centimeter of brain
is more active than another part,
then it's hard to imagine how you
could look for the representation of an arch
as a block on top of two others.
But you should be able to make a hypothesis about
a representation and then design an experiment in which you
show a picture of an arch and then quickly
show a picture where there's a little space between them
so it's not being supported by.
And blink those on and off and see
if different kinds of changes in the representation
cause different kinds of brain activity.
But I suspect that most experiments on watching brain
activity are from giving a stimulus and not a pair
of quickly changing ones, maybe.
So you want to find out what parts of the brain
are activated when a certain kind of difference appears.
And it shouldn't be hard to make such experiments,
but my impression is that they don't do that so much as you
show a certain face for a couple of seconds
and then you show something else and you
look to see if the activity moves somewhere.
But if your resolution is low, maybe
you should be putting in stimuli that change
so that you're finding the response to the changes.
It's just a.
One of the problems is that there is a delay.
You can, in brain waves, you can get like a,
you can get low real-time reaction, but if MRI is.
Yeah, it usually takes several seconds to get anything.
You have to do a, you'd have to repeat it many times.
And I think it still takes several seconds
to get any information, doesn't it?
The first brain wave experiments were in the late,
in the 1940s, and that Englishman,
Gray Walter, who also made that first robot
turtle and things like that.
I was just reading some of the, some papers
he wrote in the middle 1950s.
They're not very illuminating about AI,
but they show you what some people were
thinking in the days before computer science.
Yeah?
When you talk about the, when you're
talking about neural networks and the machines that
accumulate huge libraries of statistical data,
you use that they cannot develop much governance
because they don't have these, sorry, they, here.
Because they don't have higher reflective levels.
What are these higher reflective levels?
Well, that's thinking about what you were thinking a minute ago.
You think something, and then you say, that was a bad idea.
Why did I get that?
Or now I realize I didn't understand something.
I've wasted five minutes because reflective thinking is
thinking about your recent thoughts.
Maybe all thinking is any coherent train of thinking.
Each thought is something about the previous thought,
but it doesn't have the word I in it.
You say, why did I waste so much time?
Why did I focus on this rather than that?
What did that person say?
Maybe I missed the point.
Maybe most of your thinking is, what did I just think?
Yeah?
So here we have to talk a lot about cognitive science
and psychology.
And I'm curious, how important do you
think brain and cognitive science and psychology
are to the field of AI, and whether the right way of trying
to build intelligent machines and understanding intelligences
through understanding what we've already seen,
or it's playing around with computers
and trying to make systems that solve the problems we
want to solve?
I'm glad you asked that because I
don't think it's very important because I think we all,
we've got to the point where we know that people solve problems
and we all know how to think about how
we solve some problems.
We don't know the details of how we did it.
But I think if you look at what's been done in AI,
it's more than clear enough where the present system
stopped and where they fail.
And we keep thinking of ways to fix them.
And we get sidetracked because you get some idea
and it's too hard to program.
Somebody says, use C++.
And somebody else says, why don't you go back to Lisp?
And I guess my answer is, I don't
think we need desperately to know more about psychology
because we already have programs that
are pretty good at things and we can see where they get stuck.
But it would be nice if there were a community out there
helping us because the AI groups are all alone
and they don't communicate very well with each other
and they're not very well supported.
But I bet as we make machines smarter,
the psychologists will pay more attention
and they'll come back and tell us better things.
And eventually, there'll be a real cognitive science,
sort of like physics.
Physics got very well with Newton and Galileo
and quantum mechanics.
But now they have a great community.
And when some serious problem comes up,
somebody will spend a billion dollars for a new accelerator
or something.
There's nothing like that in AI.
If you say, why did the Newell-Simon general problem
get stuck on the missionary and cannibals?
Somebody should say, well, here's a billion dollars.
I know it's not enough, but maybe you
can make it a little smarter.
Nobody's offering this.
Two somewhat, I guess, somewhat related questions.
So first, since AI is mostly an engineering discipline,
it's a question of, how can we make machines that solve
these problems that look intelligent?
Do you think this is going to lead
to a better understanding of intelligence?
And how important do you think that is to this more,
I guess, mostly scientific, but also slightly philosophical
question?
I think it's just an engineering question that there just
isn't a way to get bright people, enough bright people
to compete with each other to make better AI systems.
Anybody have a theory?
You see, I'm speaking from the point of view,
feeling that there hasn't been much progress in recent years.
And maybe I'm wrong.
And there's a lot of great stuff just ready to be exploited,
but I don't see it.
I think we're kind of in an actual delivery room of sorts
where people are doing a lot of the work in terms of,
for instance, tuning the parameters
and choosing machine learning approximations in order
to solve problems that there are incentives out there to solve.
And in principle, if we had AI that was good,
the AI would do that work instead of programmers
having to tune parameters and figure out
which algorithms are good for different problems.
But as of now, the way the incentives are structured,
it's going to take a big energy push
to sort of get over the hump of actually creating
the infrastructure that's necessary for that stuff
to happen automatically.
There are AI groups.
There are few people at Georgia Tech and Carnegie Mellon,
although my impression is that they're mostly playing robot
soccer or something.
So a lot of the people who are empowered to do the right
thing are, I mean, look at Stanford.
It's wonderful to make these self-driving cars,
but I don't think a single thing has been learned from that.
Maybe a little has been learned from the Watson thing, but.
They won't come out in the source code.
Right.
And if they did, I think they could read the Society of Mind
that says, have a lot of different methods
and find some way to integrate them.
What's missing in the Society of Mind
is better ideas on how to integrate them.
And Watson might have some, but on the other hand,
it might not.
Maybe if it can end up with an answer that's
one word, like a person or a sport, then it's done.
And so it may be that we know it's at the lower levels,
and we don't know what's the best way to do it.
We don't know what's at the higher levels,
and maybe it's no good.
On the other hand, maybe there are 10 very important ideas
there, and you'd have to read that long paper
and try to guess what they were.
Do we have a spy in there?
Are they telling us something?
I get little bits and pieces about it, yeah.
I mean, I think it is kind of, you know,
I think the good news about that is it has made some progress,
and it is kind of a society of models,
and they have some supervisory processes that
try to figure out which, actually, the most important
thing they do is try to figure out
which methods are good for which kind of questions.
That would be good.
So they might have some good critics and selectors
like things.
Yeah, so there's some of that, I think, in there.
I don't think there are a lot of very brand new techniques,
but I think there's probably some of that.
They fired their other AI group, but I
don't think it was getting very far either.
You know, the one I mean, Eric Mueller and no, he moved.
He worked on the Watson.
No, I mean, Doug Reichen's group.
It was doing more mathematical AI than heuristic AI.
Any other company doing anything?
What are the common sense groups in Korea and places like that?
Well, I'll find out in December when I go there.
Henry's going to visit some of them.
The mysterious east.
Yes?
So there has been, like, since a long time ago,
from the nuclear factor assessment,
there has been, like, machines that
are trying to build, like, a conveyor, right?
So there's, like, a layer, right?
There are critics.
And even though the idea died out in the 80s,
but then there's still some machines,
like maybe Watson has all critics.
But at the, like, reflective layer,
I feel like it does a lot of different things.
So what do you think is missing from that layer
that, like, no project has pulled back yet?
OK.
I'm not sure what you're asking, but there
is Pat Winston's group working on stories.
And my impression is that that's making definite progress.
And if he can integrate it with Henry Lieberman's
kind of large, common-sense knowledge base,
maybe something great will happen.
But progress is a little bit slow.
Jerry Sussman is still full of ideas,
but he keeps teaching courses in physics.
And he's out there fixing telescopes.
And he's absolutely a prodigy.
And now he's working on this theory of propagators,
which he claims is relevant to AI.
And I don't understand it yet.
But, uh.
It's good.
What?
I swear.
I'd like to see it solve some interesting problem.
So we have a lot of resources here.
But if you look at the world as a whole.
And for example, you talked about how
we should combine the perception in the common-sense group
with the huge common-sense knowledge base, right?
So I feel like doing that, we need some new, newly-invented
missionary.
Yeah, to what extent is?
Well, if you would like to work on it,
please come see me after this.
It's a very lively group.
What's happening to Lenat's group?
Is he just hiding, or is he?
No, I think Doug Lenat is a side project.
And it's been steadily growing.
And I think one thing that, so what was,
he had a very interesting article recently
about using it for common-sense for medical queries.
So the Watson guys said that they
wanted to apply Watson to medicine.
But I think Lenat had a really good article
about applying it to medical queries.
It was things like, so the doctors would ask things
like which operations for some disease or something
had complications.
And the system would have to understand
what's a complication, right?
And a complication is when things don't go right.
So having a drug reaction could be a complication.
Leaving a scalpel in the patient could be a complication.
So you have to understand some of the ideas of,
common-sense ideas of what might be a complication
or what might cause trouble, those kind of things.
He did a very nice system for the Cleveland Clinic.
And the doctors loved it.
And they wrote about it in the online magazine.
But that was a real success.
Oh, I haven't seen that.
Dr. Lenat.
I think the problem is that the reason
that you haven't heard a lot of applications for psych
for so long is because they were funded for decades
by three-letter agencies in the government.
I think they did actually quite good work for them,
because otherwise, the program would have continued
for 25 years.
But the problem is, when they do something good
for secret agencies, nobody else funds out about it.
It doesn't advance the field.
I have a great story about that, which is almost unbelievable.
Which is, I was at a meeting with Doug Lenat.
This was a long time ago when it was just starting.
And this was in a building a block from the White House.
And it had all these people from some agency
about whether AI could help them with their problems.
And somebody pulled out some slides
and was about to give a lecture.
But the shelf that had the projector on it had hinges.
And all the screws were missing on one side.
And it fell down like this.
And they fussed for a long time.
And couldn't get the projector to line up.
And then I had this thing.
And I took three screws out of it.
It had three hinges.
And I took three screws out of here
and put them in here, and here, and here.
And then the shelf stayed up, and the show went on.
It's like the joke about the anyway.
So they were astounded, because I actually
fixed this stupid thing.
And I said, well, why didn't you?
And they said, we asked for maintenance three weeks ago.
And they never got around to it.
And I said, this is the agency.
And they said, yes.
Then they said, but why did you have that thing with you?
Today, you never get past the metal detector.
When I was a kid, I heard some story, oh, never mind,
about when a car wheel rolls off,
you take one screw from each of the other three.
So I was doing exactly that.
And these agency people had never
thought of doing it themselves.
So what does it mean when you have a government run
by people who can't fix this hinge?
I once met a freshman who didn't know which way to turn a screw.
At MIT, how many of you have to try both?
The left hand.
Some rule, right?
If you're screwing in at weird angles,
like upset pieces and stuff.
Yes, sometimes.
That's right.
Enough stories.
Are you sure?
So has he?
Oh, can you send us a pointer to that paper?
Lenin's?
Oh, yeah, sure.
That would be nice.
He's one of the great pioneers of AI.
I guess that's a question about extracting
a different knowledge from experience.
I feel like this is something that's
done in the respective layer in this.
So it could be done in all layers,
but maybe it's probably done in the respective layer.
So how do you think it does that?
How do you retrieve your knowledge?
How do you turn that experience into a piece of a rule
used by the critics?
How do you learn from an experience?
You do something, and then you get some knowledge,
and where do you put it?
If we could answer that, we could all quit and go home.
You're asking the central problem of how do you learn
from experience and later retrieve how you learned.
I just can't think of any way to answer that
except write a whole book and then have everybody
find out what's wrong with it.
Yeah, science is making the best mistakes.
If you make a really good mistake,
then somebody will fix it, and you'll get progress.
If you make a silly mistake, then nothing is gained.
Maybe we should have to search into how
to make better mistakes.
Well, I didn't decide what to try.
That's my complaint about the probabilistic methods,
because if there are a lot of, well,
I talked about the other day, if there
are a lot of different aspects of the situation, like 100,
then there's 2 to the 100th conditional probabilities
to think about.
And so probabilistic learning machines
work wonderfully well on small problems
where the search trees aren't too big, but they don't.
But the hard problem is what to do
when there's a lot of different factors
and you don't know which are important.
And in lots of situations, just first order correlations.
So if there are 100 factors, and you just
look at the probabilities of each of them,
and then there's 5,000 pairs of things,
and you look at the 5,000 joint conditional probabilities
of two things, and maybe five of them pop up,
and you've only got five things to look at,
and that's where that kind of AI system works.
And it's become immensely popular.
And the trouble is it'll never get smarter,
because if you have to look five steps ahead, then instead
of 10 possibilities, you have 100,000.
Anyway, my concern is that there are quite a lot of millions
of dollars going into AI research,
but most of it is going into dead ends.
So it's not as though there weren't a maybe.
Maybe there is enough money, but it's
going to the easy problems instead of the hard ones.
Who has an easy question?
I have an easy question.
So a lot of smart people like to play games and procrastinate.
Do you think artificial intelligence will also
like to play games and procrastinate?
Well, there's the opposite question.
I got a message from somebody I don't remember.
Somebody I don't remember who I had complained
that nobody has been able to get Push Singh's AI
program to work.
And somebody suggested what?
The E-M1?
Yeah.
And somebody suggested that I forget the name.
There's some group of people who like problems.
And I can't remember what it is.
It's just some bunch of people out on the web
who like to solve programming problems.
And this person suggested sending the code
to that group of a couple of thousand people.
And maybe they would self-organize
to try to figure out how it works and fix it.
So do you think that would work?
Could that work?
Yeah.
We have a big bunch of code.
It's partly commented.
Could we get 1,000 really aimless hackers out there
with lots of ability to?
So maybe I'll try it.
Sort of.
The danger with that is that they
01:34:52,720 -
2:05,000
Do you think there's ever going to be a way to crowdsource AI
research at all?
That's what I meant.
That's the expression I was looking for,
for fixing the push theses.
But it would be nice.
It wouldn't be a self-organizing thing.
Someone would have to do that.
I feel like that would be hard for people
to self-organize to do that.
But if there were already the structure,
and that minimal piece that everyone could do for AI
research was already defined.
Do you think AI research is structured in a way
that could ever be broken down?
Well, don't these crowd things usually start with some?
They must start with some sort of leader,
but then they become self-organizing.
I mean, they work because every participant
has a specific and distinct head, basically the same style
that they have.
I mean, they don't become more complex than that.
I mean, it becomes a community, or whatever.
But it doesn't, you know, like the idea of lowering the floor
of doing AI research so that more people can contribute.
It's a nice question.
Well, let's think about it.
If we take this PhD thesis code, it
wouldn't be much good to send the whole thing to everyone.
Well, of course, it wouldn't cost anything to do that.
But you need somebody to make a first pass at chopping it up
into saying, look, this function didn't work.
Maybe there's some code missing.
And so you might need a person or a couple of people
to sort of organize the project.
But once you've got a community, they
might be able to cooperate.
A community already existing to be able to contribute.
They might do it without a leader
once the problems became clear enough, because.
I would say that, I mean, there are some crowdsourced AI
projects.
Certainly, you go to SourceForge or the restaurant
game of Jeff Horton and all that.
That's their crowdsource.
You can think of that as a crowdsource.
They are a problem.
But I don't think the crowdsourcing is really
great for problems that demand a lot of creativity.
You know, it's commands that are projects that
are labor intensive.
It's good for, like, setting at home and that kind of thing.
But for projects that demand a lot of creativity,
it kind of breaks my heart almost,
because if you look at the open source work on Unix,
they've done a great job at organizing people
to work on Unix and Linux and three versions of Unix.
But on the other hand, the software isn't very innovative.
They just implement 60 versions of the mail probably.
The Unix interface hasn't changed since the 1960s pretty much.
So you know, it's everybody's still
programming on terminal windows.
So I think it's crowdsourcing is mainly
good for projects that are labor intensive.
But I think AI needs individual creativity more.
It's like McCarthy said, it needs
2.3 Einstein's and 1.7 Hatton projects.
In fact, you know, it's probably good for the Hatton projects
but not for the Unix studies.
On the other hand, given we have the movie,
it might be that the problem of getting this code
to make that movie isn't so creative.
You could start it up and see where it gets stuck.
And it's worth it.
A great possibility is if you have something
long-winds of Watson that incorporates lots and lots
of small programs, then you can have
people contribute small programs.
And whether they're good or bad, the system
can figure it out in the more than one.
Well, in some sense, Watson was crowdsourced
because it wasn't only developed by that IBM group
that they had lots of collaborators in ISI and CMU
and other places.
And they crowdsourced them by giving them little research
grants to integrate their employee with the research
into Watson.
So I think you could argue that that actually was crowdsourced.
Another thing we haven't tried is
called throwing money at it.
Suppose we got $5,000 or $1,000 and told some programmer,
can you get this to work?
Well, if you have good enough descriptions
of various small programs that you
can use for problem solving, then I
think that part of the problem is creativity.
Because some parts or some sub-programs
could be more stupid.
As long as you have a good description
of what that program is doing, then you
could have some really creative program.
That might use those stupid programs as part of its reasoning.
But you still need that one creative person
to make the decision.
Well, you still need that one creative person
But you don't get so many if you organize it in Watson.
Yeah.
I'm going to just label it Bowman Warcraft 10.
Leave it on the internet.
Bowman Warcraft 10, leave it on the internet.
My grandson was suspended from Warcraft for three weeks
because he hacked the thing to get a higher
priority on something.
I think he was not.
Do you know how old he was?
Yeah.
No, miles.
No, I think he was about 10 or 12.
And he had actually managed to get into the thing
and get instant service.
He was very proud of being banned.
I give up.
Any last request or idea?
Thanks for coming.