The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
I presume everyone has an urgent question to ask.
Maybe I'll have to point to someone.
There's one over there.
Oh, good.
So I don't know if that's exactly what's said,
but you said that maybe the game lights are associated
to the glia cells.
Is that right?
Oh, I don't want to speculate on how the brain works,
because there's this huge community of neuroscientists
who write papers about, and they're very strange papers,
because they talk about how maybe it's not the neuron.
And I just downloaded a long paper
by someone whose name I won't mention about the idea
that a typical neuron has 100,000 connections.
And so something awesomely important
must go on inside the neuron's body.
And it's got all these little fibers and things.
And presumably, if it's dealing with 100,000 signals
or something, then it must be very complicated.
So maybe the neuron isn't smart enough to do that.
So maybe the other cells nearby that support the neurons
and feed them and send chemicals to and fro around there
have something to do with it.
How many of you have read such articles?
It's a very strange community, because I
think the problem is that history of that science
started, first, it was generally thought
that all the neurons were connected.
And then around 1890 was the first clear idea
that nerve cells weren't arranged
in a continuous network.
I think it was generally believed
that they were all connected to each other,
because as far as you could tell with the microscopes
of the time, it didn't show enough.
And then the hypothesis that the neurons are separate
and there are little gaps called synapses,
as far as I can tell, started around the 1890s.
And from then on, as far as I can see,
neurology and psychology became more and more separate.
And the neurologists got obsessed with chemicals,
hormones, epinephrine, and there are about a dozen chemicals
involved that you can detect when
parts of the brain are activated.
And so a whole bunch of folklore grew up
about the roles of these chemicals.
And one thought of some chemicals
as inhibitory and excitatory.
And that idea still spreads, although what
we know about the nervous system now,
and I think I mentioned this before,
is that in general, if you trace a neural pathway
from one part of the brain to another, what happens
is that the connections tend to alternate.
Not always, but frequently.
So that this connection might inhibit this neuron,
and then you look at the output of that neuron,
and that might tend to excite neurons in the next brain
center.
And then most of those cells would tend to inhibit.
I mean, each brain center gets inputs from several others.
And so it's not that a brain center
is excitatory or inhibitory, but the connections
from one brain center to another tend to have this effect.
And that's probably necessary from a systems dynamic point
of view, because if all neurons tended to either do nothing
or excite the next brain center, then what would happen?
As soon as you got a certain level of excitement,
then more and more brain centers would get activated,
and the whole thing would explode.
And that's more or less what happens
in an epileptic seizure, where if you
get enough electrical and chemical activity of one
kind or another, mostly electrical, I think,
but I don't know, then whole large parts of the brain
start to fire synchronously, and the thing spreads very much
like a forest fire.
So that's a long rant.
I guess I've repeated it several times,
but it's hard to communicate with that community
because they really want to find the secret of thinking
and knowledge in the brain cells rather than
in the architecture of the interconnections.
So my inclination is to find an intermediate level,
such as at least in the cortex, which
is what distinguishes the, does it start in mammals?
I think so.
I think if I'm, rather than a neurology book,
I'm thinking of Carl Sagan's book, which
there's a sort of triune theory that's very popular, which
is that the brain consists of three major divisions,
and the, I forget what the lowest level one is called,
but the middle level is sort of the amphibian and then
the mammalian, and it's in the mammalian development
that most of the large parts of the brain are cortex.
And the cortex isn't so much like a tangled neural net,
but it's divided mainly into columns.
And each column, these vertical columns,
tend to have six or seven layers.
I think six is the standard, and the whole thing
is about four millimeters, four or five millimeters thick.
Maybe a little more.
And in each of these columns, there's
major columns, which have about 1,000 neurons,
and one of these columns is made of maybe 10 or 20
of these many columns that are 50 or 100 or whatever.
And so my inclination is to suspect
that since these are the animals that think and plan
many steps ahead and do all the sorts of things
we take for granted in humans, that we
want to look there for the architecture of memory
and problem solving systems.
In the animals without cortexes, you
can account for most of their behavior
in terms of fairly low-level immediate stimulus response
reflexes and large major states, like turning on some parts
of some big blocks of these reflexes when it's hungry
and turn on other blocks when there's an environmental threat
and so forth or whatever.
Anyway, I forget what.
Yes.
So in chapter three, you talked about the stages
we go through when we face something
like your car breaks down and you can't go to work.
That's an example given in the book.
I'm wondering, how do you decide that we transition
from one stage to another?
And why do we go through stages of denial, bargaining,
frustration, depression, and then only the last stage seems
productive?
I guess my main question is, how do we
decide that we should transition from one stage to another?
What marks the end?
And why do we start over?
That's a beautiful question.
I think it's fairly well understood in the invertebrates
that there are different centers in the brain
for different activities.
And I'm not sure how much is known
about how these things switch.
How does an animal decide whether it's time to,
for example, most animals are either diurnal or nocturnal.
So some stimulus comes along like it's getting dark.
And a nocturnal animal might then start waking up.
And it turns on some part of the brain
and turns off some other parts.
And it starts to sneak around looking for food
or whatever it does at night.
Whereas a daily animal, when it starts to get dark,
that might trigger some brain center to turn on.
And it looks for its place to sleep and goes and hides.
So some of these are due to external things.
Then, of course, there are internal clocks.
So for lots of animals, if you put it
in a box that's dimly illuminated
and it has a 24-hour cycle of some sort,
it might persist in that cycle for quite a few days
and go to sleep every 24 hours for half the time and so on.
A friend of mine once decided he would see about this.
And it's a famous AI theorist named Ray Solomonoff.
And he put black paint on all his windows
and found that he had a 25- or 26-hour natural cycle, which
was very nice.
And this persisted for several months.
I had another friend who lived in the New York subways
because his apartment was in a building that
had an entrance to the subway.
And he stayed out of daylight for six months.
But anyway, he too found that he preferred
to be on a 25- or 26-hour day than 24.
I'm rambling.
So we apparently have several different systems.
So there's dead reckoning system,
where some internal clocks are regulating your behavior.
And then there are other systems where people are very much
affected by the amount of light and so forth.
So we probably have four or five ways
of doing almost everything that's important.
And then people get various disorders
where some of these systems fail and a person doesn't
have a regular sleep cycle.
And there are disorders where people fall asleep.
What's it called when you fall asleep every few minutes?
Narcolepsy.
Narcolepsy and all sorts of wonderful disorders
just because the brain has evolved
so many different ways of doing anything that's very important.
Yeah?
Can you describe the best piece of criticism
for the Society of Mind Theory?
Best piece of what?
The best criticism.
Oh.
It reminds me of an article I recently
read about the possibility of a virus for what's
the disorder where?
Alzheimer's?
No.
Actually, there isn't any generally accepted
cause for Alzheimer's, as far as I know.
What?
Somebody did an experiment where they injected Alzheimer's
infected matter into someone and they got the same lack.
Oh, well, right.
I wonder if that's a popular theory.
No, what's the one where people are?
Fibromyalgia.
Say it again?
Yes, right.
Which is not recognized by most theorists
to be a definite disease.
But there's been an episode in which somebody,
I forget what her name is, was pretty sure
that she had found a virus for it.
And every now and then, somebody revives that theory
and tries to get more evidence for it.
Anyway, there must be disorders where the programming is bad
rather than a biochemical disorder,
because whatever the brain is, the adult brain
certainly has a very large component
of what we would, in any other case,
consider to be software, namely lots of things
that you've learned, including ways for one part of the brain
to discover how to modulate or turn on or turn off
other parts of the brain.
And since we've only had this kind of cortex
for four or five million years, it's
probably still got lots of bugs.
Evolution never knows what, when you make a new innovation,
you don't know what's going to come after that that
might find bugs and ways to get short-range advantages,
short-term advantages at the expense of longer-term
advantages.
So lots of mental diseases might be software bugs.
And a few of them are known to be
connected to abnormal secretions of chemicals and so forth.
But even in those cases, it's hard to be sure
that the overproduction or underproduction
of a neurologically important chemical is a biological
disorder or a functional disorder
because some part of the nervous system
might have found some trick to cause abnormal secretions
of some substance.
So that's the sort of thing that we
can expect to learn a great deal more about in the next
generation because of the lower cost and greater resolution
of brain scanning techniques and what's his name,
and new synthetic ways of putting in fluorescent
chemicals into a normal brain without injuring it much
so that you can now do sort of macrochemical experiments
of seeing what chemicals are being secreted
in the brain with new kinds of scanning techniques.
So neuroscience is going to be very exciting
in the next generation with all the great new instruments.
As you know, my complaint is that somehow introduction
to the, I'm not saying any of the present AI
theories have been confirmed to tell you
that the brain works as such and such a rule-based system
or such and such a, or use Winston type representations
or Roger Shank type representations
or scripts or frames or whatever.
And the next to last chapter of the emotion machine
sort of summarizes, I think, almost a dozen
different AI theories of ways to represent knowledge.
Nobody has confirmed that any of those particular ideas
represent what happens in a mammalian brain.
And the problem is that the, to me,
is that the neuroscience community just
doesn't read that stuff and doesn't design experiments
to look for them.
David has been moving from computer science and AI
into that.
So he's my current source of knowledge
about what's happening there.
Have any of you been following contemporary neuroscience?
That's strange.
Yeah.
So you were talking about software a little bit.
So I think they analyzed Einstein's brain
and realized that's why I talked about the glia cells.
And maybe he had a lot more glia cells than normal neurons.
And so do you believe that the intelligence of humans
is more on the software side or on the hardware side?
We have computers that are very, very powerful.
Could we create software that we can run these machines that
were produced in humans?
I don't see any reason to doubt it.
As far as we know, computers can simulate anything.
What they can't do yet, I suppose,
is simulate large-scale quantum phenomenon
because if you know the Feynman theory of quantum mechanics,
it's that if you have a network of physical systems that
are connected, then it's in the nature of physics
that whatever happens from one state to another
in the real universe, whatever happens actually
happens by the wave function.
The wave function represents the sum
of the activities propagating through all possible paths.
So in some sense, that's too exponential to simulate
on a computer.
In other words, I believe the biggest supercomputers
can simulate a helium atom today fairly well.
But they can't simulate a lithium atom
because it's sort of four or five layers of exclamation.
It's between 2 to the 2 to the 2 to the 2
and 4 to the 4 to the 4 to the 4.
Those numbers get out of hand.
But I suspect that the reason the brain works
is that it's evolved to prevent quantum effects from making
things complicated.
The great thing about a neuron is that generally speaking,
a neuron fires all or none.
And at this point, you have to get
a full half-volt of potential between the neuron's fibers
surrounding fluid.
And that's a half a volt is a big difference.
So Blake, do you believe that the software that we have right
now is equivalent to, for example, the intelligence
that we have in dogs or, for example, simple animals?
Is the difference that we just need to implement the software,
like modify the software?
Or somehow we need to create a whole different software that
knows there doesn't seem to be much difference
in the architecture of the local architecture.
I'm turning the microphone off.
I want to be quiet.
Oh, can I turn it off?
Yes.
It's not green.
Yeah, so throw the switch.
Is it green now?
Now it's green.
The difference between the dog and a person
is the huge frontal cortex.
I think the rest of it is fairly similar.
And I presume the hippocampus and the amygdala
and the structures that control which parts of the cortex
are used for what are somewhat different.
But the small details of the all mammalian brains
are practically the same.
I mean, basically you can't make an early genetic change
in how neurons work, or all the brain cells of the offspring
would be somewhat different and the thing would be dead.
So evolution has this property that generally there
are only two places in the development of an embryo
that evolution can operate, namely
in the pre-placental stage.
You can change the way the egg breaks up and evolves
and you can have amazing things like identical twins happen
without any effect on the nature of the adult offspring.
Or you can change the things that happen most recently
in evolution, like little tweaks in how some part of the nervous
system works if it doesn't change earlier stages.
However, mutations that operate in the middle of all that
and change the number of segments in the embryo,
I guess you could have a longer tail or a shorter tail
and that won't affect much.
But if you change the 12 segments of the spine
that the brain develops from, you'd
get a huge alteration in how that animal will think.
So we're sort of, in other words,
evolution cannot change intermediate structures
very much or the animal won't live.
Bob Lohler.
If one thinks of comparing a person to a dog,
would it not be most appropriate to think of those persons
who are like the wild boy of southern France
who grew up in the woods without any language
and say that if you're going to look at an individual's
intelligence, that would be a fair comparison with a dog.
Whereas what we have when we think of people today
is people who have learned so much through interaction
with other people that the transmission of culture
is it not essentially ways of thinking
that have been learned throughout the history
of civilization and some of us are
able to pass on to others?
Sure.
Although if you expose a dog to humans,
it doesn't learn language.
It may or may not come.
Right.
But presumably, language is fairly recent.
So you could have mutations in the structure of the language
centers and still have a human that's alive.
And it might be better at language
than most other people or somewhat worse.
So we could have lots of small mutations in anything
that's been recently evolved.
But the frontal cortexes and the human cortex
is really very large compared to the rest of the brain.
Same in dolphins and a couple of other animals.
I forget.
Whales.
Yeah.
So the reason why I ask that is that it seems to me
that we have some quality, like some kind of we
can see the world, like add some qualities to the world.
And this is what I would call consciousness.
And for me, it seems that dogs also
have this quality of seeing the world
and adding qualities to the world.
So maybe this is good, this is bad.
There are different qualities for different beings.
And the software that we produce right now
seems to be maybe faster and maybe do more tests than what
maybe a dog does.
But for me, it doesn't seem that it has essentially
these quality things.
It doesn't have consciousness in this sense.
It doesn't aggregate quality to the things in the world.
Well, I think I know what you're getting at.
But you're using that word consciousness,
which I've decided to abandon because it's
36 different things.
And probably a dog has five or six of them or 31.
I don't know.
But one question is, do you think
a dog can think several steps ahead
and consider two alternative?
That's funny.
Oh, let's make this abstract.
So here's a world, and the dog is here,
and it wants to get here.
And there are all sorts of obstacles in it.
So can the dog say, well, if I went this way,
I'd have such and such difficulty,
whereas if I went this way, I'd have this difficulty.
Well, I think this one looks better.
Do you think your dog considers two or three alternatives
and makes plans?
I have no idea, but the curious thing about a person
is you can decide that you're going to not act
in the situation until you've considered 16 plans.
And then one part of your brain is
making these different approaches to the problems.
And another part of your brain is saying, well, now
I've made five plans, and I'm beginning
to forget the first one, so I better reformulate it.
And you're doing all of these self-conscious in the sense
that you're making plans that involve predicting
what decisions you will make.
And instead of making them, you make the decision to say,
I'm going to follow out these two plans
and use the result of that to decide which one to do.
Do you think a dog does any of that?
Does it look around and say, well, I could go that way
or this way?
I remember our dog was good at if you throw a ball,
it would go and get it.
And if you threw two balls, it would go and get both of them.
And sometimes, if you threw three balls,
it would go and get them all.
And sometimes, if a ball would roll under a couch
that it couldn't reach, it would get the other two,
and it would think, and then it would run back to the kitchen
where that ball is usually found.
And then it would come back disappointed.
So what does that mean?
Did it have parallel plans?
Or does it make a new one when the previous one fails,
and they're not actually parallel?
What's your guess?
How far ahead does a dog think?
Do you have a dog?
Yeah, I do have a dog, but I don't
believe that's the essential part of beings
that have some kind of advanced brain.
We can plan ahead.
Humans can plan ahead.
I don't think the fundamental part of intelligence.
Humans, I think Winston says that humans
are better than primates in they can understand stories,
and they can join together stories.
But somehow, I don't buy the story
that primates are just like rule planners.
I think somehow we have some quality machine of the world,
and somehow we're not writing a software.
But you know, it's funny.
Computer science teaches us things
that weren't obvious before.
It might turn out that if you're a computer
and you only have two registers, then, well, in principle,
you could do anything, but that's another matter.
But it might turn out that maybe a dog has only
two registers and a person has four.
And a trivial thing like that makes
it possible to have two plans and put them in suspense
and think about the strategy and come back and change one.
Whereas if you only had two registers,
your mind would be much lower order,
and there's no big difference.
Computer science tells us that the usual way
of thinking about abilities might be wrong.
Before computer science, people didn't really
have that kind of idea.
Many years ago, I was in a contest.
I mean, you know, a science, because some of our friends
showed that you could make a universal computer
with four registers.
And I had discovered some other things,
and I managed to show that you could make a universal computer
with just two registers.
And that was a big surprise to a lot of people.
But there never was anything in the history
of psychology of that nature.
So there never were really technical theories of it's
really computational complexity.
What does it take to solve certain kinds of problems?
And until the 1960s, there weren't any theories of that.
And I'm not sure that that aspect of computer science
has actually reached many psychologists or neuroscientists.
I'm not even sure that it's relevant,
but it's really interesting that the difference between two
and three registers could make an exponential difference
in how fast you could solve certain kinds of problems
and not others.
So maybe there'll be a little more mathematical psychology
in the next couple of decades.
Yeah.
So in artificial intelligence, how much of our efforts
should be devoted to reflecting on our own thinking as humans
and trying to figure out what's really
going on inside our brains and then trying
to implement that versus observing and identifying
what kinds of problems we as humans can solve
and then come up with any sort of way for a computer
to, in a human-like way, solve these problems?
There are a lot of nice questions.
I don't think it doesn't make any sense
to suggest that we think about what's
happening in our brains, because that
takes scientific instruments.
But it certainly makes sense to go over
older theories of psychology and ask what kinds of procedures
to solve a certain kind of problem, what kind of procedures
are absolutely necessary.
And you could find some things like that,
like how many registers would you need
and what kinds of conditionals and what kind of addressing.
So I think a lot of cognitive psychology,
modern cognitive psychology, is of that character.
But I don't see any way to introspect and well
enough to guess how your brain does something,
because we're just not that conscious.
We don't have access to.
You could think for 10 years about,
how do I think of the next word to speak?
And unlikely that you would.
You might get some new ideas about how
this might have happened, in fact.
But you couldn't be sure.
Well, I take it back.
Probably people, you could probably
get some correct theories by being lucky and clever.
And then you'd have to find a neuroscientist
to design an experiment to see if there's any evidence for that.
In particular, I'd like to convince some neurologists
to consider the idea of K lines.
That's described, I think, in both of my books.
And think of experiments to see if you
could get them to light up or otherwise localize.
And once you have in your mind the idea
that maybe the way one brain connects,
sends information to another is over something like K lines,
which I think I talked about that the other day,
random superimposed coding on parallel wires,
then maybe you could think of experiments
that even present brain scanning techniques
could use to localize these.
My main concern is that the way they do brain scanning now
is to set thresholds to see which brain centers light up
and which go turn off.
And then they say, oh, I see.
This activity looks like it happens
in the lateral hippocampus, because you see that light up.
I think that there should be at least
a couple of neuroscientist groups
who do the opposite, which is to reduce the contrast.
And when there are several brain centers that
seem to be involved in an activity,
then say something to the patient
and look for one area to get 2% dimmer and another
to look 4% brighter and say, that
might mean that there's a K line going from this one
to that one with an inhibitory effect on this or that.
But as far as I know right now, every paper
I've ever seen published showing brain centers lighting up
has high contrast.
And so they're missing all the small things.
And maybe they're only seeing the end result of the process
where a little thinking has gone on
with all these intricate, low-intensity interactions.
And then the thing decides, oh, OK, I'm going to do this.
And you conclude that that brain center which lit up
is the one that decided to do this,
whereas it's the result of a very small, fast avalanche.
OK.
Have you seen the one a couple weeks ago
about reading out the visual field in real time?
From the visual cortex?
Yes.
Quite a nice hack.
They aren't actually reading out the visual field.
They, for each subject, they do a massive amount of training
where they flash thousands of one-second video clips
and assemble a database of very small perturbations
in different parts of the visual cortex lighting up.
And then they show a novel video to each of the subjects
and basically just do a linear combination of all
of the videos that they've done in the training phase
weighted by how closely things line up in the brain.
And you can sort of see what's going on.
It's quite striking.
Can you tell what they're thinking?
You can only tell what they're seeing.
But I think.
Yeah, if your eyes are closed, your primary visual cortex
probably doesn't do anything, does it?
I think it's just, yeah.
But the secondary one might be representing things
that might be there.
Yes.
So the goal of the authors of this paper
is eventually to literally make movies out of dreams.
But that's a long way off.
It's an old idea in science fiction.
How many of you read science fiction?
Wow.
That's a majority.
Who's the best new writer?
He's been writing a long time.
Yeah.
As I had dinner with Stevenson at the Hillis's
a couple of years ago.
Yeah.
So from what I understood, it seems
that you're saying that the difference between us
and, for example, dogs is just a confrontation of power.
So do you believe that the difference between dogs
and computers is also just a confrontation?
What is the difference between dogs and a Turing machine?
Well, it might be that only humans and maybe some
of their closest relatives can imagine a sequence.
In other words, the simplest, oldest theories in psychology
were the theories like David Hume
had the idea of association.
One idea in the mind or brain causes another idea
to appear in another.
So that means that a brain that's learned associations
or learn if-then rule-based systems
can make chains of things.
But the question is, can any animal other than humans
imagine two different situations and then compare them and say,
if I did this and then that, how would the result
differ from doing that and then this?
If you look at Jerry Sussman's thesis,
if you're at MIT, a good thing to do is to read the,
when you're taking your course, you
should read the PhD thesis of your professor.
It not only will help you understand better
what the professor said, you'll get a higher grade if you care
and many other advantages, like you'll actually
be able to talk to him and his mind won't throw up.
So I don't know if a dog can recapitulate a,
can the dog think, I think I'll go around this fence
and when I get to this tree, I'll do this, I'll pee on it.
That's what dogs do.
And then I'll, whereas if I go this way,
something else will happen.
It might be that pre-primates can't do much of that.
On the other hand, if you ask, what is the song of the whale?
What's the whale that has this 20-minute song?
It's the, I think my conjecture is that a whale has
to swim 1,000 miles or several hundred miles sometimes
to get the food it wants because things change.
And each group of whales, humpback whales,
I guess, sing this song that's about 20 minutes long.
And nobody has made a good conjecture
about what's the content of that song.
But it's shared among the animals.
And it goes, they can hear it 20 or 50 miles away
and repeat it.
And it changes every season.
So I suspect that the obvious thing that it should be about
is, where's the food these days?
Where are the best flocks of fish to eat?
Because a whale can't afford to swim 200 miles to the place
where its favorite fish were last year and find it empty.
It takes a lot of energy to cross the ocean.
So maybe those animals have the ability
to remember very long sequences and even some semantics
connected with it.
I don't know if dogs have anything like that.
Do dogs ever seem to be talking to each other?
Or are they just?
So I have a story about dogs.
So apparently, in Moscow, not all dogs,
but a very small fraction of the stray dogs
in the city have learned how to ride the metro.
They live out in the suburbs because, I guess, people
give them less trouble when they're out in the suburbs.
And then they take the subway each day
into the city center, where there are more people.
And they have various strategies for begging in the city center.
So for instance, they find some guy with a sandwich.
And they bark really loudly behind the guy.
And the guy would drop the sandwich.
And then they'd steal it.
Or they have a pack of them, and they all know each other.
And they send out a really cute one to beg for food.
And so they'll give the cute one food.
And the cute one brings it back to everyone else.
And simply navigating the subway
is actually a bit complicated for a dog.
But somehow, a very small group of dogs in Moscow
have learned how to do it, like figure out where their stop is,
get on, get off.
Our dog once hopped on the green line and got off at Park Street.
So she was missing for a while.
And somebody at Park Street called up and said,
your dog is here.
So I went down and got her.
And the agent said, you know, we had a dog that
came to Park Street every day and changed trains
and took the red line to somewhere.
And finally, we found out that it used
to go to work with its owner every day.
And he died.
And the dog took the same trip every day.
The tea people understood that he shouldn't be bothered with it.
Our dog chased cars.
Was it Jenny?
And it was terrible because we knew
she was going to get hurt.
And finally, a car squashed her leg.
And she was laid up for a while with a somewhat broken leg.
And I thought, well, she won't chase cars anymore.
But she did.
But what she wouldn't do is go to the intersection of Carlton
and Ivy Street anymore, which is.
So she had learned something, but it wasn't the right thing.
I'm not sure I answered her.
Go ahead.
Thank you.
Well, actually, according to Iso,
there's this story that you gave in Chapter 2
about the girl who's digging dirt.
So in the case where she learns whether digging dirt
is a good or bad activity is when
there is somebody with whom she had an attachment
bond with president who's telling her
whether it's good or bad.
And in the case where she learns to avoid that spot
is when something bad happens to her in the spot.
So in a sense, the dog is behaving just like that logic.
Yes, except that the dog is oriented toward location
rather than something else.
It's about a possible hierarchy of higher order representation
schemes of knowledge.
There's like semantic nets on top and at the bottom.
There's like neural network in the middle of KLIs
and on the bottom there's something such a.
So the way I thought about the questions
that were just asked that humans, it's just natural to me
that we need all the intermediate representations
in order to support something like semantic nets.
And it seems natural to me to think that humans of all these,
the whole hierarchy of representations by dogs
might have something only in the middle,
like they might have something like neural nets or something.
So my question is, what behaviors
that you could observe in real life
could only be done with one of these intermediate
recommendations of knowledge that
can't be done with something like machine learning?
Hmm.
You mean machine learning of what,
of some particular kind?
The kind that's currently fashionable, I think.
Kind of like with like Qt data set before sort
of calibration of some grammar.
It seems to me that if you recognize a behavior like that,
it might be a worthy intermediate goal
to be able to model that instead of trying
to model something like natural language, which
is you might need the first part to get the second part.
Well, it would be nice to know.
I wonder how much is known about elephants, which are awfully
smart compared to, I suspect that they are very good
at making plans because it's so easy for an elephant
to make a fatal mistake.
So unfortunately, probably nobody, no research group
has enough budget to study that kind of animal
because it's just too expensive.
How smart are elephants?
Anybody?
I've never interacted with one.
I'm not sure if you have a question.
The question is, are there behaviors
that you need an intermediate level of the repetition
of knowledge in order to perform that you don't need
like the highest level, like the semantic,
like basically natural language in order to do?
So you could say that if I saw an animal doing this behavior,
I know that it has some intermediate level
of representation of knowledge.
That's more than kind of a brute force machine learning
approach.
Because what's discussed before, a computer
can do pathfinding with just like a brute force approach.
But I don't think that's how humans do it or animals do it.
I can't think of a good example.
It's just hard to think of any animals besides us that
it's just hard to think of any animals besides us that have
really elaborate semantic networks.
There's Coco, who's a gorilla that apparently
had hundreds of words.
I think the question is to find something lower than words.
Like maybe Betty the crow with her.
With that stick?
Yeah.
How many of you have seen the crow movie?
She bends the, she has a wire that she bends
and pulls something out of a tube.
I don't think machine learning can do that.
So I don't think you need semantics.
I have a parrot who lives in a three dimensional cage.
And she knows how to get from any place to another.
And if she's in a hurry, she'll find a new way
at the risk of injuring a wing because there
are a lot of sticks in the way.
So flying is risky.
Our daughter Julie once visited Coco, the gorilla.
And she was introduced Coco's in a cage.
And Penny, who is Coco's owner, introduces Julie
in sign language.
Coco, it's not words.
It's not spoken.
It's sign language.
So Julie gets some name.
And she's introduced to Coco.
And Coco likes Julie.
So Coco says, let me out.
And Penny says, no, you can't get out.
Coco says, then let Julie in.
And I thought that showed some fairly abstract reasoning
or representation.
And Penny didn't let Julie in.
But Coco seemed to have a fair amount of declarative syntax.
I don't know if she could do passives or anything like that.
If you're interested, you probably
can look it up on the web.
Penny thought that Coco knew 600 or 700 words.
And a friend of ours was a teenager who worked for her.
And what's his name?
And he was convinced that Coco knew more than 1,000 words.
But he said, you see, I'm a teenager.
And I'm still good at picking up gestures and clues better
than the adults here.
Anyway, I gather Coco is still there.
And I don't know if she's still learning more words.
But every now and then, we get a letter
asking to send more money.
Oh, in the last lecture, I couldn't
think of the right crypt arithmetic example.
I think that's the one that the new old Simon book starts out
with.
So obviously, m is 1.
And then I bet some of you could figure that out
in four or five minutes.
Has anybody figured it out yet?
Help send more questions.
Yeah.
I have an example of where, since I go out
to a restaurant of this type of exotic food
that I've never, ever had before,
and I end up getting sick from it.
So what determines what I learn from this?
Because there are many different possibilities here.
There's the one possibility of I learn
to avoid the specific food I ate.
Another possibility is I learn to avoid that type of food,
because it might contain some sort of spice
that I react to badly.
And the third possibility, there might be more,
is I learn to avoid that restaurant,
because that just might be a bad restaurant.
So in this case, it's not entirely clear
which one I ought to pick.
And of course, maybe in real life,
I might go there again and empirically try another food
or try the same food at different restaurants.
But what do you think about this in that scenario?
What causes people to pick which one?
The trouble is we keep thinking of ourselves as people.
And you should think of yourself as a sort of petri dish
with a trillion bacteria in it.
And it's really not important to you what you eat,
but your intestinal bacteria are the ones who are really
going to suffer, because they're not used to anything new.
So I don't know what conclusion to draw from that.
But...
Seriously, you mentioned David Hume,
not that not represented as associations.
And that occurs to me as being sort of like a wiki structure
where entries have tags.
So an entry might be defined by what tags it has
and what associations it has.
I'm wondering if that structure has been,
if somebody has attempted to code that
into some kind of virtual structure,
has there been any success with that idea into potential AI?
I don't know how to answer that.
Do any psychologists use semantic networks
as representations?
Pat, do you know, has anybody, I know,
is anyone building an AI system with semantic representations
or semantic networks anymore?
Or is it all, everything I've seen
has gone probabilistic in the last few years?
Your project, do you have any competitors?
No.
Any idea what the IBM people are using?
I saw a long article that I didn't read yet.
My impression is traditional information retrieval
plus 100 tags plus machine learning.
They seem to have a whole lot of different,
slightly different representations
that they switch among.
But none of them are very semantic.
Well, they probably have, I don't know,
does anybody know what the answer is?
But they must have little frame-like things
for the standard questions.
Of course, the thing doesn't answer any,
it doesn't do any reasoning, as far as you can tell.
Right.
So it's trying to match sentences in the database
with the question.
Well, what's your theory of why there aren't other groups
working on what we used to and you are?
Well, when those are computing is a fact.
And if you can do better in less time that way than figuring
out how it really works, then that's what you do.
No one does research on chess.
No one does any research on how humans might play chess
because the build-over computers have won.
Right.
There were some articles on chess and checkers
early in the game.
But nothing recent, as far as I know.
So it's a local, in many ways, it's a local maximum phenomenon.
The build-over computing stuff has got up to a certain local
maximum.
And so you can do better than that some other way
but in too fast a time.
Well, I wonder if we could invent a new TV show where
the questions are interesting.
Like I'm obsessed with the question of why you can pull
something with a string but you can't push it.
And in fact, what was this?
We had a student who actually did something
with that a long time ago.
I've lost track of him.
But how could you make a TV show that had common sense
questions rather than ones about sports and actors?
Well, if you imagine what happens when you push with a string,
it's hard to explain that in words.
Hypocles.
It's easy to imagine.
Yeah.
So you can simulate it.
So I have a question.
So suppose in the future we can create our own,
which is as intelligent as human, as smart.
And how we should evaluate it?
When do we know that we reach, like, certainly, like,
which test should pass or which should, I don't know.
So for example, Watson, right?
It can answer pretty hard questions and seem
to be intelligent.
But what all it is about is intelligence.
Pretty hard questions and seem to be intelligent.
But what all it is doing is doing some algorithms
and then calculating some probabilities and stuff.
Humans don't do that.
They try to understand the questions,
and they assume for the answer, right?
But then suppose you can create a robot that can behave as it is.
Like, I don't know.
How would you evaluate?
Like, when do you know that you reach something?
That's sort of funny because if it's any good,
you wouldn't have that question.
You'd say, well, what can't it do?
And why not?
And you'd argue with it.
In other words, people talk about passing the Turing test
or whatever.
And it's hard to imagine a machine that you converse with
for a while.
And then when you're told it's a machine, you're surprised.
I think that, for example, we can make a machine
to say some very intelligent and smart things
because it may know all this text information
from different books and all this information
it has somewhere in the database, right?
But then when people speak,
they kind of understand what they're speaking.
How do you know if someone doesn't understand something,
doesn't understand, or does it have to understand at all?
Well, I would ask you questions like, why can't you
push something with a string?
Well, anyone have a Google working?
What does Google say if you ask it that?
Maybe it'll quote me or someone who's, yeah?
Yeah?
How would you answer that question?
Why can't you pull but not push?
I'd say, well, it would buckle.
And then they would say, what do you mean by buckle?
And then I'd say, oh, it would fold up so that it got shorter
without exerting any force at the end or blah, blah.
I don't know.
There are lots of answers.
How would you answer it?
A physicist might say, if you got it really very, very,
very straight, you could push it with a string.
But quantum mechanics would say you can't.
Yeah?
I feel like if you like the typical or an interesting show
would be have an alternate cookie show or something,
where you have to use objects that's not normally found
to have that used.
So you want to paint a room, but you're not given a brush.
You're given, say, a sponge, a piece of cloth, and eggplants.
You want to paint it purple.
So it has to represent the thing in a different way
other than words.
Words.
That's interesting.
When I was in graduate school, I took a course in knot theory.
And in fact, you couldn't talk about them.
If anybody had a question, they'd
have to run up to the board and they'd
have to do something like this.
Is that a knot?
No.
No, that's just a loop.
But if you were restricted to words,
it would take a half hour.
That's interesting.
Yeah?
You mentioned solving the string puzzle
by imagining the result. And I think I heard someone else say,
computers can do that in some way.
You can simulate a string.
And we know in the physics that you
could give a reasonable approximation of the string.
But I find that the question that is often not asked in AI
by computers is, how does one choose the correct model
in which to answer questions?
There's a lot of questions we're really
good at answering with computers.
And some of them genetic algorithms are good for.
Some of them basic statistics.
Some of them formal logic.
Some of them physics simulation.
But to me, this is the core question,
because this is what people decide and no one
seems to have ever tackled in AI.
Well, for instance, you have to, if somebody asks the question,
you have to make up a biography of that person
because the same question from different people
would get really different answers.
Why does a kettle make a noise when the water boils?
The water boils.
If you know that the other person is a physicist,
and it's easy to think of things to say,
but it's not a very good example.
What's the context of that?
How do you, in a human conversation,
how does each person know what to say next?
I guess one question is, how do people
decide what AI methods to use to tackle a problem?
And I guess the more fundamental question
is, when people are solving problems,
how do they decide how they're going to think about the problem?
Are they going to think about it by visualizing it,
think about it by trying a different thing,
think about it by analogy or morphology?
Of all the tools we have, why do we get the ones we do?
Yeah, well, that goes back to the if you make a list of the 50
most common ways to think, and somebody asks you a question
or ask why does such and such happen,
how do you decide which of your ways to think about it?
And I suspect that that's another knowledge base.
So we have common sense knowledge about,
if you let go of an object, it will fall.
And then we have more general knowledge
about what happens when an object falls.
Why didn't it break?
Well, it actually did, because here's
a little white thing which turned into dust.
And so that's why I think you need
to have five or six or how many different levels
of representation.
So as soon as somebody asks a question,
one part of your brain is coming up with your first idea.
Another part of your brain is saying,
is this a question about physics or philosophy
or is it a social question?
Did this person ask it because they actually want to know
or they want to trap me?
Or so I think generally this idea of there
must be many kinds of society of mind models that people have.
And each person, whenever you're talking to somebody,
you choose some model of what is this conversation about?
Am I trying to accomplish something by this discussion?
Is it really an interesting question?
Do I not want to offend with the person
or do I want to make him go away forever?
And little parts of your brain are making all these decisions
for you.
I'd like to introduce Bob Lawler, who's visiting.
One of my favorite stories about Feynman
comes from asking him at dinner one night.
I asked him how he got to be so smart.
And he said that when he was an undergraduate here,
he would consider every time he was able to solve a problem
just the beginning step of how to exploit that.
And what he would then do would be
to try to reformulate the problem in as many
different representations as he could
and then use his solution of the first problem
as a guide in working out alternate representations
and procedures in that.
The consequence, according to him,
was that he became very good at knowing
which was the most fit representation to use
in solving any particular problem that he encountered.
And he said that that's where his legendary capability
of being so quick with good solutions and good methods
the solutions came from.
So maybe a criteria for an intelligent machine
would be one that had a number of 15 different ways
of thinking and applied them regularly
to develop alternative information
about different methods of problem solving.
He would expect that to have some facility at choosing
based on its experience.
Yeah, he wrote something about because the other physicists
would argue about whether to use Heisenberg matrices
or Schrodinger's equation.
And he thought he was the only one who
knew how to solve each problem both ways
because most of the other physicists
would get very good at one or the other.
He had another feature, which was that if you argued with him,
sometimes he would say, oh, you're right.
I was wrong.
Like he was once arguing with Fredkin about,
could you have clocks all over the universe
that were synchronized?
And the standard idea is you couldn't because of relativity.
And Fredkin said, well, suppose you start out on Earth
and you send a huge army of little bacteria-sized clocks
and send them through all possible routes to every place
and figure out and compensate for all the accelerations
they had experienced on the path,
then wouldn't you get a synchronous time everywhere?
And Feynman said, you're right.
I was wrong without blinking.
He may have been wrong.
More questions?
And then I want to stay in line with this question
about how do we know what method to use for solving problems.
I'm kind of curious how we know what data set
and what data to use when solving problems.
Because we have so much sensory input in the moment
and so much data that we have from experience.
But when you get a problem, you instantly
I guess can be a sort of a solution for that.
But if it turns to how you could possibly represent
good data relationships in a way that a computer might be able
to do, because right now the problem is that we always
have to very narrowly define a problem for a machine
to be able to solve it.
But I feel like we could come up with good methods
for filtering massive data sets to just what might be relevant.
It doesn't involve trial and error.
Yes.
So the thing must be that if you have a problem,
how do you characterize it?
How do you think, what kind of problem is this?
And what method is good for that kind of problem?
So I suppose that people vary a lot, and it's a great question.
That's what the critics do.
They say, what kind of problem is this?
How do I recognize this particular predicament?
And I wish there were some psychologists
who thought about that the way Newell and Simon did.
God, in the 1960s, it's 50 years ago.
How many of you have seen that book called
Human Problem Solving?
It's a big, thick book, and it's got all sorts of chapters.
That's the one I mentioned the other day, where they actually
had some theories of human problem solving
and simulated this.
They gave subjects problems like this and said,
we want you to figure out what numbers those are.
And they lied to the subjects and said,
this is an important kind of problem in cryptography.
The secret agents need to know how
to decode cryptograms of this sort, where usually it's
the other way around.
The numbers stand for letters, and there's
some complicated coding.
But these are simple cases, so you have
to figure out that sort of thing.
And then the book has various chapters
on theories of how you recognize different kinds of problems
and select strategies.
And of course, some people are better than others.
And believe it or not, at MIT, there
was almost a whole decade of psychologists
here who were studying the psychology of five-person
groups.
It became, suppose you take five people and put them in a room
and give them problems like this.
Or not the same cryptography, but little puzzles
that require some cleverness to solve.
And you record a video.
They didn't have video in those days, so it was actual film.
There's a whole generation of publications
about the social and cognitive behavior
of these little groups of people.
They zeroed in on five-person groups
for reasons I don't remember, but it turned out
that almost always when you had that,
the group divided into two competitive groups
with two and three, and every now and then
they would reorganize.
But it was more a study in social relations
than in cognitive psychology.
But it's an interesting book, and there
must be contemporary studies like that
of how people cooperate.
But I just haven't been in that environment.
Any of you taken a psychology course recently?
Not a one?
Just wonder what's happened to general psychology.
I used to sit in on Teuber and a couple of other lecturers
here, and the psychology course was
sort of like 20% optical illusions and stuff like that.
They also concentrate a lot on developmental psychology.
Well, that's nice to hear, because I
don't believe there was any of that in Teuber's class.
I think Professor Gabrielli now teaches the introductory
psychology, and he still wants to talk about it.
Do they still believe Piaget, or do they think that he was wrong?
I think they probably take the same approach as with Freud.
They would say, great ideas and a revolution,
but they also don't think he's the end of the world.
Well, he got a
I know plenty of the childhood development class.
You read Piaget, but you read the books.
Yeah, in Piaget's later years, he got algebra envy,
and he wanted to be more scientific
and studied logic and a few things like that
and became less scientific.
It was sort of sad to, I can imagine,
being browbeaten by mathematicians,
because they're the ones who were getting published.
How many books did Piaget?
Incredible numbers.
If I may add a comment about Piaget here,
that really comes from an old friend of many of us, Seymour.
As you know, he was, of course, Piaget's mathematician
for many years.
We got back from Piaget's lab.
But Seymour said that he felt that Piaget's best work was
his early work, especially building his case studies.
And one time when we were talking
about the issue of focusing from the AI lab,
the work done in psychology here,
Seymour said he felt that was less necessary than more
of a concentration on AI, because he expected
in the future the world of study of the mind
would separate into two individual studies, one much
more biological, like the neurosciences of today,
and the other focused more on the structure of knowledge
and on representations and, in effect,
the genetic epistemology of Piaget.
And he added that something that was a quote later in the end
was that even if Piaget's marvelous theory today
proved to be wrong, he would ensure
that whatever replaced it would be
of theory of the same sort, one of the development
of knowledge in all its changes.
So I don't think people will get away from Piaget however much
they want to.
I don't think so either.
I meant to introduce our visitor here,
because Bob Lowler here has reproduced a good many
of the kinds of studies that Piaget did in the 1930s
and 40s.
And if you look him up on the web,
you'll must have a few papers.
Actually, I'd better tell you what the website is,
because it's still hidden from web probes.
It's nlcsa.net.
That would be hard to.
Natural Learning Case Study Archive.net.
It's still in process, still in development,
but it's worth looking at that.
How many children did Piaget have?
Well, Piaget had three children whose development he studied.
But what he did was to mix together
the information from all three studies
and supported the ideas with which he began.
So it was illustrations of his theories.
Anyway, Bob has quite a lot of studies
about how his children developed concepts of number
and geometry and things like that.
And I don't know of anyone else since Piaget
who's continued to do those sorts of experiments.
There were quite a lot at Piaget's Institute
in Geneva for some years after Piaget was gone.
But I think it's pretty much closed now, hasn't it?
Well, the last psychologist that Piaget hired was Jacques
Vanech, who was no longer at the university.
He retired, and it has been taken over
by the neo-Piagetians who are doing something different.
Is there any other place?
Well, there was Yoichi's lab on children in Japan.
There aren't many people who take Piaget seriously
in this country as well as others.
So Robert mentioned that fire had
more representations of the world
than usual people.
When I talked about Einstein and the glia cells,
I referred to that because I believe
k-lines is a way of representing the world.
And maybe Einstein had better ways of representing the world.
And I believe that, for example, agents and resources
are not different from the Turing machines.
You can create a very simple Turing machine
that acts like agents, and you have some mental states.
But there is no, I believe, good way right now
of representing the world and updating
this representation of the world.
It seems to me that when you grow up,
you're learning how to represent the world better and better.
And you have some layers, and that's all k-lines.
And if glia cells are actually related to k-lines,
so it means that Einstein had a better
hardware in representing the world.
That's why he would be smarter than other people.
Well, it's hard to I'm sure that that's right,
that you have a certain amount of hardware,
but you can reconfigure some of it.
Nobody really knows, but some brain centers
may have only a few neurons.
And maybe there's some retrograde signals
so that if two brain centers are simultaneously activated,
then usually the signals only go one way from one to the other.
Have to go through a third one to get back.
But it could be that the neurons have a property
that if two centers are activated,
maybe that causes more connections
to be made between them that can then be programmed more.
I don't think anybody really has a clear idea of whether you
can grow new connections between brain centers that
are far apart.
Does anybody know?
Is there anything?
Yeah?
One of the knowledge that there was no such thing
as adult neurogenesis, and now it
is known that it exists in certain limited regions
of the brain.
So in the future, it may be known
that it exists everywhere.
ecent ones,
but he had an army of students, and he was extremely funny.
What else?
Continuing on the idea of hardware versus software,
what do you think about the idea that intelligences or humans
may need strong instincts when they're born?
And the interplay between their instincts,
like they know to cry when they're hungry
or to look for their mother.
And they need these instincts because they
need these instincts in order to develop
higher orders of knowledge.
You'd have to ask L. Ron Hubbard for it.
Thank you.
I don't recall any real attempts to see.
I don't think I've ever run across anybody
claiming to have correlations between prenatal experience
and the development of intelligence.
I was talking about before intelligence
has really developed, before you learn language,
you need to have a motivation to do some things.
So you need to have instinctual reactions to things.
And by accumulation of experiential knowledge,
after you're born, you need to have that.
Children learn language 12 to 18 months.
What are you saying?
That they need some preparation?
I'm not sure what you're asking.
So thinking from an engineering point of view,
if you were to build a robot, would
you need to program it with some instincts,
some real thumb algorithms in order
to get it started in the world in order
to build experiential knowledge?
You might want to build something
like a difference engine so that you can represent a goal
and it will try to achieve it.
So you need some engine for producing any behavior at all.
If you take the approach that maybe to build an AI,
you should build an infant robot and then you
teach it as you were like a human child,
then would it be useful to make it
dependent on some other figure in order
to help it learn how to do things like a human child would?
Well, in order to learn, you have to learn from something.
And one way to learn is in isolation, just to have some,
you could build a goal to predict what will happen.
And the best way to predict, as Alan Kay put it once,
the best way to predict the future is to invent it.
So you could make a, or you could put a model of an adult
in it to start with so that, in other words,
one way to make a very smart child
is to copy its mother's brain into a little subbrain
when it's born.
And then it could learn from that
instead of depending on anybody else.
I'm not sure.
You have to start with something.
Of course, humans, as Bob mentioned or someone mentioned,
if you take a human baby and isolate it,
it looks like it won't develop language by itself
because I don't know what because.
In fact, I remember one of our children
who was just learning to talk.
And she said, something came up.
And she said, what because is that?
Do you remember?
It took a while to get her to say why.
So she would come up and say, what because?
And I would say, you're asking, why did this?
After a long time, she got the hint.
Why do all WH words start with WH?
One of them doesn't.
How?
Could you say, wow?
Is there a theory?
It's a basic sound telling that you're
making a query before you can do the rising inflection.
It's interesting.
Is it true in French?
Quoi?
Well, the land of the silent letter.
That's it.
Anybody know what's the equivalent of WH words
in your native language?
What?
N?
In what?
Really?
They all start with N?
Wow.
Interesting.
Maybe the infants have an effect on something.
Do questions in Turkish end with a rise?
Is it rising?
So only the WH questions, OK, all questions
end in a kind of an inflection.
But normally, you have a little word
that you would put at the end of any sentence
to make it into a question, except for the WH questions,
which are standalone words and you don't need them.
Yes, you'd say, this is expensive.
And they don't need the WH if you do enough of that.
So the question, is that in the brain at birth?
Is that pattern married in English where you can say,
is this expensive?
And you can say, how expensive is this
without that rising intonation?
It's not a marriage thing using a separate word,
but you don't need that separate word if it's an N word.
But if you're saying, how expensive is this
without the question of inflection,
it almost sounds like you're making a statement about just
how ridiculously expensive it is, you know?
Like, you're going, how expensive is this?
Versus, how expensive is this?
Well, I should let you go.