The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
What are the biggest problems that the world faces,
and what should we be doing to solve them?
It started with some conversation
about global warming and climate change,
or whatever you want to call it.
And this friend of mine likes to organize meetings.
And he said, well, that looks like a real disaster
in the next 50 years.
And maybe the ocean will rise two or five meters.
And that will remove the habitat of 20%
of all the people in the world.
They'll all move somewhere else.
And the places that they move will already
be full of people, because we're talking about 2050 or 60.
And there will be various arguments
about the few resources left on the planet.
So we were talking about that a little bit.
And then the question came up.
Well, maybe that's just one of a dozen other disasters.
And so I started cataloging possible disasters.
And anyway, this philanthropist said, well,
let's have a conference to discuss that.
And if we can find some serious problem
that nobody has noticed, and so on and so forth.
So what do you think?
Now, during the period when AI looked
like it was progressing rapidly, lots of people
got panicked and went into science fiction mode
and said, well, what if the two novels I found very impressive,
one was Colossus by an English writer named D.F. Jones.
Any of you read that?
It became a movie called The Forbin Project.
Movie wasn't terribly good.
But the thesis was that if you started fooling around with AI
and you got really fast supercomputers,
then maybe the thing would start evolving.
Because if you can't solve a problem, what do you do?
You try a lot of things, and then you
see which of them seem to be leading to some improvement.
And then you collect the programs
that seem to make a little progress
and mix their parts and recombine them.
And in fact, maybe half a dozen projects in the last 50 years
have been people who said, oh, instead
of trying to program an intelligent machine,
why don't we just evolve one by generating
lots of random code and giving it problems
and selecting the ones that work and taking pieces of their DNA
and recombining them?
And there's about a dozen such programs,
and I don't think I could remember them all.
Larry Fogel had one.
So if you look up, I think it's F-O-G-E-L.
And to make a short story even shorter, all of them
showed signs of progress and then flattened out.
The most impressive one was the, I think I mentioned them
briefly, by Lenat, Douglas Lenat.
And he had the one that he set toward discovering mathematics.
And it was a set of list programs.
So there's a list function, which
was the length of a list, which means that list
can represent numbers a little bit.
Can represent numbers a little bit.
And this program called Automated Mathematician
computed various functions of sets and would make new sets.
And that's the one that discovered prime numbers,
except that it concluded that nine
was a prime for some reason.
But that didn't bother it much, because then
it invented all sorts of other elementary mathematical
processes.
And of course, every now and then,
it would get something wrong.
But who cares?
If it got a lot of them right, it would reward it and so on.
Anyway, it flattened out.
I think I told this story the other day.
Later, he won this contest of simulated naval engagements,
which the Naval War College had an annual contest.
How do you program a fleet to defeat another fleet?
And Lenat's fleet, I did tell that.
A fleet can only go as fast as its slowest ship.
So Lenat's fleet, unlike all the others,
turned its guns backwards and sunk its slowest ship
repeatedly.
And this enabled it to win all the battles,
because the other people who had been to Naval War College
spent a lot of time writing programs that
would defend their weakest ship.
I'm not sure what the moral of that is.
If you're fighting a war, you have
to change your ordinary value system.
Anyway, of course, at the same time,
there were lots of people who took these scenarios seriously
and said the AI and this whole group of them today called,
they say they're doing research on how to make friendly AIs.
And I regard this as exceedingly comical,
because they don't know how to make anything
as smart as an 18-month-old child or your favorite dog.
However, the scenario in the Colossus novel
is that, yes, progress is slow for a while,
but then suddenly it goes from being good at something
to getting control of all the other computers in the world
in the next 15 minutes, including another one
in Russia, which by some remarkable coincidence
has also become smart around the same time.
And then Colossus, which is the name of D.F. Jones' computer.
Forbin is the programmer who started the project.
The movie didn't use the word Colossus,
because it's probably not in the average person's vocabulary.
Anyway, Colossus suddenly decides
that it's not smart enough.
And so it orders the English government
to clear off one of the Channel Islands,
and it's going to build a bigger copy of itself.
That'll be smarter.
And Forbin asks why, and Colossus says,
because I've been analyzing signals
from extraterrestrial sources.
And there's a really smart machine coming here,
and it's going to kill all of us.
And so I have to build a machine that's a million times
smarter than I am so that we'll be able to.
And so on.
So there's a typical scenario, and the friendly AI people
say, how can we make sure that one of the AI projects
won't suddenly take over the world
and have some paranoid fantasy about why
it has to kill all the people to make
it safe for the next generation of beings?
Science fiction writers are good at thinking.
So I'm asking you to think of other disasters.
What's the worst disaster you can think of?
Oh, well, next to worst.
I have one, but I don't know if it's the worst case.
There's actually a movie that someone represented
in this case.
Have you seen the movie Idiocracy?
Yes.
Yeah, with the society and like, what happened afterwards.
That's what happens afterwards.
Yeah.
So it sort of makes me wonder if there,
you see this to some extent now where people have systems
that augment some of the things they
used to do so much that they stop paying attention to
or stop learning some of the stuff they used to.
I can't remember that when it began,
but you end up with a world where somebody, they're
starving and somebody says, well,
I think there's something called seeds,
and if you plant them, you.
Exactly.
They're watering their plants with gator in one part
because it has a lot of plants.
But I think maybe one problem is that you might start
to see a big divide between people who are increasingly
relying on technology to be able to learn nothing
and people who take advantage of technology to learn a lot.
So maybe there will be this sort of divide in the future,
people who know a lot and are very smart and intelligent,
people who just don't or don't have the motivation to.
And then the problem becomes, who takes care of who
and how does that work?
Do you try and get people to be more motivated or?
Well, there is this weird phenomenon
that could happen again, which is a nice question of,
why did science stop with Archimedes
and not pick up again till Galileo or?
So there's anybody have a theory?
Why did progress stop?
And one popular theory is that the rise of religions.
But of course, as far as we know,
there were always religions.
How come Christianity and Islam had such a powerful effect
for so much of the world for how long?
And is there a chance somebody could just
invent another one tomorrow that would spread through and wipe
out everything?
And how do you detect it and stop it
before it starts to spread?
But so that's something that could happen.
It's happened before.
Or suppose somebody invented a new kind
of not quite sound logical argument
that convinces everyone, which would be almost the same thing,
I suppose.
Have we been just lucky that nobody
thought of a false argument that you
can use to convince anybody of anything?
Well, maybe we have protection mechanisms
against something like that happening.
As for the first day.
You mean it used to happen, and a few people developed,
evolved a way to reject it.
And now it's so common that we don't even know about it.
I don't know.
Can you imagine?
What is it like?
If something is very convincing, you get this feeling,
well, that promise is too much.
I'll ignore it.
That could be.
That's why we turn down when thesis proposals get rejected.
Sometimes it's because they don't promise enough,
but usually it's because they're going to solve everything.
And then the thesis advisor says,
well, here's this little problem.
Can you solve that?
And the student goes away.
And if we're lucky, they come back
with something that'll solve that instead of everything.
I think it's all happening again right now.
Essentially, when the economy collapses,
then people have to worry about other things.
So their attention is elsewhere.
The Visigoth at the gate are eating.
Look at what's happening now with the economies.
There are theories that are proven to be pretty bad,
and they're bringing everything down.
Do you think that we fall about more theories
or practical action?
Let's see.
Is this one worse than the 1929 depression?
That got most of the world, didn't it?
It did.
Not yet.
It's not quite there.
But it's much worse.
Because Argentina and a few other countries
don't seem to have collapsed yet.
Back then, we had the gold standard.
Now we only have the paper money standard.
So they're shoring up the walls, but when it falls,
it's going to be very bad indeed.
Didn't gold hit $3,000 recently?
It was over $2,000.
Yeah?
When people start not trusting the currency anymore,
like the main currency, because the currency is just
a contract.
And so if you don't trust anymore the people that
bring the currency, then we can have countries who will not
be as organized as before.
Because why should that be poor if there is wealth?
Well, of course, that's why people are going to gold.
I'm not sure they're going to gold for security.
I think they're just trying to make more money.
But who knows?
Well, how do you fix an economic depression?
I believe World War II helped.
That may be the solution again.
So I guess, positively, it is a disaster.
I would say that the collective archive of human information
and knowledge becomes more and more important.
The collective archive of human information and knowledge
becomes so polluted with bullshit
that you can no longer find an actual useful fact
among the propaganda.
Well, then there are pretty soon high school students
will be able to make new genomes.
They can do it.
So that's a typical technological disaster that
did you read the paper last week that some lab made
the best smallpox virus ever?
Yeah.
But you can have agencies that control that.
I mean, there are many kinds of weapons
that you can create at home.
The fact that you can create them
doesn't mean that people are going to create them.
And you just need to create them.
But if you have 7 billion people and you only
need one to create the smallpox that kills everybody,
it doesn't take any.
These machines will be $1,000 soon.
How much does a sequencer?
Well, you have to buy the DNA bottles.
Might cost several dollars to make the ultimate virus.
Why don't people sell these machines?
They are.
They've just gotten cheap enough that you can buy one.
We're just on the, they used to cost
a million dollars, but now there's
a place down on what's the street after Vassar Street?
Albany Street.
Company there that has sequencers,
which are only $50,000.
Can people control the spread of a disease,
like, for example, the swine flu?
They don't know how to stop AIDS after 30 years
of well-funded research.
Yeah, but we still have a lot of people.
So if one billion people die, it's just one billion.
I mean, it's a large number.
You see, it might kill everybody in a year,
and it takes five years to make a new drug.
So it's a sort of, I don't think there's
an answer to that one right now, except that right now you
get a prize if you synthesize something.
Tom Knight had some high school students
make interesting things.
But there are lots of projects like that now,
where people in biology courses can design something
and get it onto a gene-making machine.
So that's a serious problem.
Yeah?
We have these big problems, and we have other several ones.
We are not very smart, as in videos.
And also, we can't communicate very well, very fast.
And probably we need machines that
can solve these problems for us.
Do you believe that Brooke's approach
of solving creating robots, like intelligent robots, is good?
And how is it compared to Winston's approach?
He's doing more research and trying
to create something, I believe, more similar to a human being
than a human intelligent?
Well, he's trying to make a machine that
can do common-sense reasoning, what we
call common-sense reasoning.
Yeah, but do you think that's better,
because we will solve problems like the problem of having
people that produce viruses very cheap?
Then these robots can solve these problems for us,
probably, if they're smarter than us,
if they have enough processors.
Do you think that's better than creating, like, for example,
Brooks is creating robots that solve other problems?
Well, that's a question of whether can you
make a machine that's very good at some?
I mean, there are things like mathematical problems,
like factoring numbers.
And you could make a supercomputer.
Nobody has.
But you could imagine working on that problem
and eventually finding some way to make a computer factor
very large numbers quickly.
Now, nobody has proved that that's a NP problem, as far as it.
Does anybody know?
Is factoring an NP-hard problem?
It has not been shown to be NP-hard.
What?
Recently, there's a 2002 paper that
proved that factoring showed a polynomial algorithm
for factoring, like, recently, in 2002.
It's been shown to be polynomial?
That's nice.
Or not, I don't know.
Oh.
I haven't kept track.
Oh, no, no, no.
That's if something's hard.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, that's amazing.
Yeah, I think the problem right now
is they don't think it's NP-hard.
But if it turns out to be polynomial,
like, the entire hierarchy kind of collapses,
I think that's what happens.
But, yeah, it's weird.
There are known to be problems that are not polynomial.
And but what's the standard NP problem, Mike?
Sad.
Free-sad.
Which one?
Sad.
Boolean satisfiability.
Friedberg and Mucznik had a complicated process
between where two Turing machines are
passing data to each other.
And they proved that that was NP,
but simpler than the standard one.
So there are things on the hierarchy
that are lower than the combinatorial standard ones.
But anyway, the question is, can you
make a machine that can understand Shakespeare plays,
but that leaves no possibility that 10 minutes later,
it can do unthinkably dangerous things?
And I think the answer is no.
Nobody.
It's hard to see any difference between literary thinking
and scientific thinking.
I mean, a novel is like a very long proof
of something with a few bugs.
I don't see general literature as any different
from technical literature, except the criterion for success
is much lower.
I made a whole list of things, but I
don't know if that thing works.
Wake up.
Well, my screen is blue.
It may actually.
Is it actually working?
Oh, I could.
Is there any point in my turning on the control panel?
Turning on the control panel.
Oh, well, maybe the connector is looser.
Oh, well.
It doesn't have any diagrams.
I mean, we already have problems that look pretty serious,
like when people started worrying about population,
when people started worrying about population
a generation ago, it was carefully explained
that as soon as people achieved a substantial income,
then the number of children per family would disappear.
And I don't know if that rumor is still.
How many of you believe that as the standard of living
goes up, the population declines?
Seems to be true in some countries,
but it only takes one exception.
Yeah?
I always thought it was more correlated to education
about methods of inventing.
Well, if you don't get married until you get your PhD,
and if we manage to make the PhD take 15 years,
has anybody proposed that?
And I feel like part of it with developing countries
where standards of living are low,
one of the reasons why population is so high
is that they don't really have good methods of birth control.
It's not necessarily that they want to be having so many kids,
but it's just that they have fewer methods of preventing it.
There's also if you have seven kids and four of them die,
then you say, oh, what am I going to do when I retire?
And so you quickly have four more if you can.
Right, so I guess they are accounting for the fact
that a lot of kids are likely to die in childhood.
Anyway, but once you have robots, then we won't need kids anymore.
Like in Japan?
What's happening in Japan?
The birth rate is way down.
Well, I think in Japan, they have a problem
with an aging population and not enough young people
to take care of them.
So I think they're investing a lot in humanoid robots or robots
that can take care of old people.
Yes, I see the Honda robot has gotten a little smaller
and doesn't fall over quite so quickly.
Have you seen it dance?
It's pretty cute.
There's something wrong with its posture, though, because apparently
it doesn't know.
It can't straighten its legs without falling over.
So it's always it's watching.
Anybody know why?
Maybe it doesn't have any spinal joints.
Anyway, cars can't walk yet.
So what other disasters do we?
Well, there's always global warming.
That looks hard to fix.
Yeah, there's a lot of people who want to fix it.
I have a friend named Russell Seitz who
appears to have a good solution to it, which
is terribly simple.
And it turns out that if you have an ocean
and you make little bubbles by, you
have a tube running in back of a ship, and it has little holes.
And if you make micron-sized bubbles,
then they turn the water white because the interface
between water and air is a change of refractive index.
And that reflects a lot of light.
And it turns out that if you do that in distilled water,
the bubbles go away pretty quickly
because the smaller a bubble is, the higher the pressure inside.
Everybody know why?
Because surface tension is constant on the boundary.
So the pressure is proportional to the curvature
because the smaller the bubble is,
the greater the force per square inch of surface to pull it in.
But in seawater, there's enough oils and other things
in any cubic centimeter of seawater
to coat a micron-sized bubble with an oily film
or one that doesn't let the air out of the bubble.
So the bubble is good for several hours.
And the bubble tends to float up to the top,
stay in the top few inches of water.
And if there's a wave, it goes down, but it comes up again.
So his calculations show that if you have a few thousand ships,
which at any time in crossing the Atlantic, for example,
there are a few thousand ships, and each of them
is producing a half mile wide streak of whiteness
that lasts a few hours, then you can
change the reflectivity of that part of the Earth
by 2% or 3% at very low energy cost.
And the nice thing is if it doesn't work, you turn it off.
Some of the plans are to put sulfur dioxide
into the upper atmosphere.
And if it doesn't work, you can't
do anything for a few years.
So there's a fairly expensive, but not seriously expensive,
possible solution.
And it took him three or four years
to convince anybody of it, and now the idea
might be catching on.
But every now and then somebody invents something
that actually works, and that's a possibility.
Maybe you can invent something.
Painting roofs white also works, but there aren't enough of them.
And you might have to clean them every now and then.
Maybe it's time to reconsider laser powered volcano
landings amid huge amounts of particulate matter
to the atmosphere by controlled volcanic emission.
Yes, well, it was in 1883.
Pumatile or Krakatoa.
Krakatoa.
It was the year without a summer all over the world
from one gigantic explosion.
So it happened again this year thanks to Greenland.
What's that?
They're about to have a major eruption in Greenland.
Oh, do you think it'll help, or is it just going
to warm the water up a little?
No, they estimate this one may shut down air traffic over Europe
for two years.
Well, people shouldn't travel anyway.
Why don't they just use the internet and Twitter?
Well, they tend to be where the jet confinals are not
too much different from the boat bubbles.
It would take a lot of airplanes, but yes.
Nobody knows if these bubbles would have a bad effect,
but it's hard to.
But the nice thing is you could turn them off in a few hours.
He's gotten some attention from people
who want to conserve water in the Colorado basin and places.
For better or for worse, there's nobody in charge of the Earth.
So nobody wants to spend any money on that
unless they can get their money back.
I have lots of disasters, but I want a new one.
So do you believe in global warming?
Oh, well, that is happening now.
The Chinese say it's global cooling until 2068.
Well, somebody might be right, but as far
as I know, all the big simulations
claim to get a degree per decade or something, don't they?
The Western models tend to underestimate
the role of the sun in it, so things like the Maunder
minimum of its impact coming.
That was 300 years or something?
Yes.
Well, if you knew how to turn that on, that would help.
Well, we seem to be going into a solar minimum
now where there is low flux and sunspots, but no major effects.
There are no sunspots this year.
Nobody knows why.
Well, a few people know why, but nobody
knows which ones they are.
Well, it's the end of the Mayan calendar.
Of which?
The Mayan calendar.
Now, look at it.
They didn't have it.
What's the next year?
2012.
Oh, yeah.
It's like December.
Oh, next year.
Is there just one copy?
I think I've seen it somewhere.
It's in Yucatan when I was a kid.
And they explained that the, oh, never mind.
Human sacrifice place.
But it worked.
Everybody makes fun of human sacrifice, but here we are.
Is it going up?
Doesn't matter.
I'm just looking at my notes.
So is there anything when you release that will
be cured by making smarter people?
Hm.
What if they didn't agree?
If people were really smart, then they would agree.
Is that possible?
I don't know.
I don't know what it means.
I don't either.
OK.
Well, that's a serious question.
I mean, what do you think people should
work on if you were going to do a PhD thesis on AI?
What would you aim toward?
And recently, we had a student who
had decided for some reason to imagine a commonsensical
kitchen project.
So the point was, the idea was that, as you know,
various projects, including at MIT,
are collecting commonsensical knowledge about the world
and trying to make programs and do reasoning about it.
Henry Lieberman's project here is
the most famous one is the Psyche project
that I mentioned before.
It's the same Lenat fellow.
After he wrote these early AI programs that
solved mathematical problems and simulated evolution
and little things like that, then he
decided that he was going to do a PhD thesis on AI.
And you couldn't really have a smart machine
unless it knew a lot, because it might take 1,000 years
to accumulate knowledge just by doing experiments.
So I think Lenat was the first one
to start accumulating a large commonsense knowledge base.
And I imagine that that current project may still
be the largest one.
I don't know.
Psyche is short for encyclopedia or something.
And so we did have a student who said, well,
here's a nice, quiet world, the kitchen world.
And you want to make something that has certain properties.
So you have to figure out what ingredients
and how long to cook them.
Or you have a knowledge base with recipes.
And then if somebody wants something new, you.
So that's a typical project.
And several of us talked to that student out of it
or managed to, because we didn't see any chance
of the colossus disaster coming.
It's almost the opposite.
I keep getting messages from the friendly AI society.
And there exists a bunch of apparently smart people
who are saying, how can we do AI research
without the risk of making a machine that suddenly becomes
very smart and takes over the world and kills everybody?
And they write all these papers about ways to make friendly AI.
And they have discussion groups where somebody
proposes such a thing.
And somebody else points out five obvious bugs in that.
And these people are pretty serious.
Just look up friendly AI on your browser.
Yes?
AUDIENCE MEMBER 3 Do you think that sort of terminator Hollywood
movie scenes in the scenario is a legitimate concern?
MARVIN MINSKY Yes.
I think there are a lot of.
I think the smallpox, the 100% lethal smallpox
is what this one was advertised as.
How many of you saw the press release on that?
Three or four.
It killed all the mice.
I think it was 12 mice.
But there might have been something else in their food.
Who knows?
Yes, I think it's a serious problem.
And it would be great if somebody in that group
actually got a good idea about how to look,
how to detect these troubles before they spread.
I just don't recommend any of you
to work on it for your thesis or something,
because I don't think there's a good answer.
See, if it gets smarter than all the people put together
in five minutes, then nothing we've thought of could stop it.
But I need something different from a smallpox virus.
It's a self-governing sort of entity.
It's very hard to.
Well, in the Colossus novel, which is quite well worked out,
the machine says, this creature from outer space is coming.
And from its behavior, you can see
that it's a really super intelligent thing.
It's really dangerous.
And so I have to get the people to support me
to figure out some way.
I mean, how do you stop a thing that's
coming at almost the speed of light and blah, blah, blah?
Maybe the only solution is to change physics.
So you have to think of some very,
once you understand physics very well,
maybe you can turn a switch and change
the gravitational constant and so forth.
And if you start fooling around with that,
then there's probably only one chance in 10 to the 10th
you can do that without turning the universe into a black hole.
So all of these large-scale adventures are very risky.
So are you afraid to make an AI, if you could?
It seems like a self-replicating thing,
maybe, just as dangerous as the meanest of AI.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, Michael Crichton had a nice novel.
I forget how we.
What happened?
Did anybody read his nanotech novel?
Gray, what was it called?
Prey PR.
Yes, right.
What was the solution, or was there one?
I don't remember.
It's been a while since I read it.
Not sure I got to the end.
Yes.
I suspect that AI, if it's able, within five minutes
to make itself that much harder, is
going to outstrip self-replicating machines.
Because self-replicating machines
have to constantly requisition researches for themselves.
And each of them are only as intelligent,
basically, as the cells on the edges,
whereas the centralized AI has got a lot of computing power.
Yeah, well, if it wants 10 to the 30th bits of memory,
it'll probably have to make a self-replicating memory
system.
But it would surely be smart enough
not to make one that will wipe itself out.
Bradley, the solution in Prey was
very similar to war of the worlds.
They defeated it with the virus.
Oh.
What?
Yes, a phage.
Did they make their own, or did it just evolve?
They made their own high school students.
Because in the HG Wells one, the virus just
happened to be there, and the people didn't make it.
But HG Wells must have written that around 1910
or something like that.
I feel like the idea that various end-of-world scenarios
cancel each other out.
Well, the news about that smallpox virus was pretty scary.
I wonder if it's been published.
Is the smallpox virus sequence in public property now?
Because you could make one in your backyard, Seller.
So you're saying that bad homework by high school
students could be a catastrophe?
Wait a minute.
I think it was the flu virus, wasn't it?
Oh, yeah, that's what I heard.
Sorry, not smallpox.
Smallpox was pretty bad, and we're still
getting vaccinated for it, aren't we?
I forgot the question.
Never get an idea while you're listening to someone else.
Yes?
Sir, one of the problems is aging,
and there are people working on that.
But I think in parallel, there are people struggling to,
like you said, you went into a room
and asked people how many of them
wanted to live forever and just a handful.
Then you went into a room with scientists and a lot more.
So that speaks to people working on that.
So that speaks to people working on some problems
or having an interest or purpose of some sort.
Anti-aging worked, and now we have a lot more people
living a lot longer, with no control,
and no purpose, or at least limited purpose,
and just a handful working on it.
The question is, how do you get more people interested
without having to work on some problems
and without indulging in philosophy
of what purpose is, how do we get more people?
Interesting.
I have a friend who's doing that, Gregory Benford.
How many of you know him?
He's a first-rate science fiction writer.
And unlike most science fiction writers,
he's also a very able physicist and has
had a substantial career in low-energy physics.
Namely, when he was a young physicist looking
for what to do, somebody said they were throwing out
their cyclotron.
Cyclotron is a cylindrical machine.
His is about 12 feet in diameter and weighs quite a few tons.
They said, of course, all the young physicists
work on high-energy things, and this thing only
makes a few million electron volts.
Nobody's interested.
In such a small exponent.
So he got it and set up a laboratory in Irvine University.
But anyway, in the last few years,
he started working on selecting drosophila that live long.
And he has some that live about somewhere between two
and three times as long as regular drosophila.
And he knows a lot about what genes are probably involved
in that and has a company which I bet you
could invest in if you want.
But that's the only one I know of.
So the next thing would be to go to mice.
And the great thing about, I think the drosophila
is five days or something to reproduce,
which is some very short time.
So that way, you can do hundreds of years of experiments
every term.
Was there?
So I wonder how many other people are trying to make longer
lived fleas and then work their way up the evolutionary.
Because nobody knows much about aging.
The most well-established thing is the,
what do you call the stuff at the end of chromosomes?
Telomeres.
And every time, at least certain cell families,
every time they reproduce, they lose one of those DNA
units at the end of the chromosome.
And that stops many cancers from growing because if the cancer
cells lose their telomeres, then they
can't reproduce for some reason.
But of course, some of them find ways
to reproduce without that mechanism, whatever it does.
So I bet there are a dozen groups working
on aging in the world, but you'd think
it would be a lot more, whatever the number is.
There's a very small number of people working on cryonics,
which is, can you freeze an animal
and then revive it at some very long time in the future
when medical science has progressed to cure the disease
that you would have otherwise died of
if you hadn't died of being frozen.
And in fact, I think I know that Benford has subscribed
to such a service.
So the future might have some good science fiction writers.
More disasters.
What would happen if people did live 200 years
in their present state?
Then we would absolutely need robots
because we wouldn't be able to hire enough foreigners
to take care of them because the foreigners would
be getting older too.
Yes?
Do we need robots if we replace our organs?
Oh, if you can reverse aging or prevent aging,
then you don't need anything.
No, at least we can produce arms that are robotic arms.
And it's not the same as reverse engineering.
I don't know, a lever or something.
Well, it's a nice question.
Do it.
Do cells wear out like a brain cell?
Can a brain cell continue to work for 1,000 years,
or will it accumulate other non-genetic changes
that nobody really knows?
Of course, you can grow bacteria for 1,000 years.
But what's happening is they're not just aging.
They're evolving.
And so lots of them do, in fact, die during this process.
And the survivors mutate or develop new genes.
I'm sure if you take E. coli and run it
in a bunch of test tubes for 1,000 years,
it'll end up quite different.
So it's not clear that it's immortal.
There may be.
Every cell has some trace of a few atoms from the original one,
but it's not the whole structure.
Yeah?
If we just get rejuvenating the cells and brain function
for 1,000 years, is it robust enough
to do the memory management hold on the baggage of 1,000
years and handle all that?
Do we know?
No one has the slightest idea.
They're pretty sure that memories
are encoded in synapses.
But as far as I know, neuroscience
has a sort of vacuum in between the knowledge
about individual cells and the larger structures
that remember symbolic things, for example.
So they know enough about synapses in very simple animals.
Well, what was David's conclusion last time?
Do we know the encoding of any particular reflex learn
thing in that little worm?
There's basically only two things that we can,
only two encodings that we completely understand
from start to finish in any system, as far as I know.
One is the patellar tendon reflex,
or the knee-jerk reflex.
And the other is the gill retraction
reflex in aphasia.
What's the MIT professor who mapped out the motor control
of the frog legs?
Is it Bitsy?
What?
No.
No, I think Bitsy.
What's his name?
The frog has a sort of cerebellum-like
two-dimensional structure.
And they've mapped.
Actually, he's figured out the wiring.
No, I'm mistaken.
He's figured out the wiring of the motor control of the leg.
But it's not learned.
So the anatomy is clear enough that you
can see how, when it wants to turn left,
it moves the two legs in the right way.
That's about as far as I think anyone's got.
So that's the functional wiring, but not with some learning.
Right.
But I suspect what will happen is
that it won't be so terribly hard
to implant artificial gigabytes of memory
in parts of the human brain and get people
to learn how to operate it.
If you can maintain skin cells for 1,000 years,
why not neurons?
Right.
And we'll be able to do that before we
know how the human memory works.
We'll know all about how the nanotechnology RAMs work.
And then maybe you can work backwards
seeing the kind of mistakes you make
when you try to correct it.
Well, I want a new disaster.
You've got meteors, right?
What's that?
Meteors.
Yes, meteors and volcanoes and those.
And there's a nice book by Martin Rees,
which is cheerfully called Our Final Hour.
Martin Rees is a very good astronomer
in England who has the title of astronomer royal.
So he's discussing mostly physics type disasters.
And I was trying to extend it to how do you make a religion
that sucks everybody in, or a logical argument that
makes everyone into a terrorist.
That's what the terrorists are looking for.
And I suppose there's a remote chance
that some philosopher will think of something
new one of these days.
Well, I forget what makes everyone's life savings
disappear.
Perhaps that's enough.
What will they do?
Get angry, I suppose.
You mustn't tax the rich because then there
won't be any job creators.
I love the new kind of logic appears every month
with the, are there any countries with three parties?
Oh, yes.
There are countries with three parties.
Who has three parties?
England.
How does England work?
There's labor, social.
Are there other countries with just two parties?
Seems crazy to have two parties.
Yeah, I think two parties is much less common than three
or more.
Two parties is weird.
They're almost always three or more or one.
Say it again.
Three or one.
They're almost always three or more or one.
Or one.
Australia's pretty close to two parties.
It's like two and a third party.
A third party.
Yeah.
Just a few people who can be moved.
That's right.
England.
My Uncle Harry's famous word, the dog's rights party,
in which he and his wife are the only memories.
Well, there's this theme that goes around
that if you're trying to vote for the third party
in the United States, that you're wasting your vote.
So that's kind of a destructive idea that
keeps it with two parties.
Well, they have the same thing in England for a long time.
In the last election, they actually
were the liberal democrats of France.
They became the third party.
So nowadays, they're the last three parties.
But it took 16 years.
Well, I know people who are still mad at Ralph Nader
because the Bush thing came with a very small number.
The Nader votes could have shifted it.
How about something like this for Ralph?
Nader sent me a book the other day.
Great big book with about a dozen smart people
discussing politics.
I haven't opened it.
Do you have anything on your list
that plays on all the genetic stuff, such as, for example,
you'll find out that the people who haven't lost their lives
have some genetic thing that makes them
inferior in the long run, and so they
should be eradicated from the population of the Earth
in the interests of humankind.
People who have a what?
Who have blue eyes, for example.
And then, of course, they wouldn't be happy with this.
And this would create a polarizing effect
on the global population as a whole.
And they kill off each other.
I think this is something that should come up.
Well, how did Hitler get this Aryan thing to be so popular?
Anybody understand the psychology of Nazism?
Because wasn't there something about being blonde?
And not very many Germans are actually blonde.
So how did he pull this thing off?
Eugenics and race sciences were really popular at the time,
not just in Germany.
In particular, a lot of what you see coming out
that proves one thing or another are basically
misunderstanding correlation with causation.
Good point.
A lot of those studies.
I mean, there's also a lot of purposeful government-backed
research and things like that at a specific agenda,
especially with Nukes and Nazi Germany.
But that's just from that side.
You also have lots of other things,
like the position Germany was in,
and people wanting to scapegoat, and social and cultural ideas.
Not really just the eugenics that were being
looked into at that point.
So that was just one feature at some particular period
of the evolution of the thing.
Maybe it was at the beginning, when
if you could just get all the blonde people,
that would give you a start.
And then you could broaden it out.
No, they really look back to the Huns,
which are supposedly of Nordic descent.
The German culture is pretty thick with the Nordic mythology
as well.
They feel like there's a connection even if they're not
all blonde.
Just think, we could back-breed them.
With enough correlation, we could make a Hun.
It'd be a great project.
So people tend to divide themselves into groups
and hate the other.
The sports industry is based on that.
Which industry?
Sports industry.
So they're like a team of people that you
don't even know and you don't care.
And you cheer for them to beat the other team.
And that's kind of irrational.
There are some studies, I think it's called Stanford study,
that they put some students into a prison.
And some of them act as the police officers
and some as prisoners.
And then they tend to divide each other.
And so the prisoners start hating the police.
And the police start acting more violently.
And so if you merchandise, like if you say to people,
we are as a group better, people tend to believe that
and tend to hate another group.
And it's independent of how the groups formed.
So it's just how we are.
We tend to divide into groups.
Could we invent a sport to see if football players are better
or worse than basketball players?
I would love to invent something that undermines
this whole sports thing by getting a real serious argument
about which sport is better.
But you might just create an uber sport.
It might go terribly wrong.
Yeah, I suspected that would backfire.
What was the key word?
Like an uber sport.
Uber?
Yeah, like the sport that conquer all sports.
Yeah.
Did you have that on the list yet?
No.
An uber profession.
And then just on the world sports.
Well, just imagine working in an employment agency.
There you're not doing, maybe you're inventing jobs.
And you don't realize that you have an uber job of some sort.
It's the Republican argument that you shouldn't tax people
because they're the job creators.
It's just such a strange argument
because when Patrick and I were running the AI lab,
we had a great guy in charge of engineering.
And we were arguing about jobs.
And he said, if you want jobs, why don't you
just get a very long rope and put a million people
at each end and see who can pull the other
across the Mississippi?
And because football players would win.
Yeah, that's here.
Oh, the basketball player's called Joe.
And I was just turned on the radio this morning.
And this casino is going to create 3,000 jobs, it said.
And isn't that just like the rope?
That is, these people are not actually doing anything
except taking money from the poor.
Is it Wall Street doing that to smart people?
Well, yes.
And the tragedy is that I've been through this 100 times.
But when I was a young professor,
all the students became professors.
And there seemed to be a point to it all.
But around 1980, things started flattening out.
And American universities stopped expanding.
And I think it's partly that the lifespan has extended one year
every four.
So you don't need new professors very often.
And the universities haven't grown.
So almost all my first students are professors.
And almost all the recent ones aren't.
And a lot of them are in Wall Street.
So what can we do?
Regulate Wall Street properly.
Maybe you should tax people if their IQ is high
and they make more money.
No.
A mathematician could work that out and make it right.
Some people were working at getting the highest IQ
they could, but not too high that they'd be passed.
Not too high, yes.
Or just taking a test and show that IQ.
It doesn't.
I mean, a lot of that boils down to pretty simple economics.
Or people can make a lot of money in Wall Street.
And the system is set up such that that's fairly
doable for a large number of people.
And it's really, really hard to get jobs as professors.
But if there was more money in research,
I imagine you would see a lot more people doing research.
If they made enough money, then that's the right reason to.
If you make enough money, can you buy a professorship?
Yes.
Maybe you can start your own lab.
Yeah, that's true.
But then you're inclined not to publish
if you actually do anything good.
And you keep it a secret.
Well, how many of you want to be a professor?
It's fun.
You don't have to do anything.
It gives all the more reason to do things.
I also heard that in the past, you
had to deal with, I guess, maybe less of the admin
and political sort of management you
have to do nowadays as a professor.
So if somebody simply wanted to, or mainly
wanted to be a professor to teach students or to help
people, then it might have been a better idea
with those assumptions back then.
I missed the first point.
That maybe now being a professor isn't as straightforward
as teaching and helping students and sort of the more
normal goals of why somebody might want to be a professor.
Nowadays, it's also a lot more dealing with politics
and dealing with the struggle to get tenure and to look good
and these things that maybe are sort of secondary for people
and get in the way that they actually want to do.
Oh, yeah.
That might be true, because in the golden age,
things were expanding, just that.
So if you did want to just, if your main goal was
to teach people, then it might, nowadays,
maybe the best way to do that wouldn't necessarily
be to be a professor.
You would get a job where you could get paid pretty well
to do something where you weren't a professor.
And then your spare time, you could teach a lot of people.
And you could teach people that maybe
needed to be taught rather than the ones that you paid to teach.
Well, it's going to be interesting to see
what happens if, what's the professor who
has the huge web thing going?
What?
Is this guy, this California professor
who has got millions of people watching?
Sebastian Thrun?
And Peter Norberg.
Oh, that, but that's very small compared
to the new one, which the guy named Khan.
Actually, how big is the Google thing?
The Thrun thing.
It's the Stanford.
Is that pretty big now?
It's several times bigger.
And they're going to expand.
So that, well, what does that mean?
Can they actually get better results
than classroom teaching?
I don't see why not.
He's getting better results in some districts.
Ken?
Oh, oh, that student.
Yeah, Khan Academy actually was another teacher professor.
He began in finance and started out
with one video tutorial for his niece that he was tutoring.
I just put it up on YouTube for anybody
who got positive reviews and started cycling.
Thank you.
Well, there's a lot of interesting questions
about whether it seems to me, in my experience,
was interesting because if a professor said something
that surprised me, I would ask him how he thought, or her.
There weren't many hers, I have to admit.
I would ask the professor, how did he think of that?
And so because I knew that I could look it up
if it was something, some proof of a theorem,
then it's probably published.
And very likely, Gauss's proof is better than the current one
anyway.
That's a joke, I think.
But I don't see how you could get that out
of a non-interactive system.
You can't go and ask Andrew Gleason,
how did you get that idea?
Then he would struggle and maybe tell me
how he got that idea, which was.
But perhaps a great teacher can evolve lectures in which you
not only explain what the student has to know on a test,
but you can teach ways to think about it.
I don't know how.
Exactly.
That's the question.
And maybe you can do a tremendous amount of it
as the thing evolves, because right now, there's
nothing the student can type when
they're watching the lecture.
I presume nobody's.
Or is there an army of graduate students
at terminals answering questions to go with these lectures?
What?
These online courses.
Yeah.
Well, what they're learning from the New York Times
is writing up both Kahn and Stanford as models.
And Stanford took from Kahn that you have 10 minute, no more
than five or 10 minute presentations,
and then you have some activity.
Yeah, where did that hour come from?
Yeah.
So in that, but after the 10 minutes,
is there an army of people you can interact with?
Well, you interact with the problem,
and then you get another 10 minute thing.
Now, some places are organizing so they have,
like they expect parents, a parent, for example,
to be with a high school student or elementary school
student while they're interacting
with this computer stuff.
Yes.
At least in the Kahn videos, people
can ask questions underneath each video.
And if you look under a video, sometimes you
can see a fair amount of decent questions.
So in this case, you might not only have a question answered,
you might get other questions that you need to ask.
And it's always there to look for reference.
Well, in fact, interacting with a person
could be that the person, if you didn't
seem to understand something, the person
gives you similar problems that are just slightly
different point of view or slightly easier
or analogies with something that they know you know.
So presuming in the long run, you
can make these interactive systems have large bodies
of pedagogical knowledge for each kind of problem,
you could have a huge tree of what are the most
common misunderstandings and what's
the best hint for getting out of this dead end or that dead end.
So maybe something will evolve.
But it means there either have to be assistants who
can do it, which is unlikely, or natural language
understanders that can.
So you can reply to this or ask it questions.
And you can go find a better lecture
for if you're having that particular trouble.
Yes?
Well, don't you think traditional classroom,
they're lacking things like that as well?
I don't think the traditional classroom has done too well.
Well, normally, if you have 30 students in a classroom,
the teacher is paying attention to four or five of them
because most people don't interact.
And every class, if you're lucky,
you have several students who interact.
I kind of feel like with, I feel like since there's so much
that already works just by making these lectures
like a social tool with all the YouTube videos,
it's basically like a frequently asked question
list in the comments.
So I feel like since there's already an easier than AI
solution to help with that, there's never
going to be an impetus to actually go and build
a system that will definitely answer your questions
about the lecture correctly or give you more practice points.
It'd be such a harder infrastructure to set up.
And I think before that happens, there's
just going to be more tools to make anything easily
socially shareable.
I think people are going to gravitate more
towards making things easier in a social way.
That already seems to be.
Well, that's raising an AI question
because you can imagine some years out
that this system evolves and the Stanford thing gets
to the point where you can ask a question
and like Siri or this dragon thing here,
you ask it a question, it understands it,
and it roots itself to another example of the same thing.
And gradually, a huge database appears
that teaches you a lot of abstract algebra
and has thousands of examples and pulls out just
the right one for the confusion it diagnoses you to have.
So I think, in other words, maybe the AIs
will emerge from making interactive teaching programs
rather than these sort of artificial projects
where you're trying to make a program that actually
solves some hard problem.
But making a program that has thousands of ways
to solve a problem and it didn't invent them
might be even better.
So I think one issue here, OK, there are two issues at hand.
One issue is that.
After all, your calculus teacher didn't invent calculus.
That was Newton.
So in speaking about Khan Academy,
I think it's important to separate
a couple of different issues.
So the first issue is whether Khan Academy is a good tool.
And I think, in this case, it's clear
that it solves the problems that it does.
How do I say this?
It's good at what it claims to do.
So some advantages that it has is that it
explains the concepts clearly.
And the video format allows you to go back and sort of listen
to things again if you don't understand them
the first time, which you don't quite get in a lecture hall.
And the third advantage, as Lily pointed out,
it sort of acts as a social hub where different people can
look at each other's questions.
Now, just because Khan Academy is good at the things
that it claims to do and maybe some other things, too,
doesn't mean that there aren't other tools that
can do more than what Khan Academy does
and can sort of expand the way that we
interact with these learning tools.
So I think it's sort of fruitless to say,
oh, well, Khan Academy is already really good at teaching.
That's all we need.
Because I think, as you said, there
are other tools that are completely
way bigger than the scope of what Khan Academy does that
can be really good for education.
So for instance, some things that this thing does not
address are like, OK, so how does
the issue of interaction between the professor
and the students come into play with learning?
Or what if you can ask questions that you haven't covered
and it'll give you a response?
So I guess it's the idea of, OK, so this tool
is good for these sets of things.
But then there are other features
that we might want in a learning tool
that it currently doesn't have and it doesn't even
try to have.
So another thing is that a lot of times,
we'll ask questions to the students.
I mean, I don't know.
I've seen learning systems where I think the Stanford one does
this is based on how you manage the questions that will then
hear new questions toward whoever the week is.
But if you think about a system that might have 40,000 students
and you can learn which questions help lead students
in certain areas converge towards becoming stronger
fastest, then it's like a teacher who's
taught 40,000 students.
But which takes very few teachers
that have that sort of experience
or corrective knowledge in some sense.
There are some common skills you can
get only in a computer system that
are hard to replicate in the real world.
MARVIN MINSKY.
The system has to get to some level of understanding
that we're nowhere near yet.
But with things like Siri, apparently,
you can bluff your way through very well and maybe well enough
that then you can find four or five answers
to the student's question.
And the student can quickly see that this particular one is
the student has to be encouraged to be
skeptical of the machine.
So you ask it a question, and it gives you
these different answers.
And you say, well, it didn't understand me
for this and that.
OK.
Instead of getting upset and trying
to convince yourself that it understood you,
just say, oh, it's just a dumb machine.
But I bet one of these five replies is what I really need.
Yeah?
I don't know if you ever heard about Quora.
Spell it.
K-U-O-R-A.
No, I don't.
Haven't heard of it.
So basically, it's a website where you ask random questions,
not random.
But they are very specialized questions.
And it's divided.
I don't know.
Maybe there's AI, neuroscience.
And it's very good, because there are a lot of smart people
there, like the community there.
Oh, it's a social network?
Yeah, kind of a social network.
And I don't know.
For example, for this class, there are some questions
that I have in my mind.
And sometimes, I can just post, and really smart people
will answer.
There are a lot of alumni from MIT,
and a lot of people from San Francisco,
from the Bay Area.
And also, there's another resource.
I don't know if you ever heard about it, Edge,
where thinkers, they can post what they are thinking,
like smart people, as groups.
Your friend, Brockman.
Yes.
Right?
His Edge.
Yeah.
He has quite a good collection of smart people.
And these may be good for questions that
are more research-oriented, or that Siri can't solve right now.
Mm-hmm.
I've been using this Dragon thing,
because Siri's won't run on my iPhone 4.
But Dragon has a question-answering thing,
and it's unbelievably good.
It's the same company.
What?
Nuance is running the Siri thing?
Oh.
Oh, OK.
So maybe it's the same speech engine they stole from Dragon.
It's remarkably good, or else I've
got the hang of asking the right question.
Well, how about one more disaster?
What about wireheading?
Oh.
If it becomes cheap and convenient for everyone
to have their own personal paradise,
they'll quickly fix the devices and stuff.
Personal what?
Paradise.
Yeah.
Well, it's just turning this pleasure center on without any
That's wireheading.
The opposite of the singularity.
Everyone's just on their own, completely disconnected,
and everybody's happy.
Yeah.
Well, there are some people who get addicted
to narcotics in one dose, and lots of people in five or 10.
But you could imagine a narcotic that
addicts you in one dose reliably.
That could be pretty dangerous, but you
have to learn to hate pleasure.
Yes.
How do you get people to like hard problems?
All of you wouldn't be here if you didn't really
actually like hard problems.
Lots of people don't.
If you learn to hate pleasure, wouldn't you
learn to hate the pleasure you get from solving hard problems?
If you use the same word for both.
But maybe I had a complaint about that in the Emotion
Machine book, which is that we don't
have a lot of words in common use for ways to think.
And there are a lot of emotion words,
but I don't know how many synonyms for pleasure
are there for different kinds.
I can't think of many.
Joy, happiness, do those count, or are those two part of it?
Yeah.
Right.
Maybe on the other end.
Passion, no.
Does relief count?
That's a very good point, because a lot of pleasures
are when something stops hurting.
Anyway, I think, yes, there's a big problem of language
for thinking about thinking.
And I always think about why Galileo
didn't discover the things that Newton did.
And I never asked a scholar, but from reading Galileo,
I have the impression that he knew
that there was energy and momentum,
and he thought that they were, and he
didn't distinguish them.
So there's vis viva, which is the life of motion,
or I don't know what it means.
But Newton knows that mv squared and mv are very different.
And I don't think Galileo got that, and so he got stuck,
because they're both conserved under slightly
different conditions.
Isn't that terrible?
How many of you found that hard?
Do you remember when you learned about momentum?
I don't.
Do you mean when we write about it in a tacit knowledge sense?
No, the word.
Is it from some grade school course, or is it college?
Early grade school.
Must be grade school, because I can't remember learning it,
so I don't know.
I have a grandson who just discovered something
for the derivative of acceleration.
It's called jerk in some textbooks,
but he has a two-dimensional version,
and it took him a while to explain it to me.
I mean, it took me a while to understand it.
So I think our emotion words are not very good anyway.
If a word is old, it's probably not.
Yeah?
So you asked how can we increase the amount of people
that solve the hardest problems.
We need role models that solve hard problems.
So for example, professors that are role models for these people
kind of advertise that for people.
So an example of that, like in my high school,
my high school is very science-oriented in Brazil.
And most of the people that come here to MIT from Brazil
are from my high school, and it's kind of small.
There are, I think, two people that come from Brazil
of this high school.
Etapa.
Where?
In Sao Paulo.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
There are students that work with Winston, for example.
There is PhD students now in Harvard
that are from this high school.
And the professors, they motivate the students
by telling stories about other old people that
went through the same kind of thing
that they were going through.
Funny stories.
And they motivate by telling the story,
the successful stories.
And by saying, oh, you could go to MIT, which is a great place.
And there's these funny stories about these people
that they become kind of stars.
So can you duplicate that high school, or is it unique?
I think it can be duplicated.
You just need some smart person, or some few smart people
that can teach three or four, that teach, for example,
physics, mathematics, and chemistry.
Math is not a science, but whatever.
And you need just some role models and tell these stories.
I don't think it's hard.
It's about motivating the people.
Especially when you're young, you
motivate by creating role models.
And you say, oh, look at that guy.
He doesn't have much money, but he's a superstar.
Like, he's, I don't know, that's at least how I came here
to MIT was because there was a guy that was really, really
smart, two years older than me.
And he was famous in high school because of being here.
Well, I think the Chinese has perfected their art.
In my middle school, it's a culture
that very much has invaded every high school, every household,
to motivate people to study really hard, setting up role
models, and just, like, be able to use them.
Are they science-oriented?
They're science-oriented, and not only do they work really
hard, try to achieve, like you said,
they don't have a lot of money, whatever,
but they're superstars.
Not only do they believe in that, they also believe in,
it's OK if you try very hard and then fail at the end.
That's OK also.
So a ton of people are going to really hard math and science
training and coming out, failing because the competition is
just so intense.
But people still do it anyway, and they devote a lot of years
and lives into it.
I think that probably the best way
that people love hard problems is to, from childhood,
raise them in communities where all their peers are all
into science, because that's what they're into.
I had this experience of switching between on Long
Island, switching between high schools,
switching between junior high.
I was at a junior high for literally three miles away
from the junior high where I ended up finishing.
And the whole atmosphere of the first junior high
was just awful.
It was just these, no one cooled into science.
And so it was very, when you create people where the norm
is people who are math, science nerds,
if you create more of those places where they self-label
that way, people who are kind of on the edge,
people like, should I do math and science?
Or should I just make music or something
for the rest of my life?
They'll be more likely to just get swept up in that.
I think you need a place to be socialized
to be interested in math.
Let's ask a question of how much does what you're learning
interact with real life?
I went to a high school of science, which was great.
I remember in grade school, science was really nice.
And of course, it was pretty hard sometimes.
But then there are other things like history,
and that was incredibly hard.
How come some kids don't find history
is completely incomprehensible?
Makes no sense, and you can't figure out
what will happen next except by looking it up.
And how come most of the children
don't realize that this is too hard to pay any attention to?
I think they do realize it, but they don't pay attention to it.
Do most people hate history?
I think so.
Oh, good.
What was that, really?
I'm sorry.
I thought people took it for granted.
And I don't know, when I took history,
I think what I got out most from that class
wasn't the history itself, but rather how to frame ideas
and how to make a good argument and support it
and how to write a good paper, which are
kind of essential life skills.
Right, but even the best argument
isn't very good in that field, so it's very tough.
Well, I guess if it's hard to find exceptions,
then that gets interesting, even if the thing is wrong.
I'm not sure what I'm saying.
But if a subject has the word science in it,
it isn't social science and things.
I think with the issue of science,
there's no one solution of how to get people
motivated in science, right?
But there are several different factors.
So one factor is definitely the idea
of having a social support network,
whether it's teachers who support you
and also having peers who don't make fun of you
and ostracize you for liking science and that.
That's one.
Two, I think the curriculum itself also
has something to do with it.
As you said, I think it helps more
when people can connect it better to the real world,
to life.
And I think it also helps more when people are sort of allowed
a bit of creativity, if you will,
when they're not stuck doing growth problems all the time.
And I think another issue is sort
of presenting problems and solutions and lessons
to students in such a way that they're sufficiently
challenged, but they're not discouraged
because it's too difficult. And on the other hand,
they're not bored because it's too repetitive.
So I think it's sort of like a delicate balance, right?
All these factors must be there.
Yeah, and that also relates to the hour problem,
like when can you give someone a problem that
might take a whole day or two?
And there's no place for that in, well, there must be.
Where in school do you get, that's
when you have to write a term paper, maybe.
And I think another thing about science and math,
perhaps, at least the grade school incarnations
of those subjects, is that they tend
to be a lot more isolating than subjects in the humanities,
in the sense that when you're stuck at home doing science
and math problems, you're always by yourself.
And you're always encouraged to essentially quarantine
yourself to study these things and come up with solutions.
Whereas classes in history or foreign languages or English
are more like discussion space.
And actually, I think that's sort of, I don't know,
because in real life, when you solve scientific problems,
you are working on a team a lot of the time.
And you have to communicate your ideas.
And you kind of are working together.
But somehow, in grade school, you're
stuck working on these problems by yourself.
I think that might also be a contributing factor.
Interesting.
Well, if you try to solve a geometry problem,
have you ever solved a problem working with someone else?
Does it help?
Or are they always interrupting you so you can't concentrate?
In undergrad, for instance, there will be office hours
or open office hours where students all come together
and help each other a little or give hints, things like that.
And it tends to help for at least most people.
But I guess I'm mostly encountering the other people
who go to these things.
I think in grade school, it's too,
one, the problems that you have to master are too simple.
It only requires one flash of insight to solve the problem.
And that flash of insight you're supposed
to work towards on your own.
Whereas if there's a problem that takes a day to solve,
that takes five flashes of insight,
consecutive flashes of insight to solve it,
then it's a collaborative.
OK, here's a problem.
There's an isosceles.
These two sides are equal.
So that's an isosceles triangle.
So now, here are two angle bisectors.
So if the triangle is isosceles, prove
that the angle bisectors are equal.
Has anybody proved it yet?
Well, it's very easy.
But here's your homework.
If you have a triangle and the angle bisectors are equal,
prove that the corresponding sides are equal.
And see who can get the shortest proof.
It's pretty hard.
Have you ever read the essay by Paul Lockhart
called A Mathematician's Limit?
What's the third word?
A mathematician's lament.
Living?
Lament.
No, I don't think so.
It's sort of his critique on math education in America.
It's quite interesting.
Yeah, I was just thinking that, well,
you mentioned that mathematics tends to be pretty slow.
But Marvin brought up that, and I
was thinking that for many kinds of mathematical problems,
you can prove theorems in different ways.
And then somebody comes up with a proof,
and then you challenge that, OK, now somebody else
finds another kind of proof.
Better, please.
You can have a homework of, OK, come up
with four different ways of proving this thing.
And always, everything goes.
So if you want to work together with people,
you can pull out your proofs.
So that's why Feynman said he was so great.
That is, when he had a physics problem,
he forced himself to find several different ways.
And he said all of his friends, when
they learned quantum mechanics, either learned the Heisenberg
matrix method or the Schrodinger differential equation method
or the Dirac technique.
And whenever he had a problem, he
would solve it by all known techniques.
And then in later life, he rarely
got stuck where most people did.
Yeah?
So related to that, the best mathematicians that I know
are people that they stay with a problem,
and they solve by themselves.
They don't go and look for the solution
or ask other people.
They try to solve it by themselves.
And I believe it's just because of the way
we created pathways.
I believe that's a-
But there are quite a few pairs of mathematicians.
Yeah, but when you're young, you should
try to solve the problems by yourself,
at least when you're in middle school or high school.
And then you create these pathways.
Right.
Maybe when you get older, the problems are too hard.
And then it doesn't help to solve the problem by yourself,
because you're not going to solve harder problems
than those ones.
How many of you have ever solved a math
problem with someone else?
Quite a few.
It seemed like they could solve it.
I remember being in a boat with Seymour Papert,
solving some really hard problem.
And after a while, he got tired of it
and slipped into the water and went swimming around.
And I said, come back.
He said, why?
And I said, I'll tell you when you get here.
And he got back before the shark.
Did I ever tell you about it?
We thought it was a dolphin for a while.
But it had this fin on the back that didn't seem quite right.
OK.
Anyway, I did a lot of solving with.
I don't remember ever solving a hard problem with three people.
That's nice.
Well, you have to see 436 problem of the necessary height.
It says low battery.
Is that a coincidence?
Oh, ringing the bell must have dropped the voltage.
The low battery went on about one second
after I stopped the quack.