The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
I usually start by asking if there are any questions,
but I thought I'd say a few things about chapter one
and then see if there are any questions.
I can't see the pointer.
Oh, anybody remember how to get word to?
Make its pointer not disappear.
Maybe I mentioned this in the first lecture,
but I was taken by this cute poem by Dorothy Parker
because the first chapter was about love and stuff
like that.
So I tried to get the rights to reproduce it,
and it turned out that she was angry at all her friends.
She must have been a perpetually pissed off person.
And so she left all her literary rights to the NAACP,
and I called them up for hours, and they
couldn't find the rights.
So finally, so it's in the version of the emotion
machine on the web, but I had to resort to Shakespeare
to replace her.
Shakespeare's a slightly better poet,
but he's not as funny as Dorothy Parker.
So the first chapter starts out, or it's mostly
about all the things we don't understand about the mind,
which is almost everything.
And the first discussion is, well, the whole chapter
is making fun of the most popular ideas.
And the most popular idea of the mind
is that people think that they're not doing the thinking,
but there's something inside them that's doing the thinking.
And this idea that there is a self
is embedded in just about everything we say and think.
And really, it's hard to see how you would do without it.
But if you ask, what is the self,
then since this idea is so popular,
people begin to believe that there is such a thing,
and it takes all sorts of various forms.
And the most dangerous form, maybe,
is the one that religions exploit,
which is that inside a person with all their complications,
there's a little pure essence called the soul, or the self,
or whatever you want to call it.
And it's impossible to describe it or explain it
in physical terms.
And so that is one of the reasons why we think there are
two worlds, a physical world and lots of other kinds of worlds.
Each of us has some imaginary model of what they are
and what they're in.
And philosophers talk about it and existentialists and so on.
So there are lots of problems about our ideas,
about ourselves.
And in reading around for half my life,
I was puzzled at the strange ideas that are around.
And in Aristotle, I find the first intelligible theories
of mind and emotions.
So if you look at particular Aristotle's,
there are a number of books.
And one of them is called Rhetoric.
And it's full of theories about how people reason and influence
each other.
And I'll show you some quotes from that.
Because when I look at the history
that I've encountered about psychology,
Aristotle stands out as being the first and among the best.
And as far as I can see, there were no psychologists nearly
as good as him.
Of course, we don't know whether there was a him exactly.
Because what we have of Aristotle,
and there's a lot of writing, but it's all cobbled together
by students from all sorts of manuscripts by other people,
and people who took notes.
And Aristotle claims to have learned a lot from Plato.
We have very little writing from him.
And so there you go three centuries
before the Christian era, as it's called.
And then a couple of thousand years later,
you start to find people like Spinoza, and Kant, and John
Locke, and David Hume, who start to make psychology theories,
very little of which is as good as the ones that Aristotle
has in all his fragments.
So one question that frequently bothers me,
and it should bother everyone, is why did science
disappear for 1,000 years?
And the standard explanation is the rise
of the great religions, and why did it come back?
And you see with the first signs of anything
like modern science, at least in my view,
with Galileo and Newton, there are
a couple of people before that.
There are some people in the Muslim world
who invented some high school algebra,
and they make a big fuss about that.
It looks like Archimedes, in a very recently discovered
manuscript, computed an integral.
He found the volume of a cone, which is, what is it?
Sixth BH, I forget.
Anyway, so why did science disappear?
And why did psychology appear so late?
Because there isn't much psychology in the modern sense
until 1900, or the late 1800s, with Francis Galton
and William James lived around here,
and Rudolf Fleiss, Sigmund Freud, starts writing in 1895.
People make fun of Freud, as I mentioned last week.
But in fact, among other things, how many of you
have read the recent criticisms of Freud,
which claim that he was a complete faker
and never cured a single patient?
This is popular stuff.
I don't believe Freud ever really
claimed to cure a single patient.
So the critics, who are really very ferocious,
claim that he made up all his data and so forth.
But most of what Freud says is that psychoanalysis
might be a good way to find out what you're really thinking
and discover more about yourself and your goals and so forth.
And I had the good or bad luck to be introduced to L. Ron
Hubbard by John.
When I was an undergraduate, John Campbell
was the great editor of the, I think
it was called Astounding Science Fiction in those days.
What a marvelous title.
And this fairly mediocre science fiction writer, L. Ron Hubbard,
invented a new form of psychiatry called,
what was it called?
Dianetics.
It's pretty good.
And I'll tell you that story another time.
But John Campbell had Thanksgiving in the Commander
Hotel every year and invited a bunch of friends.
And I don't remember if that's how
I got to meet Asimov and Heinlein and other people.
But anyway, I did, and science fiction
had a big influence on me from my actually early years.
But starting in college, it got very serious.
Anyway, so chapter one starts to talk
about this phenomenon of psychology.
And one of the funny parts is this little section 3,
1.3 of trying to say, what are emotions?
And I looked up emotions in dictionaries.
And can you all read that?
I don't feel like reading aloud.
But there's lots of discussion of emotions
and how mysterious and complex they are.
And then the marvelous thing is how many words
there are for emotional states.
I think I got 300, but I don't remember.
Anyway, here's from A to D. And I don't recall
how I found those, but I think that's a lot.
How many words for ways to think are there?
Now, that's a serious question because I complained,
maybe, on the next page.
No, I didn't.
I found myself complaining that there were very few words
for ways to think.
And then this afternoon, when I was pruning these slides,
it occurred to me that I didn't really try.
So maybe I just didn't think enough.
So if there are a couple of hundred words
for everyday emotions, if any of you
can find me a list of 10 or 20 common words
for styles of thinking, I'd appreciate it because I
wonder if there are a lot.
And if not, why not?
So here's a list of typical situations,
grieving for a lost child, panic at being in an enclosed space.
I'm not sure any of the words in the list of 300 standard
emotions are good enough to describe
how you feel for any of these not unusual states.
Have you ever lost control of your car at high speed?
No, but when I first learned to drive,
I couldn't believe that you could read signs at the same
time as.
Well, anyway, one of the very best psychologists in history,
or pair of psychologists, aren't even called psychologists.
These are two guys named Conrad Lorenz and Nico Tinbergen.
And somebody made up the word ethology.
What they study is the behavior of animals.
And in some sense, presumably, they're
studying the psychology of animals
because just as with a person, when somebody flies into a rage,
you're not describing their mental state.
You're describing something about how they behave.
And so the ethologists, too, are psychologists.
And Tinbergen and Lorenz, starting around 1920s,
started to analyze the behavior of animals in great detail.
And so here's an example of how a certain fish behaves.
I actually forgot which fish it is,
but there's a picture of it in the book.
And at different points in its life,
it's in different phases.
And this is just one diagram of a dozen
for this particular fish and its reproduction, which
involves an environment with plants and other things.
And it divides its behavior into parenting, courtship,
nesting, and fighting.
And then you see each of those as a lot of subdivisions.
And Tinbergen and Lorenz and some students
discovered all these things by sitting in front of fish tanks
and watching the fish for months and years.
Tinbergen also spent years on some beach watching seagulls.
And so he has a diagram like this
for a particular class of seagulls.
When I came to Boston, my friends and I
used to go to Nahant and look at these tide pools
there, where there are a lot of activities.
And it was very interesting.
And I got a big fish tank and imported
all sorts of little animals and plants
from the tide pools in Nahant.
And I watched them for about a year and didn't learn anything.
And that was before I read Tinbergen.
And then I realized there's something
about those people, which is they could watch a fish
and recognize all sorts of behaviors.
And I would just watch a fish and wonder whether it was hungry
or what.
Wouldn't you get bored swimming back and forth for three years
in this?
Anyway, so here are the great psychologists of our day,
Aristotle 2,000 years ago, and Lorentz and Tinbergen
in the 1930s, and Sigmund Freud and Galton and William James
around 1900.
And then what went wrong?
There's almost no good psychology
between then and 1950s, when something called cognitive
psychology started.
And it was partly due to people who said,
let's make psychology more scientific.
And you've probably all heard of Pavlov or Watson.
And what happened is around 1900, some psychologists said,
well, these Galton's and Freud's and William James
are very poetic and expressive and literary.
And they write much better than we do and tells good stories.
But they're not scientists.
And they don't do reproducible experiments.
So what we have to do is simplify the situation
to find the basic laws of behavior.
So let's take a pigeon and put it in a vacuum in the dark.
Well, they didn't go that far.
But they did put it in the dark.
And there were two illuminated levers to work.
And you could make a sound.
And the sound could be very annoying.
Or you could have a bright, annoying flashing
light or something.
And the animal would push one of two levers.
And one of them would make the stimulus even more annoying.
And one of them would make it go away.
And you'd plot curves of how often the animal pressed
these levers.
So you would get a quantitative theory of how much it learned
and how much it could remember and how many trials it
would have to do.
Then instead of just looking at reactions to stimuli,
they quickly switched to trying to teach the animal things
by giving it two alternatives, turn left or turn right
or push this button or that or whatever.
And if they pushed the one you approve of,
then you'd give them a little pellet of food.
And there was a lot of engineering
so that you would make sure that the food got to them
right away.
Because if there were a 10-second delay
between an action and a reward, the pigeon or a squirrel
or a rat or a cat or a dog would learn much less quickly
than if there was a one-second delay.
And anyway, that went on for 50 years, starting around 1900,
Pavlov and his dogs.
And there's a great movie that some guy came around with
that had been taken of Pavlov's lab.
And it shows sort of like a great dictator or something.
There's this room with a lot of cages and dogs and mostly
dogs in this case.
And Pavlov comes in, and there are
a bunch of lackeys who sort of bow and scrape
because he's a lord.
And he comes in, and all the dogs
run into the corner of their cage and yelp.
So the Pavlovians tried pretty hard
to get that movie suppressed.
And I haven't seen it in recent years.
But anyway, Fred Skinner, who was a professor when
I was an undergraduate at Harvard,
was the first one to really automate
this experimental psychology.
And he invented what's called a Skinner box,
but it's just a soundproof, lightproof, well-ventilated
and thermally regulated cage.
And you can put a rat or a pigeon.
Those are the most common animals.
They're very inexpensive because they're free.
No one knows much about dolphins.
They've been studied for 50 years.
Whenever John Watts's name, remember
the name of the great dolphin?
Lily, thanks.
He discovered a lot about dolphins
and a certain amount about their communication
and a little bit about whales.
But there's an interesting mystery.
I forget which whales, but some whales have a 20-minute song.
And they repeat it for a whole season.
And next year, that song is a little bit different.
But it goes essentially without repeating.
It's very complicated for 20 minutes.
And people have studied that a lot.
And no one has the slightest idea of what it means.
And nobody even has any good conjectures, which bothers me.
What I think it probably means is this.
When there's a whole bunch of fish somewhere
for one of these whales, it might be 200 miles away.
Whales eat a lot.
And it's very important to find where the fish are.
And I believe this message, which
changes a bit during the season, might be telling you
where the food is on the Atlantic or Pacific coastline
in great detail.
Because if somebody finds a lot of fish somewhere,
you have to swim 300 miles.
And if they're not there.
So anyway, it's interesting that John Lilly got a lot
of publicity, but he didn't discover squat.
And finally, the dolphin study years
gave up because nothing happened.
Anybody have heard anything?
I haven't paid any attention for 20 years.
Have you heard of anybody discovering anything
about dolphins?
Except they're very good at solving
a lot of physical problems.
Anyway, I'm bothered by the mystery
of why was there some psychology in Aristotle's time.
And why didn't it get anywhere till 1950
when there was regular psychology?
But it was afflicted by what I call physics envy.
Namely, you run into people like Estes.
And well, he was pretty good, actually.
But there are a lot of psychologists who made up
things like Maxwell's equations for how animals learn.
And there were generally three or four laws.
And if there's a sequence of events,
then animals remember a lot about the first few
and the last few in the sequence.
They don't remember much about the middle.
And of course, the reliability of their memory
depends a lot on how recent it was
and on how powerful the reward was and blah, blah, blah.
And so they get these little sets of rules
that look like Newton's laws.
And that was the kind of sort of psychological physics
that the so-called behaviorists were mostly looking for.
This was not what Tinbergen and Lorentz did,
because they wrote books with extensive descriptions
of what the animals did and made little diagrammatic guesses
about the structure of the subroutines
and substructures.
Anyway, end of history, but it's a nice question.
Why do some sciences grow?
And why was psychology just about the last one?
I suspect it was it could have been earlier,
but people tried to imitate the physicists
and tried to say maybe there's something like Newton's
or Maxwell's laws for the mind.
And they found a few, but they weren't enough to explain much.
So there are a lot of questions.
When Seymour Papert and I started
thinking about these things, which was really around 1960,
I had been working on some ideas about AI in the late 50s.
And my PhD thesis was a theory of neural networks,
which was sort of interesting, but never really
went anywhere.
I went to a meeting in London somewhere
and gave a talk about a theory of learning
that was based on some neural network ideas.
And there was this person from South Africa
named Seymour Papert who gave the same paper.
And I hope this happens to you someday.
Find somebody who thinks so much like you,
only different enough that it's worth it
and that you only have to say about three words a day
and some whole new thing starts, because we really
did write the same paper and it had the same equation in it.
And he had been working for Piaget,
who was the first great child psychologist.
I should have mentioned Piaget, who probably
discovered more things about psychology
than any other single person in history.
And there are lots of people now who say,
he was wrong about 0.73, because children learned that
at the age of 2 and 1 half instead of 2 and 3 quarters.
I'm parodying the Piaget critic community,
but it's pretty bad.
And I think those poor guys are uncomfortable,
because Jean Piaget published 20 books full of observations
about children that, as far as I know,
no one had made systematically before.
And in his later years, he started
courting algebraic mathematicians,
because he wanted more formal theories.
And in my view, he wanted to make his theories worse,
and nothing much happened.
But he did visit here a couple of times,
and it was really exciting to meet
the starter of a whole new field.
Anyway, Papert and I discussed lots of things,
and somehow or other, we kept finding more ideas
about psychology.
And it finally gelled into the idea that, well,
if you look at the brain, you know
that there are several hundred different brain centers.
What's all that stuff for?
And how could it possibly make any sense
to try to explain what it does in terms
of four laws like Newton?
How does a car work?
Is there a magical force inside the engine that
causes the wheels to turn?
No.
There's this funny thing in the back
to cause a differential, so that if the car isn't
going in a straight line, the two wheels
going at different speeds won't rip the.
If the two wheels were going at the same speed,
the tread would come off in five minutes.
You ever wonder what a differential is for?
So most of the car is fixing bugs in the other parts.
Most of the brain is because we started out
as fish or lizards or whatever you like.
And making the brain bigger wouldn't
help much because you'd just get a heavier lizard that
had to eat more and would think more slowly.
So size is bad.
But on the other hand, if you need another cubic inch
of brain to fix the bugs in the other part,
then the evolutionary advantage of being smarter
had better make you able to catch a little more
food per hour.
And so each person is an ecology of these different processes.
And the brain reached its present size
about a million years ago, I guess.
What's the current guess?
Anybody been tracked?
They keep discovering new ancestors of humans.
And I don't have the patience to read about them
because you know that next week somebody will say,
oh, that isn't in the main line.
And you were just unlucky to discover that skeleton.
So anyway, Papert and I and a lot of students
gradually developed this picture that the mind is made
of lots of processes or agents or resources
or whatever you want to call them.
And it's anybody's guess what they are.
If you look at the anatomy of the brain,
you know that people label regions.
So it's very clear that this occipital lobe back here
is largely concerned with vision.
But I forget where the one for hearing is.
If you destroy the part of the brain
for hearing in some animals, you get a little bit
of increased function in some part of the visual system
that seems to enable the animal to hear a little bit
and make some reactions.
And there's a whole lot of hype, I think you have to call it,
about the flexibility of the nervous system.
That is, if certain brain areas get destroyed,
other parts take over.
They almost never are as good.
And mostly, many functions never get taken over at all
but are replaced by ones that superficially seem similar.
And so there's a whole lot of, I guess,
wishful thinking that the brain is immensely resourceful
and error-correcting and repairing.
I think there was some idea that that was a general phenomenon.
But if you do some arithmetic, you
get an interesting result. Suppose
that each function in the brain occurred
in 10 different places at random.
Then if you removed half the brain,
how many functions would you lose?
Well, almost no arithmetic tells you
you would lose about one part in 1,000.
And so, in fact, you would never be able to detect it.
So this idea that the brain has enormous redundancy
will now change that number to five.
Suppose each function is somewhat
supported in five different parts of the brain.
Then if you take off half the brain, then what am I saying?
One part in 32, chance of losing some significant function.
So probably lots of things that we do
are supported in several parts of the brain.
Apparently, the language center is pretty unique,
and some others.
But be careful about the conclusions
you read from optimistic neuroscientists.
Anyway, Papert and I worked on this idea
of how could these large numbers of different processes
be organized.
And we made various theories about it.
And then around, I guess, the late 1970s,
we stopped working together.
And Papert developed his revolutionary ideas
about education, which certainly have had a lot of influence,
although they didn't sweep the world in the way we had hoped.
And I kept working on the society of mind theory.
And we didn't work together so much,
but we still did plenty of criticizing
and supporting of each other.
Anyway, my theory ended up with this idea
that is sort of based on Freud.
I don't know if I kept a picture of his here.
Freud concluded that the mind was an interesting arena,
sort of.
And he had the mind divided into three parts.
At one end of the mind, which were inherited
from most other animals, is called
the id, which is a bunch of instinctive,
mainly built-in behavioral mechanisms.
And a second part of the mind is
what he called the superego, which
is a collection of critics.
So in Freud's first image, the brain is in two parts.
One is a set of instinctive, built-in behaviors.
And the other is a set of critics,
which actually are associated with a culture or, well,
culture and a tradition.
And you learn from other people things that are good to do
and things that are bad to do.
And that's called the superego.
This is your set of values and standards
and tests for suitable behavior.
And the middle is this strange object
called the ego, which is not what people think it is.
At least Freud's word, the ego is
a kind of big, neutral battleground
where the instinctive behaviors I keep wanting to.
Oh, you can see that arrow if I take my finger off it.
And then gradually, as I kept trying
to figure out how problems are solved
and what kind of processes might be involved,
I got this picture, which has six layers.
And various people come around and say,
I don't think you need to distinguish between layers
four and five.
Why don't you just lump all the three top layers into one?
And I sort of laugh quietly and say,
these people are trying to find a physics-like, unified,
minimal theory of psychology.
And they're probably right in one sense.
But if they do that, they'll get stuck.
Because if you get a new idea, there'll be no place to put it.
So if you have something that's very mysterious,
don't imitate the physicists.
Because if you make a theory that's exactly right
and just accounts for the data and there's nothing extra
and nothing loose, then when you notice a new phenomenon,
like dark matter, then the physicists
don't know what to do.
Should they regard dark matter as some obscure feature
of spacetime, or does it have something
to do with this universe being near another one
that you can't otherwise communicate with?
And it's all very puzzling.
But there are lots of things that don't fit into Newton's
laws these days.
And I'm not suggesting a six-layer theory of physics,
but it might be worth a try.
OK, so what am I?
I made up some nice slides, but I think I'll stop.
So who has some questions?
And what would you like to see in a theory of psychology?
What do you want to be explained?
A lot of people are convinced that there
are some really serious problems and mysteries,
like what is consciousness?
And if you look at chapter 4, my feeling
is consciousness is an etymological accident
that people got a word, which is a suitcase for all
of the things they don't understand
about the mind and more.
But once you've got a word and it goes in the culture,
consider the word consciousness for a minute
from a legal point of view.
Suppose that you happen to be walking along,
and you're carrying something.
Where is that pointer?
And it happens to stick somebody's eye out.
Then it's very important when they sue you
to establish whether you meant to do it
or whether it was an accident.
Did you consciously plan to?
I can't think of the English word for it.
I can't think of the English word
for putting somebody's eye out.
There's beheading and also gouges is a good word.
So anyway, it's very important for social reasons
to have a word for whether an action was deliberately
violating the rules as opposed to accidentally violating
the rules, like if you tripped on the stairs
and landed on somebody and broke their neck.
That's not a crime unless you were
so clever as to make it appear that it was an accident.
Anyway, you see what I mean?
So our whole system of fairness and ethics
and social responsibility is based
on the distinction between whether an action was
deliberate or not.
And so did he do that consciously is a word for that.
And somehow the idea of conscious became elevated.
Well, that's a very superficial.
You can probably think of 10 other reasons
why a word like that.
Yes?
Yeah, Martin, sometimes in your writing,
it seems to me that there's both sides of it.
Sometimes you argue with both sides of it.
It seems like in that kind of, I can well imagine
there's that kind of representation.
You have representation of self and representation
of your mind.
But then you say there's no self or no consciousness.
Why can't you think about consciousness
as just a process that is reasoning about your own mind?
Is there a problem with that?
I understand you don't want to talk about soul
because that's a religious notion.
No, but sometimes when you say conscious, that is,
do you remember doing it?
Which is?
Yeah, but don't I load up my process
that asks me what I think about my own mind?
And then I retrieve that and I say, yeah, I do remember it.
Well, you're right, actually.
I went to a lot of trouble to find
25 or 30 different uses for the word consciousness.
And probably if one of us worked harder,
we could take those and condense them
into five or six much better ones that account for more
stuff than the 30.
Well, I think you've got five right there, ideas, goals,
memory, thoughts, and feelings, right?
That might be just right for something.
Yes, well, I think that's a great criticism of one reason
why people don't like these theories quite so much,
because I propose too many things.
I really should reprint that criticism from Restak
or hand it out, because it's this neurologist who says,
why is he telling us all these things about k-lines
and representations and so forth?
The answer is, he's from a community
that doesn't have enough variety yet.
And I'd be the first to admit that I
try to go overboard and think of five more things
than are in the literature.
But that emotion thing is nice.
Remember, that was a serious challenge,
because when I made that list, I do have a laser pointer
somewhere in my jacket, probably.
How many words for at least noticeably distinct ways
of thinking, or reasoning, or figuring out,
or solving problems can you think of?
Maybe there are 20 or 30.
I just realized this afternoon that I never looked.
I don't remember where I got this list.
Yeah?
Can I ask about your perception of free will?
And I got it from a reading that you don't have a strong sense
of free will, and so what is that?
I think it's the same as the one for consciousness.
Namely, it's a legal concept.
The idea of free will is completely obscene, isn't it?
What could it possibly mean if you
did something for no reason?
So it's a thoroughly empty idea, isn't it?
Or what do you mean by it?
Do you mean there's nobody ordering you around,
so you're free to do whatever you want?
But of course, you're not.
You can only do what your computer computes you to do.
In a sense, in the same way that you
draw in the fish diagram, the fish's actions
are products of the environment and of its current state,
and it's essentially a Turing machine.
Well, it's some kind of machine, yes, sure.
And so would you argue that we are also
Turing machines that are just running out in the world?
Sure.
I've never heard of any even interesting alternative.
In other words, people who insist on free will
appear to me to be like people who
believe that there must be a god who created the world.
What's the next step?
Who created the god?
They don't take that step.
So if your will is free, OK, then who is controlling it?
There's nothing there.
But legally, it's great, because if somebody stole
so many of their own free will.
But suppose you were a peculiar kind of epileptic,
and every now and then when you go by,
your hand goes out and steals things.
Then they, what do they do?
They put you on parole?
This is very strange.
But if you look at religions, you
see that people make money on them.
13% of the world's product goes to people
who make their living on concepts like free will
and consciousness.
So it's a big money thing.
It's not just an accident.
It's an industry.
So both of those are constructs of society.
And if you could imagine a society
without the concept of consciousness and free will,
those are requirements for being free.
I don't think you could.
You'd have to make up something to keep people in check
and under control and to train them.
It's like the rat needs somebody to press the reward or punish
button.
And we have it built into our culture
works because you build into people's head
the machinery for suppressing doubt.
And it's very clever.
But you should think of it as an industry rather
than an inexplicable phenomenon.
How much money goes into it?
Yes?
How many ways of thinking can you think of?
Say it again.
How many ways of thinking can you think of right now?
That's my challenge, in fact.
There's probably a big list in some chapter or other,
but there's nothing like this.
What's the trick?
If I go like that.
Actually, Dragon has a thing, so you can tell it
to make things bigger.
How many of you used the new Dragon program speech thing?
I can't believe how good it is.
Oh, I was talking to Henry Lieberman about it earlier.
Yes?
So I'm under the impression that you
would say that the side of mind theory
applies both to humans and animals.
Is it just that we have higher levels of organization in them?
So where would you draw that line?
Like, do animals not have a notion of the self
the way you described it, like long-term planning and stuff?
That's a great question.
And it'd be interesting to think about ways to investigate it.
And researchers are often, in fact,
raising that question of, do animals
have a representation of themselves?
And there's a famous experiment, but I
can't remember what its current status is,
where you put a red dot on a chimpanzee's head.
And when the chimp passes a mirror and sees that,
the chimp might go like that.
Whereas I don't think a dog, when it passes a mirror,
would rub its forehead to see if it has a red spot.
I had a cat who walked past mirrors,
because we have some wall, full-size mirrors
around the house.
And the cat walks by, and there's
this other cat going in the mirror.
And she pays no attention to it, whatever.
So of course, I don't know what happened the first three times
she walked by that mirror, because if you
see another cat going by, you'd think it would.
Anyway, it's a good question, and people ask that.
And there's some evidence that elephants
have a model of themselves, and maybe dolphins.
And I don't know where.
Have any of you heard any stories of other animals
that can recognize, for example, when they've been painted?
Which?
Elephants?
Yes, I think elephants.
If things can't, the dolphins don't know when things can.
So there's a famous child psychology
experiment where, if you're less than a couple months old,
you actually fail this test.
Oh.
So it's actually something that comes
and is a sign of your child progressing.
So it might not be intrinsic to humanity in every sense.
So I'm sure an invention that you probably can do, yeah.
This is off the topic, but I once
had a great email correspondence with some woman who
was getting a PhD in France about how babies
recognize their mothers.
And she concluded with, you did experiments
after having other people walk into the room
with a mask of the mother or a different hairdo and so forth.
And for the first two months or three months,
I think, it turned out that the baby recognizes the mother
by the hairdo, which had not been known.
Then I think after three months, it's recognizing the mother
by a face.
And at that point, she's doing experiments
where you get another woman wearing
the face, a copy of the mother's face.
And so now there's two mothers, and the baby
is absolutely delighted.
And then, as I can't remember, but then I
think at four or five months, when
two copies of the mother comes in,
the baby gets really panicked.
So I lost track of her.
If you have a baby, let me know.
She got her PhD for this, and I haven't heard anything since.
Yes?
Here's a sort of half-formulated thought
that I just thought of regarding ways of thinking
and ways of feeling.
So it just occurred to me that it
seems like, if you go back to the list of feelings,
it seems like when we talk about feeling,
we're talking about a state that the brain is in.
So it might be a complicated state that's
like some combination of a lot of different parameters,
but it's a state that you can stay in
for an arbitrary amount of time.
But I think thinking is something
that's more sequential, as in when you're thinking
you're necessarily changing the state of your brain
all the time because you're moving bits around.
So I don't know.
I just thought of it that way.
No, I think that's right.
When we talk about intelligent behavior,
you're absolutely right.
What you've got is a process that's criticizing itself
and seeing when you got stuck and finding things to do.
And I suppose in each emotional state,
you're certainly also thinking.
So that's going on, but maybe it's more restricted,
like if you're confronting somebody
and there's a sort of conflict, then almost all your thoughts
are constrained to that subject.
And it's not as resourceful, but I'm just improvising.
Or perhaps for each emotional state,
when we say that we're in an emotional state,
the things that we're talking about
are the certain switches that get flipped in a certain state
or something that's above a certain threshold.
And you can have thoughts that are
about anything in that state, but perhaps the state itself
influences the type of thoughts that you're likely to have.
OK, I think what I'm talking about in this context
is sort of extreme forms where the person changes
into another machine, and it's like an angry person
won't listen to reason, or it's very hard to deflect them.
And so it's this kind of rigid thing.
But humans are generally are rarely
in such extreme states where nothing gets through.
The whole point of that was that I just
realized that I maybe was just too lazy,
that we have this huge vocabulary of nuances
of emotional activity.
And also, people think that these
are hard to explain and mysterious and non-physical
and blah, blah, blah.
But why do we wait till next week
and see if somebody comes up with or see if we can come up
with a set of 30 or 40 words about intellectual states,
curiosity of I just don't know how many there are.
And I haven't thought of any in the last few minutes.
Yes?
Has anybody thought of a couple of?
What's the word?
Like when you're really engaged in some activity
that you're doing and you're really in the zone.
Yes, there's a state of keeping other things out
so you can focus, not being interruptible.
Yes?
So in this side of mind, you talk about agents
and how they divide between themselves.
But I don't see anywhere about how evolution modified a lot
agents.
Like I believe that evolution modified the way we
think right now.
I don't know if you saw there is a paper
wrote like two years ago that's called The Region of Behavior.
And this guy tried to explain how we make some decisions.
Evolutionary, like in a point of view of our speech,
we are maximizing the probability
of we reproducing ourselves.
But individually, we are not increasing these efficiencies.
And I think somehow the decisions of agents or resources
would be very determined by evolution
since we have a very long time of evolution
of the human being.
And somehow we have hardwired to make some decisions.
So for example, he gives the example of a guy.
Well, for lizards, that's certainly true.
But why do you use humans keep changing their environment?
So for example, yeah.
So he gives this example of tossing a coin.
The guy says that this coin is unfair.
And he doesn't say the probabilities.
But there is 75% of getting heads
and 25% of getting tails.
And like the subjects, they choose
randomly 25% of the time the tails,
even though they can take account of the number of times
that you put heads.
And even though if you choose always heads,
you would get more money or whatever.
You would make the right decision.
That's called probability matching.
And it's not a good strategy.
Yeah, but humans do that.
No.
Well, they do it if the psychologist rigs
the experiment very carefully.
It turns out that the best thing to do.
What do you think is the optimal strategy?
No.
The optimal strategy turns out it's
the square roots of the probabilities normalized
to add up to 1.
And I'll give you a proof next time.
This theorem is due to Ray Solomonoff,
who invented inductive probability theory.
But like evolution.
So evolution, if evolution did probability matching,
then it would be wrong.
And I bet you'll find out that those experiments are wrong.
You have to see.
How did he rig the experiment so that people,
if it's probability 25%, they guess that 25%?
They made the experiments with goldfish.
I don't know.
There was a theory about why you would expect it.
It's a good question.
I don't think people use probabilities, though.
So even if an experiment shows some,
I would look for a flaw in the design of the experiment.
Yes.
So Professor Lindsay, you talked a lot about motion
in today's lecture.
And my understanding is that if someone
has a specific personality, they might have a predisposition
to feel a certain motion, like anger, depression, or whatnot.
My question is that if you had any insider theories on to what
extent our personality is affected by events or influences
that happened to us over the course of a lifetime,
and to what extent is it impacted
by chemical or biological makeup of our brain?
Well, you're asking, what do people learn?
We don't care if it's chemical or, see, if it's chemical,
it's still physical.
I read a little bit of that sort of treatments
for depression.
And the argument is that a lot of the reasons for depression
is because of some sort of chemical or biological way
our brain is constructed.
Well, there's lots of complicated things
about the brain.
One feature of the brain that I don't know if everybody,
you know that there are inhibitory and excitatory
synapses.
When one neuron connects to another,
the impulse that goes along the axon to the target neuron
may reduce the probability or the strength of its firing
or increase it.
So that's called inhibiting or exciting.
That's not quite the right word, is it?
Now, generally, in the nervous system, as a rule,
but not always, if you follow a chain of activity,
it goes inhibiting, exciting, inhibiting, exciting.
If you had too many excitatory things and there was a loop,
then it would explode and it would wear itself out
and jig time.
So there is this general feature of the anatomy
that you alternate.
So when somebody talks about a drug having
an inhibitory effect, that's sort of weird
because it's inhibiting half the neurons
and therefore lowering the thresholds of the ones
they're connected to and so on.
So I think the best thing is until you
have a diagram of the functional relations
between different brain centers, it
might be best not to try to make generalizations about how
the chemistry works.
It's easy, but people think of adrenaline as a stimulant,
but in the nervous epinephrine.
But in the nervous system, locally,
it may be inhibiting things that are inhibiting something else.
And so it appears to be exciting.
Yes?
I have a problem understanding the difference
between thoughts and emotions.
I know it might be a simple thing,
but since the only thing that I can separate in my mind
is that thoughts, so let's call it a time constant,
I can change it kind of rapidly.
Emotions, time constant is small, and I can control it again,
much less.
But since there is no, at least in this class,
there is no free will, how can I make a decision
on where the dividing line between these two entities is?
Oh, I think it's a waste of time.
As far as I can see, emotional mechanisms
are generally lower level, simpler ones
than the ones that involve several layers of the,
more layers of the brain.
So it's just a relative thing.
It's not that some states are emotional.
You're always having some high level thoughts
and low level thoughts.
And the distinction, I just don't
know why the distinction has occupied so much attention.
I think it's because, and that goes back
to having more words for, or asking,
how many words do we have for ways to think?
It seems to me that in popular culture,
there are very few words for ways to think,
and lots of words for emotions, and so they're very prominent.
Maybe you have to be smarter to distinguish between ways
to think, and people generally are dumb.
Not because they're inherently dumb,
but they come from cultures which bully you if you,
you know what happens if you're in third grade and you're smart.
You get it beaten out of you, and you learn not to show it.
I kind of think like that question of why science
happened earlier, like why don't we
have more ways to describe different ways to think.
And that's sort of puzzling, but have we just not
reflected as much on the different thinking
states or different approaches?
I wonder if the Greeks had more, but we didn't.
I think they did, I think they had also more concept of ideas
in different states, in different potencies.
Who has a theory of that?
What's your theory of the Middle Ages?
How could things get so dark for so long?
Well, I do have a theory, but I didn't.
And are we about to have one?
I think it has as much to do with the channels
in which one can communicate ideas to other people,
whether they exist or not, or whether the attributes
are underclosed.
The Middle Ages were characterized
by scientific discoveries being kept as family secrets.
Ah, Carden knew how to take Hume roots,
and he wouldn't tell anyone.
Well, the classic stupid example is baby tunnels,
which for 300 years made a single Italian family very rich.
Using tunnels to extract a baby in childbirth
increased success rate in difficult births by about 10%,
they say.
Wow.
And that was enough to build a family fortune,
until some servant finally spilled jeans,
and that was the end of that.
Yeah, wow.
So who has a theory of the Middle Ages?
Is there a standard theory?
Yes.
Well, the concept of the Middle Ages as the Dark Ages
is something that emerged mostly in the Renaissance, when
people in the 14th, well, 15th, 16th century
tried to present themselves as going back
to the classical age of the scholarship of ancient Greece
and Rome, and as being better than their predecessor
for the last few years.
This mostly happened because of discovery of manuscripts
that were translated from the ancient Greek,
and in certain cases, Latin, by Muslims, who at the time
were sort of receding from Europe.
So the entire concept of the Middle Ages
might be a fabrication of the Renaissance.
There were some significant discoveries at the time.
That's a nice idea.
In other words, when was St. Patrick?
St. Patrick.
I'm told that he popularized a lot of technical manuscripts,
brought them back into Europe.
He has two achievements.
One was bringing scientific culture back,
and the other was getting snakes out of England or something.
Ireland.
I don't know which he was sainted for.
Don't you have to do three miracles, or is it?
Yeah.
My theory is the Middle Ages ended around 2100.
After the Middle Ages ended, they'll say,
those guys back in the 21st century,
they had no idea how thinking worked.
They couldn't even think of a few ways to think.
They had poverty.
They had wars.
Those guys were barely out of their mind class.
Right.
I just read a history of AI.
I forget who wrote it.
But it had this section saying, it mentioned the Newell Simon.
There was a thing called general problem solver,
which I mentioned a couple of times in the book.
And it's the idea that the way to solve a problem is to find
it's a symbolic servo.
Find the difference between what you have and what you want,
and look in your memory for something
that can reduce that difference.
Keep doing that.
And of course, it's important to pay attention
to the more important differences first and so forth.
And I'll send you this article.
This article is saying that they made a terrible mistake,
and this was a trivial theory.
And that's why nobody uses it anymore.
And it was interesting how many AI people fell
for that idea in the 1960s.
My complaint has been that if you look in a modern textbook
on, you must have some in your first volume, Pat.
Didn't you have some GPS things?
If you want to keep up with AI, you
should read Patrick's textbook, even though people
are starting to use this new one, which
doesn't have any AI in it.
Who's it by?
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2, AUDIENCE MEMBER 3,
Russell and Norvig.
It's probably pretty good, technically.
But I leafed through it, and it didn't have any.
Never mind.
It's probably better than I think, because I'm jealous.
Yes.
Kind of a different topic.
In Society of Mind, you were talking
about the amnesia of infancy when you forget what you learned
and things that were once difficult become common sense,
and you can't even remember how it was different then.
So it's just been wondering about the reverse
of that process, when you try and say,
teach something to somebody that you internalize as people,
that you're quick to understand and bringing back up
the different levels.
I'm not exactly sure if there's a question to it.
It's just kind of quite fun, and wondering about,
is that itself another way of re-learning the things
that you learned?
That's sure an interesting question.
When I first learned about programming,
I had the idea that maybe babies think in machine language,
and then after a while, they start to think in Fortran.
And then finally, when they're a little older,
they think in Algol or something.
But when they switch from machine language to Fortran,
then they can't remember their earlier thoughts.
And there's almost no evidence of people
finding genuine recollections from two-year-olds
at later ages.
Now, almost everybody thinks they remember something,
but there's the problem that you might have rehearsed it
and translated it into the Fortran, and the Algol,
and the Lisp, and the logo, whatever it is.
One of my greatest influences was a great mathematician
named Andrew Gleason at Harvard, who I met practically
the first day I got to Harvard.
And he would always talk about things I didn't understand,
and I would go home and look them up and try to.
Anyway, one day, we were talking about number forms.
And number forms are a psychological phenomenon
which about 30% of people have, and it was first
described by Francis Galton.
And the phenomenon is, if I ask you, close your eyes
and tell me where is the number 3, how many of you
have a place for the number 3?
Well, that's a few.
And so typically, if you imagine the visual field,
it's a windshield, I guess.
So there are these numbers, and they're
nowhere in particular, except that it's usually
like that for an older child.
So here are these numbers.
And what's more, in some people, they're colored.
So I was talking to Andrew.
I had read this Galton paper, which
is 1890 or 1885 or something.
And so I was asking people if they had number forms.
And he said, oh, yes, he has one.
And he sketched it for me.
And he said, and they're colored, too.
Oh, and his went way up.
And the prime numbers were bright.
What am I doing?
Maybe the composite numbers were something was bright,
and they were colored.
So I wrote this down, and over the next couple of years,
I look in antique stores for old children's blocks,
and I found a set of blocks that matched that.
And Andrew Gleason said that he knows
when he acquired this thing.
And it was about four years old.
And he had a window in his house, and there was a hill.
And he could just see over the sill,
and he imagined these numbers on the side of that hill.
Blah, blah, blah.
Anyway, people who don't have a number form
don't know what I'm talking about.
And I don't know if the 30% is still true,
but it's an interesting phenomenon.
And in most cases of early childhood,
you can't find out because children do remember
details of a house they lived in,
but you don't know if they've copied it.
So what was the original question?
How much can you remember from infancy?
L. Rand Hubbard thought you could go back
to before you were born, and you could
remember people talking about you
when you're still in the womb.
So anyway, John Campbell said you should look into this.
And a few of us made an expedition.
We went down to Elizabeth, New Jersey
to visit the just starting up Dianetics Center.
And I met this L. Rand Hubbard, who had green eyes
and was quite hypnotic looking.
And the end of the story is he had
been writing about how if you took
this treatment of Dianetics, then you
could memorize an entire newspaper in five minutes
and do all sorts of miraculous things like that
once your mind has been cleared of aberrations and obstacles.
And it became a big industry and turned into later Scientology.
I'm sure you've all heard about that.
So we asked Hubbard to look at a newspaper
and tell us what was in it.
And he explained he was so busy training the other people
to be cleared that he hadn't had time
to go through the procedure himself.
And I never saw him again.
Yes?
What are your thoughts on memes and the fact
that we're just replicas or our thoughts are actually
all replicas of something different?
Of memes?
Just using the blackboard.
You mean Dawkins?
I didn't quite get the whole question.
The idea that, uh.
Oh, so memes, so for example, the way we talk
and the way we all talk, how we very much
remix the way our parents talked for people around us
and possibly the way we think as well.
So how does that relate to how our mind develops?
Or are we actually creative original characters?
Or are we not at all?
Well, of course, it's both because you learn things
from your culture.
And then you might just mainly repeat things,
or you might get the knack of making new ideas.
I'm trying to remember what Dawkins' main ideas are.
He invented the word meme to say that the ideas that people have
might be considered to be somewhat similar to the genes
in our heredity, and that societies
are systems in which these memes, which
are conceptual units of meaning or knowledge,
propagate around and self-reproduce and mutate
and spread.
And I don't know what to say about it,
except that it's obviously true that every now and then
someone gets a new idea and tells people,
and for one reason or another, they either forget it
or tell someone else.
And after a while, it spreads, and some of them
fill up the whole culture, and some just die out.
And whatever else Dawkins says, he's a very smart guy,
but almost everything, then, in my mind,
is that he's explaining that religions are mostly
made of these memes, and they're very bad
and cost the world a great deal in progress and productivity.
In other words, he's a militant atheist,
and there are about five best sellers in that business today.
But I don't know what else to say about memes.
It's an obviously generally correct idea.
But the great thing about genes is
we know the four amino acids or four nucleic acids
they're made of and how they're roped together and all that.
And I don't think Dawkins' theory develops anywhere nearly
as elegantly as modern genetics.
So it would be nice if it could, but a really good theory
of good ideas would be nice to have.
What would it look like?
Someday, we'll have an AI that just punches them out.
I think it would include a really good language.
Oh, right.
Robert Heinlein has some stories in which
the super-intelligent people have a language that's
so dense that in five syllables, they
can explain something that would take you a half hour.
I think I forget what it's log land.
Maybe.
Anyway, if you need a good idea, read Robert Heinlein.
Sure.
I forgot where you mentioned this,
where you talked about how geniuses,
they might have just come up with better ways
to think better, better ways to learn.
Yes.
About how to better meta-meta learning.
But why do you think they never learned that?
And why hasn't they propagated that method
of better learning about how better to learn?
That's a great question.
And do you think it's just we don't
have a concept of an idea that improves better learning?
There's a couple of phenomena that,
how come there were so many geniuses in Athens?
And then some of the best mathematicians
came from some high school in some little country
next to the Baltic.
Bulgaria?
Romania.
Yes, there was some high school in Romania
that not only produced von Neumann,
but about five or six other world class mathematicians.
I don't remember the details.
So that's a nice question.
How come if there are these great memes,
how come there aren't more big pockets of them?
But there are a lot of cultures which were very inventive
in other than intellectual fields.
How come Paris got all those artists in the?
How many of you saw the Woody Allen movie?
What's it called?
Paris at Midnight?
So funny.
Like, if you're able to take on one,
then one idea that will improve your improvement of your life.
Right.
That's a good question for each of us.
What's your very best idea?
And stop fussing with the other ones and get that one out.
There must be some people who are very quiet
and only speak once in a long time.
We should watch them carefully.
Yes?
I guess along with mine, do you ever
feel restricted by language because everybody didn't have it?
Wait.
It's the sound.
I can't hear it.
Is that strong enough to lift you?
I'm sure someone's done it.
Sorry about that.
Do you ever feel restricted by language
and that you must represent your theory of mind
or any theory or idea with language?
No, I don't.
But I once was jealous when Papert explained
that he got some idea.
And he explained he gets ideas like that
when he thinks in French.
Well, you draw pictures, too.
What?
You draw pictures, too.
Oh, yeah.
So it's not just language.
That's a language.
Graphics.
So we ought to have devices within the next few years
that draw pictures when you think.
It's so funny.
We had cyborgs.
What were they called?
I mentioned them last time.
We had Steve Mann.
And who's the other one?
Yeah.
So there's these two guys around the Media Lab
wearing various things on their head.
And they're always typing.
And you ask them a question, and they've searched Google.
When was that?
1990?
1995, I think.
But it's all gone.
Nobody walks around with direct connection to the web.
Well, Steve Mann's still best.
Yes.
Anyway, I certainly expected it to turn up,
and something wrong.
So anyway, you should be able to buy one one of these days.
And what's your name?
Who was that nice woman who had the EEG thing?
Do you remember at TED?
Forgot her name.
Anyway, she had this sort of helmet
which had about 20 electrodes.
And she induced me to put it on a stage
with about 1,000 people there, which was rather funny.
And there's a little spot on the CRT.
And I get to think about it moving one way or the other
and rewarding it when it did the right thing for only about half
a minute.
And then I could steer it around.
So here was a nice primitive gadget
where you could sort of almost draw just by thinking
this spot.
01:32:02,420 -
and who's the copy.
Frederick Pohl wrote a similar story much longer ago
where people are copied and the copy is sent on a one-way trip
to some planet to fix a broken reactor.
And they always die, and you get a million dollars
for providing this copy.
But one of the copies survived, so it's the same plot.
I can't remember the.
If you're looking for a good idea,
if you go to 1950s science fiction,
look for A.E. van Vogt or Frederick
Pohl or all those wonderful writers,
that was before it was necessary to describe really good
characters.
And science fiction got better and better
for the literary critics and generally worse and worse
for the science fiction fans.
Do we really have any more questions?
Yes.
So we're in a time age where sharing information
between many people on a short amount of time
is quite easy to internet and anything like this.
Do you think that this will change?
This will bring up many more ideas?
Do you think that this will hinder?
Because before this time, people had problems
with sharing the information.
And also now it's not easy to have a large group of people
working on one thing.
Do you think that this will change the way that we think?
And do you think that this will make us better?
It's a tough one.
Bad things can happen, and good things can happen.
That's funny, because that reminds me again
of science fiction, because in science fiction, many, many
years ago, some writers got the idea
that there would be something like an internet.
And some people realized there would be flash crowds.
And now there are flash crowds.
And I remember even as a kid talking to people who said,
why not wire up the voting machines
so that they're always there?
And so if somebody in the government
wants to know, should we do this or that,
should we bomb China or not, you could get 100 million people
to run up to the keyboard and say yes or no.
And presumably when the, what do they
call that great crowd of Jeffersons and Franklins
and the Founding Fathers, did a lot of things to prevent that.
And the one that they focused on,
which was one of the most effective,
was called the Electoral College.
And the United States is different from other places
because we don't elect congressmen or presidents.
We elect smart people from the community
who then get together and decide who should be president.
And of course, now if anybody, now they belong to parties.
And if any of them voted for the other party's candidate,
they would be held to pay.
But it was a great idea because the Founding Fathers realized
that if you had instant feedback, which
Hitler got, then you could say something really exciting
and everybody would press the yes button.
And then you kill all the Jews.
And then the next speech, you kill all the black people
and all the yellow people and all the people
whose last name doesn't begin with M.
And so what you don't want is instant feedback.
Now, the new social networks are getting us close to that.
And the question is, is it time to have,
is it time to stop that?
Is it getting dangerous?
I don't know.
But there must be a lot of people
who are recognizing that this thing is creeping up on us.
And you might be able to get 50 million people to do something
reckless in a few minutes if you don't put some limits.
I don't think we could get the electoral college back
because you'd have to get a majority to.
What does it take to fix the Constitution?
2 thirds?
We'll never see 2 thirds again.
It's the end of America.
Well, we have three minutes.
Yes?
If you design a direction for the field of psychology,
obviously one where there's a set of debunking tools,
what would you say they should be doing?
They should read Patrick Winston's thesis.
The psychologists now have disappeared
into the tar pit of statistics.
And they don't have the idea that knowledge needs
complicated representations.
And I don't care whether you assign probabilities to them
or put them in the order in which you thought of them
or do what Doug Lennett did in his thesis of swapping things
when one worked better than another.
But I forget the question.
But I think we've got to get better ideas
about representation of knowledge.
And I don't know where they're going to come from now
that the whole AI community is drifting
into these ways of avoiding representations.
I haven't read the Norvig Russell book, so does he?
Can anybody summarize what it says about knowledge
representation?
Who's read it?
Was it?
There's a chapter on logic, first order logic.
That's so funny.
First order of logic is what Newell and Simon thought
of in 1956 before they thought of the so-called GPS thing.
Logic can't make analogies.
It's a very bad thing to get stuck with.
0 or 1?
Maybe one of our papers should be on what
should AI do next year?
9 o'clock.
Thanks for coming.
Thank you.